<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.11/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.11/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.11.xsd" version="0.11" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Giant Bomb Video Game Wiki</sitename>
    <dbname>wiki_db143</dbname>
    <base>https://giantbomb.com/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.43.6</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Gb</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Gb talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="102" case="first-letter">Property</namespace>
      <namespace key="103" case="first-letter">Property talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="106" case="first-letter">Form</namespace>
      <namespace key="107" case="first-letter">Form talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Concept</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Concept talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="112" case="first-letter">smw/schema</namespace>
      <namespace key="113" case="first-letter">smw/schema talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Platforms/Evercade</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>456738</id>
    <revision>
      <id>738576</id>
      <parentid>738517</parentid>
      <timestamp>2026-02-24T18:43:27Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Marino</username>
        <id>8</id>
      </contributor>
      <origin>738576</origin>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text bytes="12302" sha1="ed3s9w5tecybl2i6ed625u1t59ck6my" xml:space="preserve">{{Platform
|Name=Evercade
|Guid=3045-180
|Image=https://www.giantbomb.com/a/uploads/scale_super/0/1992/3134988-evercade-featured-graphic-with-cart.jpg
|Deck=Evercade is a range of consoles that plays officially licensed cartridge-based collections of retro 8-bit, 16-bit, 32-bit and 64-bit console games, arcade games and 8-bit and 16-bit home computer games.
|ShortName=EVER
|ReleaseDate=2020-05-22
|OnlineSupport=No
|OriginalPrice=79.99
|Manufacturer=Companies/Blaze_Retro
}}
&lt;div id='imageData' data-json='{"infobox":{"file":"3134988-evercade-featured-graphic-with-cart.jpg","path":"0\/1992\/","mime":"image\/jpeg","sizes":"scale_tiny,scale_super,square_small,scale_small,scale_medium,square_medium,square_tiny,square_mini,square_avatar,screen_medium,scale_large,screen_kubrick,scale_avatar","caption":""},"background":{"file":"3134989-front_on_hd.png","path":"0\/1992\/","mime":"image\/png","sizes":"scale_super,square_medium,screen_kubrick_wide,scale_medium,square_tiny,screen_medium,screen_kubrick,scale_small,square_mini,scale_avatar,scale_large,square_avatar","caption":""}}' /&gt;
Evercade is a platform focused on retro gaming that launched in 2020. Initially released as a handheld and subsequently expanding to TV-connected and bartop arcade form factors, the platform takes its own proprietary cartridges, each of which contains one or more officially licensed games.

==Evercade Handheld (2020)==
https://www.giantbomb.com/a/uploads/original/8/89400/3742296-evercade-arial-shot-1024x696-1.jpg The original Evercade handheld launched in May 2020 and was available in both "Starter" and "Premium" sets. The Starter package came with a single multi-game cartridge, while the Premium edition had three.
The handheld can be played by itself, or connected to a TV via a mini-HDMI to HDMI cable, which provides a 720p upscaled version of the interface and games.
Ten cartridges were available at launch: 
* [[Games/Atari_Collection_1|Atari Collection 1]]
* [[Games/Atari_Collection_2|Atari Collection 2]]
* [[Games/Data_East_Collection_1|Data East Collection 1]]
* [[Games/Interplay_Collection_1|Interplay Collection 1]]
* [[Games/Interplay_Collection_2|Interplay Collection 2]]
* [[Games/Mega_Cat_Studios_Collection_1|Mega Cat Studios Collection 1]]
* [[Games/Namco_Museum_Collection_1|Namco Museum Collection 1]]
* [[Games/Namco_Museum_Collection_2|Namco Museum Collection 2]]
* [[Games/Piko_Interactive_Collection_1|Piko Interactive Collection 1]]
* [[Games/Technos_Collection_1|Technos Collection 1]]
These cartridges consisted exclusively of 8-bit and 16-bit home console games originally released on [[Platforms/Atari_2600|Atari 2600]], [[Platforms/Atari_7800|Atari 7800]], [[Platforms/Nintendo_Entertainment_System|NES]], [[Platforms/Super_Nintendo_Entertainment_System|SNES]] and [[Platforms/Genesis|Mega Drive/Genesis]], and more were released gradually in the months following the handheld's release.
The original Evercade handheld is now discontinued, but new cartridge releases for the platform continue to support it.

==Evercade VS/VS-R (2021)==
https://www.giantbomb.com/a/uploads/original/8/89400/3742297-vs_homescene_retroheaven-1-1536x1016-1.jpg The Evercade VS is a retro gaming console that connects to a modern TV via HDMI, providing a 1080p picture. The console includes two cartridge slots to allow more games to be available to play at one time, and four controller ports, allowing for multiplayer gaming in titles that support it. Unlike the original handheld, the Evercade VS also features Wi-Fi connectivity, primarily used for over-the-air firmware updates.
The Evercade VS launched in November 2021 in Europe, though shipping delays meant that it was early 2022 before it was available to North American players. The console's launch coincided with the start of Evercade's range of arcade-centric cartridges, so the available bundles included cartridges from this selection. The Starter Pack included [[Games/Technos_Arcade_1|Technos Arcade 1]] and a single controller, while the Premium Pack included Technos Arcade 1, [[Games/Data_East_Arcade_1|Data East Arcade 1]] and two controllers. There was also a limited edition Founder Edition available exclusively during the pre-order period, which included a special black version of the console, some additional bonuses and 6 cartridges in total.
The Evercade VS uses more powerful hardware than the original Evercade handheld and also has more internal storage, allowing the firmware to have more features. Over time, a variety of new functions were added, including custom button mapping, screen rotation for [[Concepts/Tate_Mode|tate mode]] games, DIP switches for arcade games, mouse support, [[Concepts/Evercade_Game_of_the_Month|Game of the Month]] and more. There are also a number of built-in hidden games loaded into the console itself, accessible via secret passwords, button combinations or loading two particular cartridges into the system at the same time.
It is possible to connect the original Evercade handheld to the Evercade VS to use it as a controller, but this requires a specially designed USB cable.
The original Evercade VS was revamped into the Evercade VS-R in 2024, offering the same form factor with a new colour scheme and a lower price point. The VS-R was initially released with [[Games/Tomb_Raider_Collection_1|Tomb Raider Collection 1]] as the bundled game.

==Evercade EXP/EXP-R (2022)==
https://www.giantbomb.com/a/uploads/original/8/89400/3742298-evercade-exp-005-1-scaled-1.jpg The Evercade EXP is a retro gaming handheld designed to replace the original Evercade handheld and bring the handheld experience in line with what the VS offers. The unit also boasts a higher resolution and better quality screen than the original handheld, with a better viewing angle being the most obvious improvement, and also has two sets of shoulder buttons compared to the original handheld's single set. These were included due to the platform starting to play host to more 32-bit console games, primarily from the [[Platforms/PlayStation|PlayStation]].
Evercade EXP launched in December of 2022, but in the run-up to release, all stock of the limited edition black version of the console was [https://evercade.co.uk/important-annoucement-evercade-exp-limited-editon-units-stolen-in-robbery stolen during shipping to distributors]. Replacement systems were sent out to those who had pre-ordered the limited edition version, with [https://evercade.co.uk/evercade-exp-limited-edition-what-changes-were-made some changes made to the packaging] to distinguish the new batch from the original stolen batch. The standard edition white version released in December 2022 as originally intended.
Evercade EXP was available in two bundles: the aforementioned limited edition came with the [[Games/Irem_Arcade_1|Irem Arcade 1]] and [[Games/Toaplan_Arcade_1|Toaplan Arcade 1]] cartridges, while the standard edition came with just Irem Arcade 1. Both editions of the console also featured a pre-loaded selection of built-in Capcom games, including a selection of arcade titles as well as the console versions of [[Games/Mega_Man|Mega Man]], [[Games/Mega_Man_X|Mega Man X]] and [[Games/Breath_of_Fire|Breath of Fire]].
Evercade EXP offers all the same features as Evercade VS, except the dual cartridge slots. Firmware updates over time have added new features such as custom control mapping, DIP switches for arcade games, Game of the Month and more. At launch, Evercade EXP's unique selling point was a tate mode button that would immediately rotate the screen through 90 degrees to play vertically oriented arcade games. This feature was subsequently added as a menu setting for Evercade VS via a firmware update.
The Evercade EXP was refreshed into the Evercade EXP-R in 2024, offering the same form factor with a new colour scheme and a lower price point, but without the built-in Capcom games. The EXP-R was initially released with Tomb Raider Collection 1 as the bundled game.

==Evercade Alpha (2024)==
https://www.giantbomb.com/a/uploads/original/8/89400/3742300-alpha-pair-02.png Evercade Alpha is an all-in-one bartop arcade unit that includes an 8" IPS display with a 4:3 aspect ratio, a selection of built-in games and dual cartridge slots, allowing all Evercade cartridges to be played using either the built-in arcade controls or controllers connected via USB.
Evercade Alpha was first released in November of 2024 with two variants: a Street Fighter edition which includes [[Games/Street_Fighter_II_Champion_Edition|Street Fighter II Champion Edition]], [[Games/Super_Street_Fighter_II_Turbo|Super Street Fighter II Turbo]], [[Games/Street_Fighter_Alpha_Warriors_Dreams|Street Fighter Alpha]], [[Games/Street_Fighter_Alpha_2|Street Fighter Alpha 2]], [[Games/Street_Fighter_Alpha_3|Street Fighter Alpha 3]] and [[Games/Super_Puzzle_Fighter_II_Turbo|Super Puzzle Fighter II Turbo]] as its built-in games; and a Mega Man edition, which includes [[Games/Mega_Man_The_Power_Battle|Mega Man: The Power Battle]], [[Games/Mega_Man_2_The_Power_Fighters|Mega Man 2: The Power Fighters]], [[Games/Carrier_Air_Wing|Carrier Air Wing]], [[Games/Final_Fight|Final Fight]], [[Games/Strider_1989|Strider]] and [[Games/Knights_of_the_Round|Knights of the Round]] as its built-in titles. Both were available in regular and deluxe editions, with the latter featuring authentic Sanwa parts for the arcade controls, plus additional swappable marquee art for the light-up panel at the top of the unit.
Evercade Alpha offers all the same features as Evercade VS/VS-R and EXP/EXP-R, and once again firmware updates over time have added a variety of new features.

==HyperMegaTech! Super Pocket==
While not strictly speaking an "Evercade" product, and lacking many of the firmware features of the VS/VS-R, EXP/EXP-R and Alpha, the low-cost HyperMegaTech! Super Pocket range of handhelds, also by Evercade creator Blaze Entertainment, include a selection of built-in games as well as an Evercade cartridge slot. All currently available and announced Evercade cartridges also work on these devices.

==Evercade cartridges==
https://www.giantbomb.com/a/uploads/original/8/89400/3742301-blaze48541.jpg Evercade cartridges are a proprietary design intended specifically for use in Evercade and HyperMegaTech! Super Pocket devices. They include at least one game, accessible via the device's firmware menu. Games on Evercade cartridges run the gamut from officially licensed retro games to modern indie games developed for classic platforms or natively for Evercade.
Retro games are played via emulation and support save states, multiple scaling modes and scanline filters. Native releases are specifically programmed for Evercade and thus do not include the emulation features. Native releases to date include [[Games/Donut_Dodo|Donut Dodo]] (Indie Heroes Collection 3), Bubble Seahorse Adventures (Indie Heroes Collection 3), Full Void and Murtop.
They are available in three distinct, individually numbered ranges: red cartridges primarily include games originally released on home consoles; purple cartridges primarily include games that were originally arcade machines; blue cartridges primarily include games that were originally released on home computers such as the [[Platforms/Commodore_64|Commodore 64]] and [[Platforms/Amiga|Amiga]]. All cartridges come in a plastic clamshell case with an inlay and full-colour manual, with occasional bonus extras.
Sometimes individual titles on a cartridge do not match the colour scheme but otherwise fit into the overall "theme" of the collection; for example, Delphine Software Collection 1, a blue "home computer" cartridge, includes the Mega Drive/Genesis version of [[Games/Flashback_The_Quest_for_Identity|Flashback]], and The Bitmap Brothers Collection 2, also a blue cartridge, includes the PlayStation version of [[Games/Z|Z]].
In 2024, Blaze launched the "Giga Cart" range of cartridges for Evercade, which allowed larger-scale games (primarily CD-based 32-bit titles) to be included on a single cartridge. The first releases to bear this label were Tomb Raider Collection 1 and [[Games/Legacy_of_Kain_Collection|Legacy of Kain Collection]].
On Evercade VS/VS-R and Alpha, inserting two cartridges in specific combinations can sometimes unlock additional hidden games.</text>
      <sha1>ed3s9w5tecybl2i6ed625u1t59ck6my</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>Platforms/FM 7</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>456675</id>
    <revision>
      <id>797232</id>
      <parentid>752627</parentid>
      <timestamp>2026-03-21T01:03:20Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Frobie</username>
        <id>300</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>Undo revision [[Special:Diff/752627|752627]] by [[Special:Contributions/Giantbomb|Giantbomb]] ([[User talk:Giantbomb|talk]])</comment>
      <origin>797232</origin>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text bytes="4945" sha1="5ebtt6xyyar9p2m109gmr9nwlb9w28b" xml:space="preserve">{{Platform
|Name=FM-7
|Guid=3045-114
|Aliases=Fujitsu Micro 7
|Image=https://www.giantbomb.com/a/uploads/scale_super/0/4/1151387-fm7ad.jpg
|Deck=The second in Fujitsu's FM line of computers, the FM-7 was intended more for the mass market, and received fair popularity in Japan.
|ShortName=FM7
|ReleaseDate=November 1982
|ReleaseDateType=Month
|InstallBase=220,000
|OnlineSupport=No
|OriginalPrice=500.00
|Manufacturer=Companies/Fujitsu
}}


==Overview==
http://www.giantbomb.com/a/uploads/original/0/7465/2115655-fm7demo.gif The FM-7, an acronym for "Fujitsu Micro 7," was the second home computer released by the Japanese computing company [[Companies/Fujitsu|Fujitsu]]. It was released in Japan in November 1982, for ¥126,000 ($500 in 1982 dollars, or $1200 in 2013 dollars). Alongside the [[Platforms/Sharp_X1|Sharp X1]] and [[Platforms/NEC_PC_8801|NEC PC-8801]], it was considered to be one of the big three Japanese personal computers of the early 1980s.
The most notable model for computer gaming was the FM-77 AV, which in 1985 introduced a simultaneous display of 4096 colors, surpassing the 8 color display of other 8-bit home computers at the time.
The FM-7 was released almost simultanously with the FM-11 EX (intended for businesses), and was preceded by the FM-8 (Fujitsu's first home computer release). Fujitsu were also later responsible for the [[Platforms/FM_Towns|FM Towns]], the powerful 32-bit successor to the FM-7.
The FM-7 was similar to Radio Shack's [[Platforms/TRS_80_CoCo|TRS-80 Color Computer]] (colloquially referred to as the "CoCo") in some ways, especially CPU processor (both used the 8-bit Motorola 6809) and included features. One such feature is F-BASIC, very similar to the CoCo's "[[Companies/Xbox_Game_Studios|Microsoft]] CoCo BASIC." F-BASIC is essentially a simplistic programming language, including a katakana and kanji character set, graphics manipulation, and music.

==Model Variants==
There were several different versions of the FM-7 released following the initial release in 1982, including the FM-New 7 and FM-77.
A major breakthrough for computer gaming came in 1985, with the release of the FM-77 AV, the first computer model to break the 8-color barrier of 8-bit computers and achieve a simultaneous display of 4096 colors. In addition, the FM-77 AV also came with a built-in Yamaha FM synthesis sound board, providing higher-quality audio.
FM-7 models included:
* http://www.giantbomb.com/a/uploads/original/0/7465/2115658-fujitsu_77av3c_1.jpg  FM-New 7 (1984)
* FM-77 (1984)
* FM-77 L2 (1985)
* FM-77 L4 (1985)
* FM-77 AV (1985)
* FM-77 AV20 (1986)
* FM-77 AV40 (1986)
* FM-77 AV20 EX (1987)
* FM-77 AV40 EX (1987)
* FM-77 AV40 SX (1988)

==Technical Specifications==

===Processors===
* '''Main CPU (Central Processing Unit) processor''': * 1982: Fujitsu MBL 68B09 (based on 8-bit Motorola 68B09) @ 4.9 - 8 MHz
* 1984: Fujitsu MBL 68B09 (based on 8-bit Motorola 68B09) @ 8 MHz
* 1985: Fujitsu MBL 68B09E (8-bit) @ 2 MHz (equivalent to MBL 68B09 @ 8 MHz)
* '''GPU (Graphics Processing Unit) processor''': * 1982: Fujitsu MBL 68B09 (based on 8-bit Motorola 68B09) @ 2 MHz
* 1984: Fujitsu MBL 68B09E (8-bit) @ 2 MHz
* 1985: Fujitsu MMR (Memory Mapping Register), Fujitsu MBL 68B09E (8-bit) @ 2 MHz
* '''Optional CPU processor''': Zilog Z80 (8-bit)

===Memory===
* '''Main RAM (Random Access Memory)'''* 1982: 64 KB
* 1984: 64-256 KB
* 1985: 128-256 KB
* 1986: 128 KB / 192 KB / 448 KB
* '''Video RAM (VRAM) memory''': * 1982: 48 KB
* 1985: 96 KB
* 1986: 96-144 KB
* 1987: 96-192 KB
* 1988: 192 KB
* ''''''ROM (Read-Only Memory) memory'''''': 48 KB (1982), 72 KB (1985)
* '''Storage''': * Default: 10-20 MB hard disk drive (1982), 1x-2x 3.5" DD floppy disk drives (1984)
* Optional: Cassette tape, 5.25" floppy disk
* 3.5" DD (double-density) floppy disks: 320 KB each (1984), 640 KB each (1986)

===Display===
* '''Maximum display resolution''': 640x200 pixels (1982), 640x400 pixels (1984)
* ''''''Maximum color palette'''''': 8 (1982), 16 (1984), 4096 (1985), 262,144 (1986)
* '''Simultaneous display colors''': * 1982: 3 colors (monochrome), 8 colors (4-bit color)
* 1984: 8 colors at 640x200, 2 colors at 640x400
* 1985: 4096 colors at 320x200, 16 colors at 640x200, 2 colors at 640x400
* 1986: 4096 colors at 320x200, 16 colors at 640x200, 8 colors at 640x400
* 1987: 4096 colors at 320x200, 32 colors at 640x200, 16 colors at 640x400
* '''Monitors''': [[Concepts/Multi_Monitor_Support|Multi-monitor support]] for 2-6 monitors (1985)
* '''Video digitization''': Supported (1985), Standard (1988)

===Sound===
* 1982: General Instruments AY-3-8910 sound chip (PSG synthesizer, 3 channels, 8 octaves)
* 1985: Yamaha sound board (FM synthesis, 3 channels), AY-3-8910 sound chip

===Interface===
* '''Interface''': Tape, RGB, RS232, Joystick (2), ROM/RAM cartridges, BUS

==External link==
* [http://museum.ipsj.or.jp/en/computer/personal/0017.html IPSJ Computer Museum article on FM-77 AV]</text>
      <sha1>5ebtt6xyyar9p2m109gmr9nwlb9w28b</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>Platforms/FM Towns</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>456669</id>
    <revision>
      <id>797227</id>
      <parentid>752622</parentid>
      <timestamp>2026-03-21T01:02:20Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Frobie</username>
        <id>300</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>Undo revision [[Special:Diff/752622|752622]] by [[Special:Contributions/Giantbomb|Giantbomb]] ([[User talk:Giantbomb|talk]])</comment>
      <origin>797227</origin>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text bytes="8025" sha1="jwh054nqq0m9dbvhd2hzsrk2ht4euu2" xml:space="preserve">{{Platform
|Name=FM Towns
|Guid=3045-108
|Aliases=FM Towns Marty
|Image=https://www.giantbomb.com/a/uploads/scale_super/0/4527/1109993-fmtowns.jpg
|Deck=A proprietary 32-bit computer from Fujitsu, released in 1989 only in Japan. The first computer with a standard CD-ROM drive, it had many CD enhanced versions of Eastern and Western games (including action, adventure and RPG titles) which are sought after to this day by collectors. Its console version, FM Towns Marty, released in 1993 as the first 5th-gen console.
|ShortName=FMT
|ReleaseDate=1989-02-28
|ReleaseDateType=Month
|InstallBase=500,000
|OnlineSupport=No
|OriginalPrice=3000.00
|Manufacturer=Companies/Fujitsu
}}
==Overview==
FM Towns is a proprietary 32-bit computer system manufactured by [[Companies/Fujitsu|Fujitsu]]. It was released in [[Locations/Japan|Japan]] only, in February 1989, as the successor to the [[Platforms/FM_7|FM-7]] computer platform. The FM Towns had a launch price of ¥400,000 (over $3000 in 1989 dollars, equivalent to nearly $6000 in 2013 dollars). While it was never officially released outside Japan, imports of the FM Towns were available, particularly in the [[Locations/United_Kingdom|UK]]. When it first released, the FM Towns was one of the most advanced [[Platforms/PC|PC]] platforms released up until then, rivalled only by the [[Platforms/Sharp_X68000|Sharp X68000]].

==Overview==
FM Towns was considerably advanced for its time. At launch in 1989, it was using a 32-bit Intel 80386DX CPU (later upgraded to Pentium CPU in early 90's), supported 24-bit colour which could display up to 16.78 million colours, featured high-resolution display modes up to 1024x1024 pixels, and featured the unique ability to overlay two different display modes.
It has a built in [[Objects/Compact_Disc|CD-ROM]] drive as standard, which was many years ahead of its time. Also ahead of its time was its ability to boot directly to a CD version of its operating system, TownsOS. This was a full 8 years before Microsoft thought of doing the same thing. As well as being able to run the TownsOS graphical user interface, it had versions of Windows 3, 3.1 and Windows 95 as they became available.
Games were a strong point of the system as they could be greatly enhanced by the startlingly increased capacity of CDs over floppy discs.
Games were usually enhanced in one or more of the following ways:
* Near [[Platforms/Arcade|arcade]]-quality ports, instead of inferior conversions on other home systems (with the exception of the [[Platforms/Sharp_X68000|Sharp X68000]] computer and [[Platforms/Neo_Geo|Neo Geo]] console). At release, it was a very powerful system.
* Containing [[Concepts/Voice_Acting|voiced]] speech and [[Concepts/Full_Motion_Video|full-motion video]] [[Concepts/Cutscene|cutscenes]], which was almost impossible on floppy and cartridge based systems.
* '[[Concepts/Redbook_Audio|Redbook]]' CD music [[Concepts/Original_Soundtrack_Release|soundtracks]], i.e. proper, non synthesised music that you can play on any CD player.
As the system grew older, while IBM-compatible [[Platforms/PC|PC]]'s caught up, the versions of games became identical. For example, [[Franchises/Wing_Commander|Wing Commander Origins]] in 1993 was identical on PC and FM Towns. Considering the system had been out for 4 years, that was impressive.
In the Western world, the system is perhaps best known for having many CD enhanced ports or [[Concepts/Remake|remakes]] (with improved graphics, audio, and interface) of classic Western RPG's and adventure games, such as the [[Franchises/Ultima|Ultima]]series and [[Companies/LucasArts_Entertainment_Company_LLC|LucasArts]] games, for example. The FM Towns versions are sometimes considered the best versions of these games.

==Technical specifications==

===Main processors===
* Main CPU: * 1989: Intel 80386DX (32-bit) @ 16 MHz
* 1993: Intel i486DX @ 33-66 MHz / Intel i486SX @ 25 MHz
* 1994: Intel i486DX @ 33-66 MHz / Intel i486SX @ 33 MHz
* 1995: Intel Pentium @ 90-120 MHz
* Upgradable CPU: * 1993: Intel OverDrive @ 66-100 MHz
* 1994: Intel Pentium @ 75-120 MHz / 486DX4 @ 75-100 MHz
* 1995: Intel Pentium @ 120-133 MHz
* 1996: Intel Pentium @ 133-200 MHz
* FPU (floating point unit) arithmetic co-processor: Intel 80387 @ 16 MHz

===Operating systems===
* Default: Towns OS (1989), Towns OS 2.1 (1995)
* Supported: DOS/V (1990), Windows 3.1 (1992), Windows 95 (1995)

===Memory===
* Main RAM (Random Access Memory) * Default: 1-2 MB (1989), 4 MB (1993), 6 MB (1994), 8-16 MB (1995)
* Upgradable: 10 MB (1989), 64 MB (1993), 128 MB (1995)
* Video RAM (VRAM) memory: 656 KB * Main VRAM: 512 KB
* Sprite RAM: 128 KB (1024 sprites)
* Text RAM: 16 KB
* Storage: CD-ROM (540 MB), 2x 3.5" floppy disk (1.2 MB) drives, hard disk drive * Optional storage: 5.25" floppy disk drive, hard disk drive
* CD-ROM drive speed: 1x (1989), 2x (1993), 4x (1995)
* Hard disk drive: * Default: 20-40 MB (1989), 170-340 MB (1993), 850 MB (1995)
* Upgradable: 45 MB (1989), 3.2 GB (1997)

===Display===
* Display resolutions: 256x256, 320x240, 352x232, 360x240, 640x400, 640x480, 1024x768, 1024x1024, 1120x750
* Colour palette: * 12-bit (4096 colours) @ 640x480 / 640x400 (2 planes)
* 15-bit (32,768 colours) @ 320x240 (2 planes)
* 24-bit (16.78 million colours) @ 640x480 (1 plane)
* Simultaneous colours: * 1989: * 4-bit (16 colours) @ 1024x1024 / 1120x750 (1 plane)
* 4-bit (16 colours) @ 640x480 / 640x400 (2 planes)
* 8-bit (256 colours) @ 640x480 (1 plane)
* 15-bit (32,768 colours) @ 320x240 (1 plane)
* 1994: 15-bit (32,768 colours) to 24-bit (16.78 million colours)
* Sprites: Up to 1024 sprites @ 16x16 pixels each

===Audio===
* CD audio: 16-bit sampling @ 44.1 KHz, [[Concepts/Redbook_Audio|Redbook]] audio
* FM synthesis audio: Yamaha YM2612 sound chip, 6-channel stereo
* PCM audio: * 1989: Ricoh RF5c68 sound chip, 8-channel stereo, 8-bit sampling @ 19.2 Hz
* 1994: 16-bit sampling @ 48 KHz, stereo
* Optional sound card: Creative Sound Blaster AWE32 (1994)

===Other specifications===
* Input: Keyboard, mouse, gamepad, joystick
* Other options: Video card, microphone, [[Concepts/Online|modem]], SCSI card, VGA card, [[Concepts/Multi_Monitor_Support|dual-monitor support]]

==History==
The FM Towns' main 16/32-bit rivals in the Japanese computer market were [[Companies/NEC_Home_Electronics_Ltd|NEC]]'s [[Platforms/NEC_PC_9801|PC-98]] (launched 1982) and [[Companies/Sharp_Corporation|Sharp]]'s [[Platforms/Sharp_X68000|X68000]] (launched 1987). The FM Towns had the best audio quality and multimedia capabilities upon release, and was second only to the X68000 in terms of power and graphical capabilities.
Despite this, the NEC PC-98 remained the market leader in Japan up until the mid-1990s, when the arrival of Windows 95 on [[Platforms/PC|IBM-compatible PC]]'s slowly began gaining rivalling the local Japanese competition around the late 1990s. Despite FM Towns supporting Windows 95, IBM-compatible PC's slowly came to dominate the Japanese computer market by the early 2000s. The mid-1990s is thus often seen as the end of the 'Golden Age' of Japanese computer gaming.
In 1993, Fujitsu released the a console version of the FM Towns called the FM Towns Marty, the first 32-bit console, beginning the fifth-generation of consoles in Japan a year before the launch of [[Companies/Sega|Sega]]'s [[Platforms/Saturn|Saturn]]and [[Companies/Sony_Interactive_Entertainment|Sony]]'s [[Platforms/PlayStation|PlayStation]]. A variant called the FM Towns Marty 2 was released the following year in 1994 that featured a darker grey shell and a lower price point but was otherwise the same as the original FM Towns Marty. The FM Towns Marty was also backwards compatible with FM Towns games.  

==External link==
* [http://archive.org/stream/ace-magazine-27/ACE_Issue_27_1989_Dec#page/n27/mode/2up ACE Magazine, Issue 27, article on FM Towns]
* [http://museum.ipsj.or.jp/en/computer/personal/index.html IPSJ Computer Museum]
* [http://www.old-computers.com/museum/doc.asp?c=968 Old Computers article]</text>
      <sha1>jwh054nqq0m9dbvhd2hzsrk2ht4euu2</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>Platforms/Famicom Disk System</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>456653</id>
    <revision>
      <id>797226</id>
      <parentid>752615</parentid>
      <timestamp>2026-03-21T01:01:32Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Frobie</username>
        <id>300</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>Undo revision [[Special:Diff/752615|752615]] by [[Special:Contributions/Giantbomb|Giantbomb]] ([[User talk:Giantbomb|talk]])</comment>
      <origin>797226</origin>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text bytes="6068" sha1="mgmp4tkg6ir75qzko69bm12d2773zww" xml:space="preserve">{{Platform
|Name=Famicom Disk System
|Guid=3045-91
|Aliases=Famicom Disc System,Twin Famicom
|Image=https://www.giantbomb.com/a/uploads/scale_super/0/26/10341-fds.jpg
|Deck=The Famicom Disk System was an add-on accessory for the Nintendo Entertainment System's Japanese counterpart. With its games coming on a floppy disk-like medium, many of its releases saw conversions to cartridges both overseas and within Japan.
|ShortName=FDS
|ReleaseDate=1986-02-21
|ReleaseDateType=Month
|InstallBase=4,400,000
|OnlineSupport=No
|OriginalPrice=80
|Manufacturer=Companies/Nintendo
}}
==Overview==
http://www.giantbomb.com/a/uploads/original/0/429/526431-disk_kun1986.png The Famicom Disk System was part of a line of add-on systems produced exclusively in [[Locations/Japan|Japan]] for its version of the [[Platforms/Nintendo_Entertainment_System|Nintendo Entertainment System]] called the Famicom. Its claim to fame was that its games were released on a medium similar to floppy disks. The disks, having two sides, originally contained more space than what a Famicom cartridge was capable of holding. They were also much cheaper to produce, a characteristic meant to lure developers to the platform. The Famicom also features a microphone in the controller, which certain games used, such as an updated version of the original Zelda. Despite the Disk System's moderate success, the majority of the Famicom's library still remained in cartridge form exclusively. Nevertheless, several of Nintendo's series were started on the Famicom Disk System and later entries in the series were available on more mainstream Nintendo platforms.

==The Disk==
http://www.giantbomb.com/a/uploads/original/0/4527/1751015-1.jpg The Famicom Disk System's games contained internal features impossible to replicate on cartridges. The most notable of these features was their rewriting capability. Aside from being applied to conventional tasks, such as saving progress, certain disks could also have their games entirely overwritten for a small fee.
The disks themselves were either a yellow or blue color and have the word Nintendo etched in at the bottom, with the blue version containing a shutter, whereas the yellow does not. Most disks have stickers on both sides that contain the title of the game as well as a large "A" or "B" (alternatively "Side A" or "Side B") on the left side of the sticker which tells the player the side of the disk. Typically the player needs to put Side A in first to boot up the game and once they start a game or load a saved file a message will appear on the screen telling the player to switch sides. At this point the player needs to eject the disk and flip it over to side B to start the game. Some disks are one sided meaning side B is blank and doesn't have a sticker on it. Games that have a blank side B do not need to be flipped over at any point.

==Sharp Twin Famicom==
http://www.giantbomb.com/a/uploads/original/0/4527/1757570-1.jpg Sharp Corporation released the Twin Famicom in Japan on July 1, 1986, less than five months after the release of the Famicom Disk System. The Twin Famicom combines the Famicom and Famicom Disk System into one system and is officially licensed by Nintendo. The system has a switch just below the cartridge slot that allows the player to switch between using the Disk System or the Famicom. When switched to the Disk System the cartridge slot locks to prevent players from attempting to use both slots at the same time. Similarly, if switched to the Famicom the Disk System slot locks for the same reason.
The original release of the system came in two different colors red with black highlights or black with red highlights. There was also a re-release that came in a slightly different case design, turbo controllers, and two new sets of color schemes. The first color scheme is black with green highlights and the second is red with blue and gray highlights.

==Overseas Conversions==
Because Nintendo opted to not distribute the Famicom Disk System outside of Japan, all of its games which received international releases required technical modifications so that they could function on regular cartridges. Ultimately few of these games retained their ability to save games due to the costs of incorporating batteries into the cartridges. ( [[Games/The_Legend_of_Zelda|The Legend of Zelda]] is one exception, as it still employed battery-backed saving.) Instead, many games, such as [[Games/Metroid|Metroid]], employed [[Concepts/Password|passwords]] to record players' progress.
http://www.giantbomb.com/a/uploads/original/0/429/526527-dokidoki1.png The American version of [[Games/Super_Mario_Bros_2|Super Mario Bros. 2]], however, is the most famous of these conversions. Because the [[Games/Super_Mario_Bros_The_Lost_Levels|original sequel]] in Japan was deemed to be too difficult for most players at the time, Nintendo chose to bring over what was originally a completely different game instead and retrofit it as a [[Characters/Mario|Mario]] game. The game which was chosen to do this was [[Doki Doki Panic|Doki Doki Panic]], an Arabian-themed platformer which had been produced for a television station's special event. The protagonists in the game, a family, were replaced with [[Characters/Mario|Mario]], [[Characters/Luigi|Luigi]], [[Characters/Princess_Peach|Peach]], and [[Characters/Toad|Toad]]. Additional technical alterations were made in specific areas of the game, mostly pertaining to specific sprites' animations. Enemies which were part of Doki Doki Panic remained in the new version, with many of them, such as [[Characters/Birdo|Birdo]] and [[Objects/Bob_omb|Bob-omb]], appearing in subsequent Mario games afterwards. This rendition was later released in Japan as Super Mario USA.

==Series Originating on the Famicom Disk System==
http://www.giantbomb.com/a/uploads/original/0/4527/1757561-1.jpg * [[Franchises/The_Legend_of_Zelda|The Legend of Zelda]]
* [[Franchises/Metroid|Metroid]]
* [[Franchises/Castlevania|Castlevania]]
* [[Franchises/Famicom_Detective_Club|Famicom Detective Club]]</text>
      <sha1>mgmp4tkg6ir75qzko69bm12d2773zww</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>Platforms/Fuze Tomahawk F1</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>456723</id>
    <revision>
      <id>1008541</id>
      <parentid>738522</parentid>
      <timestamp>2026-07-19T18:54:06Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Giantbomb</username>
        <id>1</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>Point cover at a rendition that actually serves</comment>
      <origin>1008541</origin>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text bytes="841" sha1="db8hozcxq2fp90qbro3hnulitijj5v9" xml:space="preserve">{{Platform
|Name=Fuze Tomahawk F1
|Guid=3045-164
|Image=https://www.giantbomb.com/a/uploads/scale_super/0/26/2850182-screen%20shot%202016-05-10%20at%2010.48.20%20am.png
|Deck=The Android-based Tomahawk F1 is built on Android and is aimed directly at the Chinese market.
|ShortName=TF1
|ReleaseDate=2016-06-01
|OnlineSupport=Yes
|OriginalPrice=140.00
|Manufacturer=Companies/Fuze_Entertainment
}}
&lt;div id='imageData' data-json='{"infobox":{"file":"2850182-screen shot 2016-05-10 at 10.48.20 am.png","path":"0\/26\/","mime":"image\/png","sizes":"scale_small,scale_super,square_avatar,square_tiny,scale_avatar,square_medium,square_small,square_mini,scale_medium,screen_medium,scale_large,scale_tiny,screen_kubrick","caption":""},"background":[]}' /&gt;
The Android-based Tomahawk F1 is built on Android and is aimed directly at the Chinese market.</text>
      <sha1>db8hozcxq2fp90qbro3hnulitijj5v9</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>Platforms/Gakken Compact Vision TV Boy</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>456754</id>
    <revision>
      <id>738737</id>
      <parentid>722619</parentid>
      <timestamp>2026-02-26T02:59:40Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Marino</username>
        <id>8</id>
      </contributor>
      <origin>738737</origin>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text bytes="523" sha1="54h5hiq4hepsglx4n088fbief65at9s" xml:space="preserve">{{Platform
|Name=Gakken Compact Vision TV Boy
|Guid=3045-196
|Image=https://www.giantbomb.com/a/uploads/scale_super/0/1992/3220237-screenshot2020-07-15at5.50.02pm.png
|Deck=The Compact Vision TV Boy is a game console developed by Gakken in 1983. Only six games were released.
|ShortName=TVB
|ReleaseDate=October 1983
|ReleaseDateType=Month
|OnlineSupport=No
|OriginalPrice=88.00
|Manufacturer=Companies/Gakken_Co_Ltd
}}

The Compact Vision TV Boy is a game console developed by Gakken in 1983. Only six games were released.</text>
      <sha1>54h5hiq4hepsglx4n088fbief65at9s</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>Platforms/Gamate</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>456725</id>
    <revision>
      <id>797235</id>
      <parentid>752647</parentid>
      <timestamp>2026-03-21T01:06:00Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Frobie</username>
        <id>300</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>Undo revision [[Special:Diff/752647|752647]] by [[Special:Contributions/Giantbomb|Giantbomb]] ([[User talk:Giantbomb|talk]])</comment>
      <origin>797235</origin>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text bytes="805" sha1="a4nhap59u94rm2aen23lumv0vzk98ch" xml:space="preserve">{{Platform
|Name=Gamate
|Guid=3045-166
|Image=https://www.giantbomb.com/a/uploads/scale_super/0/26/2917446-gamate_ad.jpg
|Deck=The Gamate, also known as the "Super Boy" in Taiwan, is a handheld platform originally manufactured in 1990.
|ShortName=GMT
|ReleaseDate=1990
|ReleaseDateType=Year
|OnlineSupport=No
|OriginalPrice=59.99
|Manufacturer=Companies/Bit_Corporation
}}
&lt;div id='imageData' data-json='{"infobox":{"file":"2917446-gamate_ad.jpg","path":"0\/26\/","mime":"image\/jpeg","sizes":"scale_super,scale_small,square_small,square_medium,square_tiny,scale_medium,square_mini,scale_avatar,scale_large,scale_tiny,square_avatar,screen_medium,screen_kubrick","caption":""},"background":[]}' /&gt;
The Gamate, also known as the "Super Boy" in Taiwan, is a handheld platform originally manufactured in 1990.</text>
      <sha1>a4nhap59u94rm2aen23lumv0vzk98ch</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>Platforms/GameCube</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>456596</id>
    <revision>
      <id>797156</id>
      <parentid>752576</parentid>
      <timestamp>2026-03-21T00:00:09Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Frobie</username>
        <id>300</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>Undo revision [[Special:Diff/752576|752576]] by [[Special:Contributions/Giantbomb|Giantbomb]] ([[User talk:Giantbomb|talk]])</comment>
      <origin>797156</origin>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text bytes="14840" sha1="30oehw1npq2fxvb7sc4rymuytuvww4i" xml:space="preserve">{{Platform
|Name=GameCube
|Guid=3045-23
|Aliases=GCN,NGC,GC,Project Dolphin,Panasonic Q,Nintendo GameCube
|Image=https://www.giantbomb.com/a/uploads/scale_super/0/1992/1426256-logo.jpg
|Deck=The Nintendo GameCube is a video game console released by Nintendo on September 15, 2001 in Japan, November 18, 2001 in North America, May 3, 2002 in Europe, and May 17, 2002 in Australia.
|ShortName=GCN
|ReleaseDate=2001-09-14
|InstallBase=21,740,000
|OnlineSupport=Yes
|OriginalPrice=199.99
|Manufacturer=Companies/Nintendo
}}
&lt;div id='imageData' data-json='{"infobox":{"file":"1426256-logo.jpg","path":"0\/1992\/","mime":"image\/jpeg","sizes":"scale_medium,scale_super,square_mini,square_medium,square_small,screen_medium,square_avatar,scale_small,square_tiny,screen_small,screen_kubrick,scale_large,scale_avatar,ignore_jpg_scale_small,scale_tiny,screen_tiny,screen_large","caption":""},"background":{"file":"2420179-gamecube_set.jpg","path":"9\/99864\/","mime":"image\/jpeg","sizes":"square_avatar,square_small,scale_medium,screen_medium,scale_small,scale_large,scale_avatar,square_mini,square_tiny,square_medium,screen_kubrick_wide,scale_tiny,scale_super,screen_kubrick","caption":""}}' /&gt;

==Overview==
https://www.giantbomb.com/a/uploads/original/0/1992/1426256-logo.jpg The Nintendo GameCube is [[Companies/Nintendo|Nintendo]]'s successor to the [[Platforms/Nintendo_64|Nintendo 64]] and predecessor to the [[Platforms/Wii|Nintendo Wii]]. The GameCube was released in Japan on September 14, 2001, in North America on November 18, 2001, in Europe on May 3, 2002, and in Australia on May 17, 2002.
The GameCube sold a total of 21.74 million units worldwide, coming in third place in the so-called "console war" slightly behind [[Companies/Xbox_Game_Studios|Microsoft]]'s [[Platforms/Xbox|Xbox]], but far behind [[Companies/Sony_Corporation|Sony]]'s [[Platforms/PlayStation_2|PlayStation 2]]. The console is officially abbreviated to the acronym "GCN" ("'''G'''ame'''C'''ube by '''N'''intendo").
A version of the GameCube with DVD playback capability was released by [[Companies/Panasonic_Interactive_Media|Panasonic]], but the "Panasonic Q Edition" GameCubes weren't available outside of Japan.
https://www.giantbomb.com/a/uploads/original/1/12813/856056-panasonic_q.jpg The GameCube also saw a fair share of games, although its most popular games were first-party; [[Games/Super_Mario_Sunshine|Super Mario Sunshine]], [[Games/The_Legend_of_Zelda_The_Wind_Waker|The Legend of Zelda: The Wind Waker]], [[Games/Metroid_Prime|Metroid Prime]], [[Games/F_Zero_GX|F-Zero GX]], and [[Games/Animal_Crossing|Animal Crossing]], to name a few. Games released only on the GameCube at the time of release have a triangle in the upper left corner that says "Only For," implicating that the game was only available on the GameCube. The final "major release" on the GameCube was also first-party, with [[Games/The_Legend_of_Zelda_Twilight_Princess|The Legend of Zelda: Twilight Princess]] being one of the most highly-anticipated titles in the console's run, though it is more well known for the version that was ported to the Wii.
As games were no longer on cartridges Nintendo released a series of memory cards where players would save their progress. Memory cards are available in 59 block (of which several were packaged with games including Animal Crossing), a 256 block, and a 1024 block versions.

===Marketing===
The first advertising campaign for the Nintendo GameCube was simply a rotating cube that would morph into the GameCube logo. A voice would then whisper, "GameCube." This was usually shown at the end of a commercial for a GameCube game.
https://www.giantbomb.com/a/uploads/original/0/7465/1844595-download.jpeg Another well known advertising campaign was the "Who Are You?" advertising campaign. This was used to market a wide variety of Nintendo games. The "Who Are You?" logo was graffiti lettering. Most of the commercials and print ads were games developed or published by Nintendo, but some third-party developers were able to use the campaign as well. The idea behind the campaign was that players were the character that they played, with print ads showing pieces of the main character taped onto a photograph of a person (e.g. the helmet of Samus Aran taped onto a ballerina to promote Metroid Prime).
There was a distinct difference in the way Nintendo of Japan marketed the GameCube and how it was marketed in western markets. Although in western markets, the GameCube was advertised as a console for experienced gamers; in Japan, it was marketed to appeal to younger and newer players, as a way of gaining back the child audience they lost to their competitors in the previous console cycle. However, it failed, and the GameCube was a commercial flop in Japan. However, due to being marketed to a different audience outside Japan, the GameCube became a very successful console in other countries.

==Hardware==
Due to pressures from developers, the GameCube was [[Companies/Nintendo|Nintendo]]'s first console to introduce a disc medium instead of cartridges, the games were recorded on mini DVDs. The disc can hold 1.5 gigabytes of data - 190 times more than what an [[Platforms/Nintendo_64|N64]] game cartridge can hold. Technologically speaking, the GameCube was more powerful than the [[Platforms/PlayStation_2|PS2]] at about half the size of the [[Platforms/Xbox|Xbox]].

===Colour Schemes===
https://www.giantbomb.com/a/uploads/original/0/9566/393160-gamecube_1_1.jpg Like Nintendo's previous console, the Nintendo 64, and many of the company's handheld consoles, the GameCube was released in a variety of colours. The two most common colours were Indigo and Jet Black (Indigo being the default color). Later, a Platinum color scheme was released and marketed as limited edition. "Orange Spice" GameCubes were also made available, but were primarily available in Japan. The GameCube's model numbers (DOL-001 and DOL-101) were a reference to Dolphin, the GameCube's codename. Official accessories and peripherals also had model numbers beginning with DOL.

===Peripherals===
https://www.giantbomb.com/a/uploads/original/0/1992/1072721-nintendo01.jpg * Broadband adapter * Allowed online gaming via an Ethernet cable and a broadband internet connection. Online multiplayer gaming was accessed via each supporting game's in-game menus.
* Modem adapter * Allowed online gaming via a dial-up modem.
* [[Accessories/Game_Boy_Player|Game Boy Player]]* Later on, Nintendo released the [[Accessories/Game_Boy_Player|Game Boy Player]] which allowed backward compatibility with [[Platforms/Game_Boy|Game Boy]], [[Platforms/Game_Boy_Color|Game Boy Color]] and Game Boy Advance games.
* [[Platforms/Game_Boy_Advance|Game Boy Advance]]* The GameCube allows direct connectivity with Nintendo’s handheld, the [[Platforms/Game_Boy_Advance|Game Boy Advance]], via a link cable.
* [[Concepts/e_Reader|e-Reader]]https://www.giantbomb.com/a/uploads/original/3/35607/2927665-9139822864-gbplr.gif * There were also some games that supported [[Concepts/e_Reader|e-Reader]] connectivity, allowing players to scan in extra game features. Supported games include [[Games/Animal_Crossing|Animal Crossing]] and [[Games/Pokemon_Channel|Pokémon Channel]].

===Online===
Although only a few games have online play for the GameCube (such as the [[Games/Phantasy_Star_Online_Episode_I_And_II_Plus|Phantasy Star Online]] franchise), the GameCube offers LAN support that allows eight GameCubes to be connected together to play a multiplayer game. Using this, fans created unofficial online services for the GameCube, such as Warp Pipe, that used LAN technology for online play.

===[[Accessories/GameCube_Controller|Controller]]===
https://www.giantbomb.com/a/uploads/original/0/3715/811125-gamecube_controller.jpg The inputs on a GameCube controller consist of a large, green A-button, a small, red B-button, two gray X- and Y- buttons, two analog sticks (with the larger being gray and simply called "the analogue stick" and the smaller being yellow and called "the C-stick", in reference to the C-buttons on the N64 controller), a D-pad, two shoulder buttons, and a purple Z-button on top of the controller next to the right shoulder button. Some Wii games [[Concepts/GameCube_Controller_Support_on_Wii|support the use of the GameCube controller]] (this is taken advantage of in Virtual Console and WiiWare games as well).
The wireless version of the controller was called the Wavebird. It allowed players to play from up to 20 feet away. It had the same button layout than the original controller except for an on and off button and a bulkier feel. The controller came with a wireless receiver. To play, the player had to tune his controller to one of the 16 radio channels that the little wheel at the bottom of the controller offered. Then, he had to put the same channel number on the receiver, plug the receiver into the GameCube's controller socket, turn on his controller and a light on the receiver would tell the player that it was receiving a signal. The controller worked with two AA batteries and in order to conserve battery life, [[Concepts/Contextual_Controller_Rumble|rumble]] is not included. It was released in summer of 2002 for the price of 34.95 dollars.

==Technical Specifications==

===Central Processing Unit===
https://www.giantbomb.com/a/uploads/original/0/9566/393161-http_www_ichdertom_de_grafik_gamecube_dsc00125_jpg_640_480_80.jpg * 435 MHz IBM Gekko PowerPC CPU
* PowerPC 750CXe based core
* 180 nm IBM copper-wire process
* 50 new vector instructions
* 32-bit ALU 64-bit FPU, usable as 2x32-bit SIMD
* FPU:1.9Gflops
* 64-bit enhanced PowerPC 60x front side bus to GPU/chipset, 162 MHz clock, 1.3 GB/s peak bandwidth
* 64 KiB L1 cache (32 KiB I/32 KiB D), 8-way associative, 256 KiB on-die L2 cache, 2-way associative
* 1125 DMIPS (dhrystone 2.1)

===System Memory===
* 43 MB total non-unified RAM
* 24 MB MoSys 1T-SRAM main system RAM, 324 MHz, 64-bit bus, 2.7 GB/s bandwidth
* 3 MB embedded 1T-SRAM
* Split into 1 MB texture buffer and 2 MB frame buffer
* 10.4 GB/s texture bandwidth (peak), 7.6 GB/s frame buffer bandwidth (peak), about 6.2 ns latency
* 16 MB DRAM used as buffer for DVD drive and audio, 81 MHz, 8-bit bus, 81 MB/s bandwidth

===Connectivity===
* 4 controller ports, 2 memory card slots
* MultiAV analog audiovisual port: interlaced YPbPr (composite, Y/C() and RGB video, stereophonic analog audio
* Digital audiovisual port: digital interlaced or progressive scan YCBCR video, stereophonic I²S sound
* Resolutions: 480i, 576i, 480p
* High-speed Serial Ports: 2
* High-speed Parallel Ports: 1
* Power supply output: DC12 volts x 3.25 amperes
* Physical measurements: 110 mm (H) x 150 mm (W) x 161 mm (D); [4.3"(h) x 5.9"(W) x 6.3"(D)]

===Graphics Processing Unit===
* 162 MHz "Flipper" LSI, 180 nm NEC eDRAM-compatible process, Co-developed by Nintendo and ArtX
* 8Gflops
* 4 pixel pipelines with 1 texture unit each
* TEV "Texture EnVironment" engine
* Fixed-function hardware transform and lighting (T&amp;amp;L), 12 million polygons/s in-game
* 648 megapixels/s (162 MHz x 4 pipelines), 648 megatexels/s (648 MPx 1 texture units) (peak)
* Peak triangle performance: 20,250,000 32pixel triangles/s raw and with 1 texture and lit
* 337,500 triangles a frame at 60fps
* 675,000 triangles a frame at 30fps
* 8 texture layers per pass, texture compression, full scene anti-aliasing
* 8 simultaneous hardware light
* Bilinear, trilinear, and anisotrophic texture filtering
* Multi-texturing, bump mapping, reflection mapping, 24-bit z-buffer
* 24-bit RGB / 32-bit RGBA color depth
* 720 x 480 interlaced or progressive scan
* Integrated audio processor: Custom 81 MHz Macronix DSP
* Instruction Memory: 8 KiB RAM, 8 KiB ROM
* Data Memory: 8 KiB RAM, 4 KiB ROM
* 64 channels 16-bit 48 kHz ADPCM
* Dolby Pro Logic II encoded within stereophonic output

===Storage Media===
* Matsushita (2.000 MB/s-3.125 MB/s) CAV mini-DVD-like 8 cm optical disk, average access time: 128 ms; capacity: 1.5 GB
* Memory cards of 59 blocks (4Mbit), 256 blocks (16 Mbit), 1024 blocks (64 Mbit), and 2043 (128Mbit) blocks.

==Launch Titles==

===Japan - September 14, 2001===
* [[Games/Luigis_Mansion|Luigi's Mansion]]
* [[Games/Super_Monkey_Ball|Super Monkey Ball]]
* [[Games/Wave_Race_Blue_Storm|Wave Race: Blue Storm]]

===North America - November 18, 2001===
* [[Games/All_Star_Baseball_2002|All Star Baseball 2002]]
* [[Games/Batman_Vengeance|Batman Vengeance]]
* [[Games/Crazy_Taxi|Crazy Taxi]]
* [[Games/Dave_Mirra_Freestyle_BMX_2|Dave Mirra Freestyle BMX 2]]
* [[Games/Disneys_Tarzan_Untamed|Disney's Tarzan Untamed]]
* [[Games/Luigis_Mansion|Luigi's Mansion]]
* [[Games/Madden_NFL_2002|Madden NFL 2002]]
* [[Games/NHL_Hitz_20_02|NHL Hitz 20-02]]
* [[Games/Star_Wars_Rogue_Squadron_II_Rogue_Leader|Star Wars: Rogue Squadron II - Rogue Leader]]
* [[Games/Super_Monkey_Ball|Super Monkey Ball]]
* [[Games/Tony_Hawks_Pro_Skater_3|Tony Hawk's Pro Skater 3]]
* [[Games/Wave_Race_Blue_Storm|Wave Race: Blue Storm]]

===Europe - May 3, 2002===
* [[Games/Batman_Vengeance|Batman Vengeance]]
* [[Games/Bloody_Roar_Primal_Fury|Bloody Roar: Primal Fury]]
* [[Games/Burnout|Burnout]]
* [[Games/Cel_Damage|Cel Damage]]
* [[Games/Crazy_Taxi|Crazy Taxi]]
* [[Games/Dave_Mirra_Freestyle_BMX_2|Dave Mirra Freestyle BMX 2]]
* [[Games/Disneys_Donald_Duck_Goin_Quackers|Donald Duck Quack Attack]]
* [[Games/ESPN_International_Winter_Sports_2002|ESPN International Winter Sports]]
* [[Games/Disneys_Tarzan_Untamed|Disney's Tarzan Freeride]]
* [[Games/2002_FIFA_World_Cup|FIFA 2002 World Cup]]
* [[Games/Driven|Driven]]
* [[Games/Luigis_Mansion|Luigi's Mansion]]
* [[Games/ESPN_International_Winter_Sports_2002|ESPN International Winter Sports 2002]]
* [[Games/Sonic_Adventure_2_Battle|Sonic Adventure 2: Battle]]
* [[Games/International_Superstar_Soccer_2|International Superstar Soccer 2]]
* [[Games/Star_Wars_Rogue_Squadron_II_Rogue_Leader|Star Wars: Rogue Squadron II - Rogue Leader]]
* [[Games/Super_Monkey_Ball|Super Monkey Ball]]
* [[Games/Tony_Hawks_Pro_Skater_3|Tony Hawk's Pro Skater 3]]
* [[Games/Wave_Race_Blue_Storm|Wave Race: Blue Storm]]
* [[Games/XG3_Extreme_G_Racing|XG3: Extreme G Racing]]

==Easter Eggs==
* Starting the console with no disc in the tray plays [http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=aFpw2kHnSuM the Gamecube menu music]. It's a looping string of high, ambient notes. This piece of music sped up to 16 times its original tempo is the [[Platforms/Famicom_Disk_System|Famicom Disk System]] startup tune.
* Holding down the Z button while starting up the system will replace the typical noises with the noise of giggling children and squeaking rubber.
* Holding down the Z button on all four controllers while starting up the system will replace the typical noises with noises such as a woodblock, drums, and a "hwaaa!"</text>
      <sha1>30oehw1npq2fxvb7sc4rymuytuvww4i</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>Platforms/GamePark 32</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>456693</id>
    <revision>
      <id>738617</id>
      <parentid>722539</parentid>
      <timestamp>2026-02-24T21:48:51Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Marino</username>
        <id>8</id>
      </contributor>
      <origin>738617</origin>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text bytes="4723" sha1="pju12eckggfta3znybbg3b6kjim0hhw" xml:space="preserve">{{Platform
|Name=GamePark 32
|Guid=3045-133
|Aliases=GP32,Game Park 32
|Image=https://www.giantbomb.com/a/uploads/scale_super/0/7465/1749578-gp3201.jpg
|Deck=The GamePark 32 is a Korean handheld that actually attained popularity in European markets after its release. The console was popular due to its vast abilities, including emulation, freeware, homebrew, music playback, and more.
|ShortName=GP32
|ReleaseDate=2001-11-23
|ReleaseDateType=Month
|InstallBase=32,000
|OnlineSupport=No
|OriginalPrice=149.99
|Manufacturer=Companies/GamePark
}}
&lt;div id='imageData' data-json='{"infobox":{"file":"1749578-gp3201.jpg","path":"0\/7465\/","mime":"image\/jpeg","sizes":"square_avatar,square_small,scale_medium,screen_medium,scale_small,scale_large,scale_avatar,square_mini,square_tiny,square_medium,scale_super,screen_kubrick","caption":""},"background":[]}' /&gt;

==Overview==
Originally released on November 23, 2001, the GamePark 32 is a Korean handheld console developed by [[Companies/GamePark|GamePark]]. The console was released mostly in Korea, although it can be found in other countries where official distributors are located, such as Spain, Italy, Portugal, the United Kingdom, and Sweden. The GamePark 32 never saw a release in North America.
The GamePark 32 is quite unlike other handheld consoles of the time. Instead of using a proprietary form of media to play games, the GamePark 32 uses SmartMedia cards, which makes the console very accessible from a development standpoint. Additionally, the console has a USB (Universal Serial Bus) port for external peripherals, such as a keyboard.

==Capabilities==
http://www.giantbomb.com/a/uploads/original/0/7465/1845241-473043gp32.jpg The GamePark 32, new out of the box, was capable of doing a few things already. It could launch applications either from a SmartMedia card of downloaded from an online store, it could play MP3 format music files, and it could connect to personal computers. Applications could be purchased or downloaded in several ways. Most commercial games were available boxed in retail stores, as well as the online "JoyGP" store. JoyGP was the international version of MegaGP, a Korean online store meant for downloading games. Games downloaded from the JoyGP online store were typically sold at a reduced price from their boxed counterparts (typically from $10USD to $30USD).
Homebrew software initially required the end user to download GamePark's "Free Launcher" to run, but later firmware rendered that not necessary. The GamePark's C-based code made it easy for application developers to create homebrew software for the GamePark 32, so many such applications were released. Some of these include various emulators (for a variety of consoles), a DivX player, file managers, homebrew games, and more.

==Launch Titles==
Upon the GamePark's initial release, there were five titles also available. Over the GamePark's lifespan, around 30 commercial games were released for the console. The console's final game was [[Games/Blue_Angelo_Angels_from_the_Shrine|Blue Angelo: Angels from the Shrine]], released on December 16, 2004. It was only available in boxed form, and was one of two games sold solely in one format (the other being [[Games/Gloop_Deluxe|Gloop Deluxe]], sold only on JoyGP).

===Korea (November 23, 2001)===
http://www.giantbomb.com/a/uploads/original/0/7465/1845243-smartmedia.jpg * &amp;lt;span&amp;gt;[[Games/Dungeon_And_Guarder|Dungeon andamp;amp;amp; Guarder]]&amp;lt;/span&amp;gt;
* &amp;lt;span&amp;gt;[[Games/Dyhard_Infinity|Dyhard Infinity]]&amp;lt;/span&amp;gt;
* &amp;lt;span&amp;gt;[[Games/Little_Wizard|Little Wizard]]&amp;lt;/span&amp;gt;
* &amp;lt;span&amp;gt;[[Games/Rally_Pop|Rally Pop]]&amp;lt;/span&amp;gt;
* &amp;lt;span&amp;gt;[[Games/Tanggles_Magic_Square|Tanggle's Magic Square]]&amp;lt;/span&amp;gt;

==Technical Specifications==
* '''CPU''': Samsung S3C2400X01 (ARM920T core), 20 (and under) to 133 MHz
* '''RAM''': 8MB SDRAM
* '''ROM''': 512KB
* '''Sound''': 44.1kHz 16-bit stereo sound, four channels, 16 part polyphonic software MIDI
* '''Storage''': SmartMedia 2-128MB 3.3.v
* '''Dimensions''': 147mm x 88m x 34mm
* '''Weight''': 0.163kg

===GP32 FLU and GP32 BLU===
http://www.giantbomb.com/a/uploads/original/0/7465/1845254-gp32.jpg The original GamePark 32 console was the GP32 NLU, or the GamePark 32 "No Light Unit." Shortly thereafter, two other versions of the console were released. The GP32 FLU (Front Light Unit) had a slightly larger screen to accomodate the front light between the plastic and the LCD, and was released in 2002. The GP32 BLU (Back Light Unit) contained a backlight, and had a second version released in 2004. The BLU+ is the only variant of the GamePark 32 that is incompatible with some software, due to the fact that it has a different LCD screen.</text>
      <sha1>pju12eckggfta3znybbg3b6kjim0hhw</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>Platforms/Game Boy</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>456577</id>
    <revision>
      <id>797134</id>
      <parentid>752557</parentid>
      <timestamp>2026-03-20T23:09:36Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Frobie</username>
        <id>300</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>Undo revision [[Special:Diff/752557|752557]] by [[Special:Contributions/Giantbomb|Giantbomb]] ([[User talk:Giantbomb|talk]])</comment>
      <origin>797134</origin>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text bytes="12878" sha1="3oedoqk8nau4w218s7bkzy32mtyzwsy" xml:space="preserve">{{Platform
|Name=Game Boy
|Guid=3045-3
|Aliases=Gameboy, GB
|Image=https://www.giantbomb.com/a/uploads/scale_super/0/1992/1426210-logo.jpg
|Deck=Nintendo's first handheld gaming console was immensely popular among gamers, selling millions. Despite its grayscale color scheme, it still got support from developers and publishers.
|ShortName=GB
|ReleaseDate=1989-04-21
|InstallBase=118,690,000
|OnlineSupport=No
|OriginalPrice=89.99
|Manufacturer=Companies/Nintendo
}}


==Overview==
http://www.giantbomb.com/a/uploads/original/0/7465/942953-database_hardware_gameboy01.jpg The [[Companies/Nintendo|Nintendo]] Game Boy was one of the first commercially viable handheld game systems on the market being released in 1989. The Game Boy was released in [[Locations/North_America|North America]] in August, 1989, in [[Locations/Japan|Japan]] on April 21, 1989, and in [[Locations/Europe|Europe]] in September 1990. The Game Boy was the first in the Game Boy line, a line that lasted over fifteen years until the release of the [[Platforms/Nintendo_DS|Nintendo DS]]. It was created by the brilliant [[People/Gunpei_Yokoi|Gunpei Yokoi]], as well as the same team that had developed Nintendo's [[Franchises/Game_And_Watch|Game andamp;amp;amp; Watch]] series. The Game Boy pack-in game was [[Games/Tetris|Tetris]], a little known puzzle game from [[Locations/Russia|Russia]] that would help lead the Game Boy to its massive success. [[People/Minoru_Arakawa|Minoru Arakawa]] and several employees from Nintendo of America went to Russia to sign a deal to get the game on their system, they saw it as the equivalent to packing in [[Games/Super_Mario_Bros|Super Mario Bros]] with the [[Platforms/Nintendo_Entertainment_System|NES]]. Despite the Game Boy's handicap of being able to only display two colors, something that was technically inferior to what other handhelds was offering at the time it was massively more successful. Part of this was due to the fact that the batteries for Game Boy lasted a significantly longer times than those used for other full color handhelds, due to the fact that it used four AA batteries. 1998 saw Nintendo introduce the Game Boy's successor the [[Platforms/Game_Boy_Color|Game Boy Color]]; the two systems games were actually compatible with each other, with the entire Game Boy line up playable on the Game Boy Color and a select few Game Boy Color titles playable on the original Game Boy (although not in color). Backwards compatibility became a stable of Nintendo handhelds, Game Boy classic games were playable up until the release of the Nintendo DS.
In 1994 Nintendo released an adapter for the [[Platforms/Super_Nintendo_Entertainment_System|Super Nintendo]] entitled the [[Concepts/Super_Game_Boy_Enhancement|Super Game Boy]], which allowed Super Nintendo players to play Game Boy games on their TV with a limited amount of colors. The adapter did not require the owner to own the original Game Boy system, just the adapter; despite this Game Boy remained as popular as ever. The first variation of the Game Boy, the Game Boy Pocket arrived in 1996. It was slimmer, more compact and the first in what would become a Nintendo tradition of releasing multiple variations of their handhelds. The Game Boy managed to sell its shipment of a million units within weeks in the [[Locations/The_United_States_of_America|United States]] and its initial shipment of 300,000 units in Japan in two weeks and reached 500,000 sales in Japan by July. The Game Boy and the color has sold 118.69 million combined worldwide and the Game Boy had sold 66.42 million alone before the release of the color. Twenty years after its introduction, in 2009 the Game Boy was inducted into the Nintendo toy hall of fame.

==Competition==
http://www.giantbomb.com/a/uploads/original/13/130768/1859791-nintendoad29.jpg When it launched in 1989, the Game Boy entered a handheld battle against the [[Platforms/Atari_Lynx|Atari Lynx]] and [[Platforms/Game_Gear|Sega Game Gear]]. Both the Lynx and Game Gear were technologically impressive for the time. They featured full color backlit screens and, in the case of the Lynx, significantly more processing power. Atari and Sega attempted to capitalize on their products' capabilites in advertisements that portrayed the Game Boy as weak and childish. A memorable Sega ad from the time proclaimed that "The Sega Game Gear separates the men from the boys". Despite their marketing efforts, the Lynx and Game Gear could not stop the Game Boy's dominance. Their weak battery life (a Game Gear or Lynx could deplete six AA batteries in 4-6 hours), combined with lackluster software libraries and higher prices, proved fatal. 

==Hardware Revisions==
There was three different versions of the Game Boy that was released during its life. The Game Boy Light however was only released in Japan.

===Game Boy===
http://www.giantbomb.com/a/uploads/original/0/9566/392624-123950_gadget26_gameboy_b.jpg The Game Boy was released on April 21, 1989 in Japan and then later in August for North America. The classic Game Boy ran on 4 AA batteries which powered the system for around 35 hours. Despite its size and less than perfect monochromatic screen the Game Boy lasted seven years until it received its first update. The Game Boy was only available in grey, in 1995 a "Play it Loud" line of the handheld was available in red, green, black, yellow, blue, white and transparent though this line had the exact same specifications. This set a trend of Nintendo handheld's being released in multiple colours. The link cable port is larger than the rest of the Game Boy line which makes it unable to link with all future models of the Game Boy.
RAM: 8 kB internal S-RAM
* Video RAM: 8 kB internal
* ROM: 8 Mb cartridges
* Sound: 2 Square Waves, 1 programmable 32-sample 4-bit PCM Wave, 1 White noise, and one audio input from the cartridge.
* Display: Reflective LCD 160 x 144 pixels
* Screen Size: 66 mm (2.6 in) diagonal
* Power: 4 AA Batteries
* Dimensions: 148 x 89 x 32 mm
* Weight: 394g (with batteries)

===Game Boy Pocket===
http://www.giantbomb.com/a/api/image/original/1777455-gameboy_pocket.jpg The Game Boy Pocket was originally released July 21, 1996 in Japan and then later released in North America in September 3, 1996. The Game Boy Pocket was smaller, lighter version of the original Game Boy designed to be able to easily fit in your pocket. An additional plus point of the system was that it only needed 2 AAA batteries, though this only powered the system for 10 hours. The Pocket featured a re-designed smaller link port, this version of the port was later used for all later models in the Game Boy line. Another improvement was an improved monochrome screen which did not blur up like on the original. The Game Boy Pocket like the original had no blacklight for darkened area and the first run did not feature a LED to indicate power levels, though due to public outcry a LED was added. The Pocket has been released in silver/chrome, red, yellow, green, black, transparent, pink and the original grey. Some limited editions of the handheld were also released.
* CPU: Custom 8-bit Sharp LR35902 core at 4.19 MHz
* RAM: 8 kB internal S-RAM
* Video RAM: 8 kB internal
* ROM: 8 Mb cartridges
* Sound: 2 Square Waves, 1 programmable 32-sample 4-bit PCM Wave, 1 White noise, and one audio input from the cartridge.
* Display: Reflective LCD 160 x 144 pixels
* Screen Size: 66 mm (2.6 in) diagonal
* Power Supply: 2 AAA Batteries
* Dimensions: 124 x 76 x 23 mm
* Weight: 148g (with batteries)

===Game Boy Light===
http://www.giantbomb.com/a/api/image/original/1777456-gbl.jpg The Game Boy Light was a Japan exclusive variation of the handheld that was released on April 14, 1998, due to its Japan only release it is one of the rarest Game Boy models. The main selling point was it's indigo coloured backlight that allowed for play in dark environments. The Light ran on two AA batteries and lasted for 20 hours with the light off and 12 with it on. Amazingly none of the consoles that followed the Game Boy Light featured a back lit screen until the 2003 release of the [[Platforms/Game_Boy_Advance|Game Boy Advance SP]]. The Game Boy Light was only available in Gold and Silver though numerous special editions were released. The Game Boy Light was never released outside of Japan due to the imminent release of the Game Boy Color and Japanese thinking that western gamers wanted color not light.
* CPU: Custom 8-bit Sharp LR35902 core at 4.19 MHz
* RAM: 8 kB internal S-RAM
* Video RAM: 8 kB internal
* ROM: 8 Mb cartridges
* Sound: Mono
* Display: LCD (Passive, monochrome, backlit) 160 x 144 pixels
* Screen Size: 2.56 inches
* Power Supply: 2 AA Batteries

==Launch Titles==

===Japan===
* [[Games/Alleyway|Alleyway]]
* [[Games/Baseball_8145|Baseball]]
* [[Games/Super_Mario_Land|Super Mario Land]]
* [[Games/Yakuman|Yakuman]]

===North America===
* [[Games/Alleyway|Alleyway]]
* [[Games/Baseball_8145|Baseball]]
* [[Games/Super_Mario_Land|Super Mario Land]]
* [[Games/Tennis_1984|Tennis]]
* [[Games/Tetris|Tetris]]

===Europe===
* [[Games/Tetris|Tetris]]
* [[Games/Super_Mario_Land|Super Mario Land]]
* [[Games/Alleyway|Alleyway]]
* [[Games/Baseball_8145|Baseball]]
* [[Games/Tennis_1984|Tennis]]

==Features==
http://www.giantbomb.com/a/uploads/original/0/7465/942954-picture_6.png The Game Boy's control was very similar to that of the original Nintendo Entertainment System. It had a D-pad, A and B buttons, and a Select and Start button. On the side of the Game Boy was a volume control, a contrast control, a link cable port, and a jack for rechargeable batteries (instead of just the regular batteries). There was a sliding on-off switch on the top of the handheld a slot for the cartridges, the classic Game Boy cartridges are usable in the entire Game Boy line. The link cable port could also be used for the Game Boy Printer. The link cable was originally designed to allow for head to head multiplayer though [[People/Satoshi_Tajiri|Satoshi Tajiri's]] wildly successful [[Franchises/Pokemon|pokemon]] series revolutionised multiplayer handheld gaming with its focus on trading rather than competitive multiplayer.

==Top Ten Best Selling Games==
# [[Games/Tetris|Tetris]] (35 Million) *Bundled with the system.
# [[Games/Pokemon_Red_Blue|Pokemon Red/Blue/Green]] (20.68 Million Approx)
# [[Games/Super_Mario_Land|Super Mario Land]] (18.06 Million)
# [[Games/Super_Mario_Land_2_6_Golden_Coins|Super Mario Land 2: 6 Golden Coins]] (11.09 Million)
# [[Games/Pokemon_Yellow_Special_Pikachu_Edition|Pokemon Yellow]] (8.86 Million Approx)
# [[Games/The_Legend_of_Zelda_Links_Awakening|The Legend of Zelda: Link's Awakening]] (6.05 Million Approx)
# [[Games/Dr_Mario|Dr Mario]] (2.08 Million)
# [[Games/Wario_Land_Super_Mario_Land_3|Super Mario Land 3: Wario Land]] (1.59 Million Approx)
# [[Games/Kirbys_Dream_Land_2|Kirby's Dream Land 2]] (1.49 Million Approx)
# [[Games/Kirbys_Dream_Land|Kirby's Dream Land]] (1.45 Approx)

==Accessories==

===Game Link Cable===
The game link cable allows for interaction between multiple Game Boy's in certain games. Originally designed for the multiplayer battle mode in Tetris, its most popular use was the transferring of data in [[Games/Pokemon_Red_Blue|pokemon]]. The game link cable for the original Game Boy was not compatible with any future variations of the Game Boy without the use of the adapter.

===Game Boy Printer===
The Game Boy printer was released in 1998, it was compatible with the Game Boy, Pocket, Color and Advance. It is designed to work in conjunction with the Game Boy Camera, though some Game Boy and GBC games were also usable. It needs 6 AA batteries to run and uses special 3.8 cm Game Boy printer paper.

===Game Boy Camera===
http://www.giantbomb.com/a/uploads/original/11/112517/1777605-gameboycamera.jpg In 1998 Nintendo released the Game Boy camera, it was compatible with the Game Boy, Color, Pocket and Advance. The camera could only take black and white pictures and when used in conjunction with the game boy printer you could print your pictures out. The Game Boy camera was aimed at children who could not afford their own camera, the Camera also had some special features and mini-games to play. The Game Boy Camera was launched in five different colors blue, green, red, yellow and clear purple. There was also some limited editions released such as The Legend of Zelda and Pokemon editions.

===Super Game Boy===
Nintendo released the Super Game Boy accessory in 1994 for $60. The Super Game Boy allows Game Boy games to be played on your TV screen by using it with your Super Nintendo. It was also compatible with Game Boy Color cartridges, any original Game Boy cartridges you played with your Super Game Boy would still be in black and white, though some later games were programmed to show up in color and display a border around the game.</text>
      <sha1>3oedoqk8nau4w218s7bkzy32mtyzwsy</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>Platforms/Game Boy Advance</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>456578</id>
    <revision>
      <id>797160</id>
      <parentid>797135</parentid>
      <timestamp>2026-03-20T23:12:32Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Frobie</username>
        <id>300</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>fix misspelled word</comment>
      <origin>797160</origin>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text bytes="14201" sha1="n5b9oelojjkqj9mnylf3orami6kb04q" xml:space="preserve">{{Platform
|Guid=3045-4
|Name=Game Boy Advance
|Aliases=Game Boy Advance SP,Gameboy Advance,GBA,Game Boy Player,GBA SP,Game Boy micro,Atlantis,Oxygen
|Image=https://www.giantbomb.com/a/uploads/scale_super/0/1992/2121789-gba.png
|Deck=The third platform in the Game Boy line, the Game Boy Advance was offered in a multitude of colors and had three hardware offerings, the sideways Game Boy Advance, the flip Game Boy Advance SP and the tiny Game Boy Advance Micro.
|ShortName=GBA
|ReleaseDateType=Full
|ReleaseDate=2001-03-21
|InstallBase=81,510,000
|OnlineSupport=No
|OriginalPrice=100.00
|Manufacturer=Companies/Nintendo
}}
&lt;div id='imageData' data-json='{"infobox":{"file":"2121789-gba.png","path":"0\/1992\/","mime":"image\/png","sizes":"square_mini,square_avatar,square_small,scale_small,square_tiny,square_medium,scale_medium,screen_medium,scale_large,scale_avatar,scale_tiny,scale_super,screen_kubrick","caption":"GBA Types"},"background":{"file":"239847-gba_skin_template.gif","path":"0\/6763\/","mime":"image\/gif","sizes":"square_tiny,square_medium,screen_kubrick_wide,scale_tiny,scale_super,scale_medium,square_small,scale_avatar,square_mini,square_avatar,scale_large,scale_small,screen_medium,screen_kubrick","caption":""}}' /&gt;

==Overview==
https://www.giantbomb.com/a/uploads/original/12/121177/1705634-810156_gba_logo_super.png The Game Boy Advance (originally codenamed "Atlantis") was originally launched in [[Locations/Japan|Japan]] on March 21, 2001 and then in [[Locations/North_America|North America]] on June 11. It is the third platform in the [[Platforms/Game_Boy|Game Boy]] hand-held line and like it's predecessors, the Game Boy Advance established itself as the leader in the portable market. The Game Boy Advance continued the [[Platforms/Game_Boy_Color|Game Boy Color]] trend of offering different colors and special branded limited editions. It also established the trend of a periodic hardware redesign (see below), which was carried on with the [[Platforms/Nintendo_DS|Nintendo DS]] and DS Lite. The Game Boy Advance series has had sales of over 81 million worldwide, approximately 43 million of which are Game Boy Advance SP units.

==Launch Titles==

===Japan===
* [[Games/GT_Advance_Championship_Racing|Advance GTA]]
* [[Games/Castlevania_Circle_of_the_Moon|Akumajo Dracula: Circle of the Moon]]
* [[Games/Super_Dodge_Ball_Advance|Bakunetsu Dodgeball Fighters]]
* [[Games/Boku_Wa_Koukuu_Kansei_An|Boku wa Koukuu Kansei-An]]
* [[Games/ChuChu_Rocket|ChuChu Rocket!]]
* [[Games/EZ_Talk_Shokyuuhen_1_6_Kan_Set|EZ-Talk Shokyuuhen 1-6 Kan Set]]
* [[Games/Fire_Pro_Wrestling|Fire Pro Wrestling A]]
* [[Games/J_League_Pocket|J-League Pocket]]
* [[Games/ESPN_Final_Round_Golf_2002|JTO Golf Master: Japan Tour Golf Game]]
* [[Games/Kuru_Kuru_Kururin|Kuru Kuru Kururin]]
* [[Games/Konami_Krazy_Racers|Konami Wai Wai Racing Advance]]
* [[Games/Momotaro_Matsuri|Momotaro Matsuri]]
* [[Games/Monster_Guardians|Monster Guardians]]
* [[Games/Mr_Driller_2|Mr. Driller 2]]
* [[Games/Napoleon|Napoleon]]
* [[Games/Pinobee_Wings_of_Adventure|Pinobee no Daibouken]]
* [[Games/Power_Pro_Kun_Pocket_3|Power Pro-Kun Pocket 3]]
* [[Games/Mega_Man_Battle_Network|Rockman.EXE]]
* [[Games/Silent_Hill_Play_Novel|Silent Hill: Play Novel]]
* [[Games/Super_Mario_Advance|Super Mario Advance]]
* [[Games/Tweety_and_the_Magic_Gems|Tweety no Hearty Party]]
* [[Games/Winning_Post|Winning Post for Game Boy Advance]]
* [[Games/Yu_Gi_Oh_Dungeon_Dice_Monsters|Yu-Gi-Oh! Dungeon Dice Monsters]]
* [[Games/Top_Gear_GT_Championship|Zen Nihon GT Senshuken]]

===North America===
* [[Games/Army_Men_Advance|Army Men Advance]]
* [[Games/Castlevania_Circle_of_the_Moon|Castlevania: Circle of the Moon]]
* [[Games/ChuChu_Rocket|ChuChu Rocket!]]
* [[Games/Earthworm_Jim|Earthworm Jim]]
* [[Games/F_Zero_Maximum_Velocity|F-Zero: Maximum Velocity]]
* [[Games/Fire_Pro_Wrestling|Fire Pro Wrestling]]
* [[Games/GT_Advance_Championship_Racing|GT Advance Championship Racing]]
* [[Games/Iridion_3D|Iridion 3D]]
* [[Games/Konami_Krazy_Racers|Konami Krazy Racers]]
* [[Games/Namco_Museum_2001|Namco Museum]]
* [[Games/Pinobee_Wings_of_Adventure|Pinobee: Wings of Adventure]]
* [[Games/Pitfall_The_Mayan_Adventure|Pitfall: The Mayan Adventure]]
* [[Games/Rayman|Rayman Advance]]
* [[Games/Ready_2_Rumble_Boxing_Round_2|Ready 2 Rumble Boxing: Round 2]]
* [[Games/Super_Dodge_Ball_Advance|Super Dodge Ball Advance]]
* [[Games/Super_Mario_Advance|Super Mario Advance]]
* [[Games/Tony_Hawks_Pro_Skater_2|Tony Hawk's Pro Skater 2]]

===Europe===
* [[Games/F_Zero_Maximum_Velocity|F-Zero: Maximum Velocity]]
* [[Games/Top_Gear_GT_Championship|Top Gear GT Championship]]
* [[Games/Konami_Krazy_Racers|Konami Krazy Racers]]
* [[Games/Kuru_Kuru_Kururin|Kuru Kuru Kururin]]
* [[Games/Ready_2_Rumble_Boxing_Round_2|Ready 2 Rumble Boxing Round 2]]
* [[Games/Super_Mario_Advance|Super Mario Advance]]
* [[Games/Tony_Hawks_Pro_Skater_2|Tony Hawk's Pro Skater 2]]
* [[Games/Tweety_and_the_Magic_Gems|Tweety and The Magic Jewel]]
* [[Games/Castlevania_Circle_of_the_Moon|Castlevania: Circle of the Moon]]

==Games==
https://www.giantbomb.com/a/uploads/original/0/7465/873717-6a00d83452033569e200e54f27386f8834_800wi.jpg The Game Boy Advance's hardware was very similar to the [[Platforms/Super_Nintendo_Entertainment_System|SNES]]'s, which made it perfect for sprite-based games. It had many ports of SNES titles, including a large number of RPGs. As well as being known for its SNES remakes and great original content a lot of original [[Platforms/Nintendo_Entertainment_System|NES]] games were made available to play on the move thanks to the [[Concepts/Classic_NES_Series|NES Classic's Series]]. The Game Boy Advance is regarded as an incredibly popular console among old school gamers and many call it [[Companies/Nintendo|Nintendo's]] best handheld in terms of games. The last game to be release for the Game Boy Advance was [[Games/Samurai_Deeper_Kyo|Samurai Deeper Kyo]] which was released on February 12, 2008 in North America. As of March, 2009 there has been over 377 million GBA games sold worldwide.

===Best Selling Games Worldwide===
# [[Games/Pokemon_Ruby_Sapphire|''Pokémon Ruby''/''Sapphire'']] (13 million)
# [[Games/Pokemon_FireRed_LeafGreen|''Pokémon FireRed''/''LeafGreen'']] (11.82 million)
# ''Pokémon Emerald'' (6.32 million)
# ''Super Mario World: Super Mario Advance 2'' (4.179 million approx)
# ''Super Mario Advance'' (3.938 million approx)
# [[Games/Mario_Kart_Super_Circuit|''Mario Kart: Super Circuit'']] (3.768 million approx)
# [[Games/Super_Mario_Bros_3_Super_Mario_Advance_4|''Super Mario Advance 4: Super Mario Bros. 3'']] (3.698 million approx)
# ''Namco Museum'' (2.96 million in US)
# ''Pokémon Pinball: Ruby &amp; Sapphire'' (2.5 million)
# ''Pokémon Mystery Dungeon: Red Rescue Team'' (2.2 million)

==Hardware Revisions==
There were three different models offered during the lifespan of the Game Boy Advance.

{| class='wikitable' style='margin:auto;width:100%;'
|-
! Game Boy Advance (GBA)
|-
| The original Game Boy Advance was released with a horizontal design. This model is backwards compatible with games for the Game Boy and Game Boy Color. Many gamers complained that the screen was not bright enough on this model and many third party lighting accessories were developed, this issue was fixed in the next iteration.||https://www.giantbomb.com/a/uploads/original/0/9566/395908-nintendo_game_boy_advance.jpeg
|-
| ===Hardware Specs===
* CPU: 32-bit RISC CPU with embedded memory
* Screen: 2.9" Reflective TFT Color LCD
* Display Size: 1.6" by 2.4" (40.8 by 61.2 mm)
* Resolution: 240 x 160 pixels
* Colors: 512 simultaneous colors from a palette of 32,768
* Size: 3.2 by 5.6 by 1 inch (82 by 144.5 by 24.5 mm)
* Weight: Approximately 5 ounces (140 grams)
* Power Supply: 2 AA alkaline batteries
* Battery Life: Approximately 15 hours continuous play||* Launch Date: June 11, 2001
* Launch Price: $149.99
|}


{| class='wikitable' style='margin:auto;width:100%;'
|-
! Game Boy Advance SP
|-
| The Game Boy Advance SP not only saw a major change with its flip design, but also added a built-in (but removeable, with tools) rechargeable battery and front mounted light. Like the original GBA, the SP is backwards compatible with all Game Boy and Game Boy Color games. This version did not have a standard headphone jack, and users dissatisfied by the small built-in speaker needed either proprietary Nintendo headphones or an adapter. In September of 2005, a back-lit model of the SP was released. This version of the hardware is recognizable by the model number AGS-101.||https://www.giantbomb.com/a/uploads/original/0/8272/1352103-gbasp_famicom.jpg
|-
| ===Hardware Specs===
* CPU: 32-bit RISC-CPU with embedded memory
* Screen: 2.9" Reflective TFT Color LCD Display Size: 1.61" x 2.41"
* Resolution: 240 x 160 pixels Color:
* Simultaneously display more than 32,000 colors
* Size (Closed): Height 3.33 inches, width 3.23 inches, depth 0.96 inches
* Weight: Approximately 5 ounces (140 grams)
* Power Supply: Lithium-Ion rechargeable battery
* Battery Life: Approximately 10 hours of continuous play with light, 18 hours without light||* Launch Date: March 23, 2003
* Launch Price: $ 99.99
|}


{| class='wikitable' style='margin:auto;width:100%;'
|-
! Game Boy Micro
|-
| Tiny in size, the third design (originally codenamed "Oxygen") borrowed from the then-popular cell phone trend of having interchangeable face-plates. Featuring a brighter screen than the SP (with 5 levels of adjustable brightness) and a standard headphone jack (found at the bottom of the unit), but with an external port unique to the Micro which did not accept a standard GBA link cable (though a cable exclusive to the micro was released) and able to play Game Boy Advance games only, this version of the platform never achieved the success of the previous two versions.||https://www.giantbomb.com/a/uploads/original/0/9983/680978-micro.jpg
|-
| ===Hardware Specs===
* CPU: 32-bit RISC-CPU (16.78 MHz)
* Screen: 2-inch diagonal screen TFT
* Display Size: 1.61" x 2.41"
* Resolution: 240 x 160 pixels
* Color: 512 out of a maximum 32,000 colors
* Size: Measures 4 by 0.7 by 2 inches
* Weight: Approximately 2.8 ounces
* Power Supply: Lithium-Ion rechargeable battery
* Battery Life: Approximately 6 to 10 hours, depending on brightness level.||* Launch Date: Sept 19, 2005
* Launch Price: $99.99
|}


==Official Nintendo Accessories==
Many accessories were created for the Game Boy Advance line.

{| class='wikitable' style='margin:auto;width:100%;'
|-
! Game Link Cable||
|-
| This 4-port cable allowed between 2 and 4 Game Boy Advance units to communicate for multiplayer games or to share or trade data. The game that is best known for its use of this accessory is [[Games/The_Legend_of_Zelda_A_Link_to_the_Past_And_Four_Swords|The Legend of Zelda: A Link to the Past &amp; Four Swords]], which is the GBA remake of the SNES classic.||https://www.giantbomb.com/a/uploads/original/16/164924/2486361-gba_link_cable_en.jpg
|}


{| class='wikitable' style='margin:auto;width:100%;'
|-
! Nintendo Gamecube Game Boy Advance Link Cable||
|-
| This cable allowed you to use your GBA with certain Gamecube games, such as [[Games/The_Legend_of_Zelda_Four_Swords_Adventures|The Legend of Zelda: Four Swords Adventures]], [[Games/Pac_Man_Vs|Pac-Man VS]] and as a controller (with screen!) for your Gamecube. Some other games also used the accessory for side features, for example being able to travel to||
|}


{| class='wikitable' style='margin:auto;width:100%;'
|-
! Game Boy Wireless Adapter||
|-
| The wireless adapter was a great alternative to the wired Game Link cable, but only worked with certain games designed specifically for it. As it was released relatively late in the handhelds life less than 20 games supported it the most pominent tat offered support was [[Games/Pokemon_FireRed_LeafGreen|Pokemon FireRed/LeafGreen]] which had the adapter included with the game.||
|}


{| class='wikitable' style='margin:auto;width:100%;'
|-
! [[Concepts/e_Reader|e-Reader]]||
|-
| This optical scanner was released in 2001 and co-created with Olympus Optical, Ltd. It worked with specially printed dot-patterned cards which could be used to unlock bonus content in games, most notably [[Games/Super_Mario_Bros_3_Super_Mario_Advance_4|Super Mario Bros. 3: Super Mario Advance 4]] (which had the most ambitious e-Reader release of all, with multiple packs of cards adding items, levels, and even "professional" replays), or to play entire games, especially retro titles like the [[Franchises/Game_And_Watch|Game and Watch]] series, or Nintendo Arcade Classics, like the original [[Games/Donkey_Kong|Donkey Kong]]. The device was inserted into the cartridge slot of the Game Boy Advance, (shown here to the right), and featured a pass-through port to allow connection of multiple Game Boy Advance units using the standard Game Link Cable. The e-Reader served as a bootable cartridge, and had onboard memory to store one game at a time, but for most other features more than one GBA was required, since there was no other way for data to be transferred to a game cartridge, severely limiting its usefulness.||https://www.giantbomb.com/a/uploads/original/0/7465/1124594-gba_e_reader.jpg 
|}


{| class='wikitable' style='margin:auto;width:100%;'
|-
! Game Boy Advance SP Headphone Jack Adapter||
|-
| This short cable connected to the charging port of the SP and allowed the user to connect a standard 3.5mm headphone jack instead of the charger. Many third parties improved on this design by allowing both the headphone jack and the charger to be used simultaneously.||
|}


{| class='wikitable' style='margin:auto;width:100%;'
|-
! Game Boy Player||
|-
| This device allowed you to play GBA games on your television by connecting it to your [[Platforms/GameCube|GameCube]]. The device installed semi-permanently to the bottom of the Gamecube and booted with a standard Gamecube disc. The Game Boy Advance cartridges were inserted in the front of the device, visible in the center of the bottom left-hand side of the picture (right).||https://www.giantbomb.com/a/uploads/original/0/9983/680979-player.jpg &amp;lt;p&amp;gt; &amp;lt;/p&amp;gt;
|}</text>
      <sha1>n5b9oelojjkqj9mnylf3orami6kb04q</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>Platforms/Game Boy Color</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>456622</id>
    <revision>
      <id>797174</id>
      <parentid>752595</parentid>
      <timestamp>2026-03-21T00:04:55Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Frobie</username>
        <id>300</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>Undo revision [[Special:Diff/752595|752595]] by [[Special:Contributions/Giantbomb|Giantbomb]] ([[User talk:Giantbomb|talk]])</comment>
      <origin>797174</origin>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text bytes="5138" sha1="f0z9flx5p80dco69n08547732d40dcj" xml:space="preserve">{{Platform
|Name=Game Boy Color
|Guid=3045-57
|Aliases=Gameboy Color,Game Boy Colour,Gameboy Colour,GBC
|Image=https://www.giantbomb.com/a/uploads/scale_super/0/1992/1426240-logo.jpg
|Deck=Nintendo's successor to the Game Boy, featuring a color screen and backwards compatibility for all previous Game Boy titles.
|ShortName=GBC
|ReleaseDate=1998-10-21
|ReleaseDateType=Month
|InstallBase=118,690,000
|OnlineSupport=No
|OriginalPrice=79.99
|Manufacturer=Companies/Nintendo
}}
&lt;div id='imageData' data-json='{"infobox":{"file":"1426240-logo.jpg","path":"0\/1992\/","mime":"image\/jpeg","sizes":"scale_medium,scale_super,square_mini,square_medium,square_small,screen_medium,square_avatar,scale_small,square_tiny,ignore_jpg_scale_small,scale_large,scale_avatar,scale_tiny,screen_kubrick","caption":""},"background":{"file":"888592-800px_color.png","path":"0\/4253\/","mime":"image\/png","sizes":"square_small,square_tiny,square_medium,scale_tiny,screen_kubrick_wide,scale_super,scale_large,scale_medium,scale_small,screen_kubrick,square_mini,square_avatar,screen_medium,scale_avatar","caption":""}}' /&gt;

==Overview==
http://www.giantbomb.com/a/uploads/original/10/103881/2693740-yellow+gbc.jpg The Game Boy Color was [[Companies/Nintendo|Nintendo]]'s second handheld video game console, and the successor to the [[Platforms/Game_Boy|Game Boy]]. It was released on November 19, 1998 in North America, on October 21, 1998 in Japan, on November 23, 1998 in Europe, and in 1999 in Australia. Unlike its predecessor, it featured a color screen. It was smaller than the original Game Boy, but slightly larger than the Game Boy Pocket. The Game Boy Color only used 2 AA batteries as compared to the originals 4, and the Game Boy Pocket's 2 AAA's. Combined sales of the Game Boy and Game Boy Color were charted at 118.69 million worldwide. Total Sales for Japan reached 32.47 million units, 44.06 million in the the Americas, and 2.16 million in other regions.
The Game Boy Color was originally a response by Nintendo from the pressure of developers for new and more sophisticated hardware. Developers felt that the Game Boy, and even the recently released Game Boy Pocket, were far too simple and stifled creative ability. To combat this, Nintendo released the Game Boy Color. The Game Boy Color was the first handheld video game console to be [[Concepts/Backwards_Compatibility|backwards compatible]], meaning that original Game Boy games could be played on it. This has since become a standard in the Game Boy line. The Color boasted a processor twice as powerful as its predecessor, as well as four times the available system memory. This allowed for developers to create much larger and longer games than possible with the original systems specifications.

===Cartridge Types===
Many games released during the Game Boy Color's run were developed to be still be compatible with the older Game Boy classic and Game Boy Pocket. Cartridges that were backwards-compatible with the older hardware kept the traditional Game Boy cartridge shape, but were colored black instead of the traditional gray. Games exclusive to the Color, however, were released in a clear cartridge with a bulging extraction grip, as opposed to the traditional indented one.

==Launch Titles==

===Japan===
* [[Games/Dragon_Warrior_Monsters|Dragon Warrior Monsters]]
* [[Games/Hexcite_The_Shapes_of_Victory|Hexcite]]
* Pocket Bowling
* [[Games/Tetris_DX|Tetris DX]]
* [[Games/Wario_Land_II|Wario Land II]]

===North America===
* [[Games/Centipede|Centipede]]
* [[Games/Game_And_Watch_Gallery_2|Game andamp;amp;amp; Watch Gallery 2]]
* [[Games/Pocket_Bomberman|Pocket Bomberman]]
* [[Games/Tetris_DX|Tetris DX]]

===Europe===
* [[Games/Tetris_DX|Tetris DX]]
* [[Games/Game_And_Watch_Gallery_2|Game and Watch Gallery 2]]
* [[Games/Centipede|Centipede]]
* [[Games/Pocket_Bomberman|Pocket Bomberman]]

==Hardware Specifications==
* Processor - Similar to the Z80, manufactured by Sharp with some bit manipulation
* Clock Speed - 8 MHz
* Memory - 32 kilobytes of system RAM, 16 kilobytes of video RAM
* Screen Resolution - 160x144 pixels
* Colors - 56 simultaneously onscreen from a palette of 32,768 colors

===Colors===
Several different colors of the system was produced, many being limited or special editions.
http://www.giantbomb.com/a/uploads/original/0/7465/813166-10351_gbc.jpg * Berry
* Grape
* Kiwi
* Dandelion
* Teal
* Atomic Purple
* [[Games/Pokemon_Gold_Silver|Pokémon Gold/Silver]] edition
* [[Franchises/Pokemon|Pokémon]] edition
* Pokémon Center edition
* [[Franchises/Hello_Kitty|Hello Kitty]] edition (Japan only)
* Clear (Japan only)
* Clear black
* Clear green (Japan only)
* Midnight blue
* Ice blue
* Clear orange (Japan only)
* Clear blue
* Tommy Hilfiger Edition

==Games==
The Game Boy Color featured an extremely robust library. Over the life of the system, [[Games/Pokemon_Gold_Silver|Pokemon Gold/Silver]] and [[Games/The_Legend_of_Zelda_Oracle_of_Seasons|The Legend of Zelda: Oracle of Seasons]] [[Games/The_Legend_of_Zelda_Oracle_of_Ages|/ Oracle Of Ages]] emerged as the best-sellers, selling 14.51 million and 7.92 million copies, respectively.</text>
      <sha1>f0z9flx5p80dco69n08547732d40dcj</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>Platforms/Game Com</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>456639</id>
    <revision>
      <id>797204</id>
      <parentid>752608</parentid>
      <timestamp>2026-03-21T00:53:06Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Marino</username>
        <id>8</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>Undo revision [[Special:Diff/752608|752608]] by [[Special:Contributions/Giantbomb|Giantbomb]] ([[User talk:Giantbomb|talk]])</comment>
      <origin>797204</origin>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text bytes="4992" sha1="h6thp4t4sehi5ntk62sxd24m7wcsux3" xml:space="preserve">{{Platform
|Name=Game.com
|Guid=3045-77
|Image=https://www.giantbomb.com/a/uploads/scale_super/0/4647/2954597-tiger-game-com-fl.jpg
|Deck=Tiger's second short-lived portable console was a video game and PDA hybrid
|ShortName=GCOM
|ReleaseDate=1997-09-12
|ReleaseDateType=Month
|InstallBase=300,000
|OnlineSupport=No
|OriginalPrice=69.99
|Manufacturer=Companies/Tiger_Electronics_Inc
}}
&lt;div id='imageData' data-json='{"infobox":{"file":"2954597-tiger-game-com-fl.jpg","path":"0\/4647\/","mime":"image\/jpeg","sizes":"square_small,scale_super,square_tiny,square_medium,scale_medium,scale_small,square_mini,scale_avatar,square_avatar,scale_large,screen_kubrick,screen_medium","caption":null},"background":[]}' /&gt;

==Overview==
The Game.com (pronounced Game Com), released in 1997, was [[Companies/Tiger_Electronics_Inc|Tiger Electronics]]'s attempt at creating a handheld that could directly compete with [[Companies/Nintendo|Nintendo]]'s [[Platforms/Game_Boy|Game Boy]]. It sported a few features that were years ahead of their time, including a [[Concepts/Touch_Controls|touch screen]], two cartridge ports (although later models did eventually move back to a single port), and internet connectivity through an optional 14.4 kb/s modem.

==Launch Games==
* [[Games/Duke_Nukem_3D|Duke Nukem 3D]]
* [[Games/Indy_500_1995|Indy 500]]
* [[Games/Lights_Out|Lights Out]]
* [[Games/Mortal_Kombat_Trilogy|Mortal Kombat Trilogy]]
* [[Games/Tiger_Casino|Tiger Casino]]

==History==
Tiger was primarily a producer of single-game LCD handhelds, based on popular film, television, and videogame licenses. They released cartridge based [[Platforms/R_Zone|R-Zone]] in 1995, but it was short-lived, as the [[Platforms/Game_Boy|Game Boy]] dominated the handheld market, and Tiger's simpler titles were less appealing to gamers. In an attempt to compete directly with the Game Boy, Tiger released the Game.com in 1997 with a puzzle title, [[Games/Lights_Out|Lights Out]], as the pack-in game. IP license agreements secured for the portable LCD games remained in effect, which Tiger expected to fully leverage on the Game.com. Popular console titles such as [[Games/Mortal_Kombat_Trilogy|Mortal Kombat Trilogy]], [[Games/Williams_Arcade_Classics|Williams Arcade Classics]], [[Games/Sonic_Jam|Sonic Jam]], and [[Games/Fighters_Megamix|Fighters Megamix]] were released either at launch or shortly after alongside adaptations of popular Tiger handheld products including Henry and Quiz Wiz, plus a promotional booklet teased ports of [[Games/Road_Rash|Road Rash]], [[Companies/EA_Sports|EA Sports]] titles and games based on upcoming films such as [[Games/Batman_And_Robin|Batman andamp;amp;amp; Robin]] and [[Games/The_Lost_World_Jurassic_Park|The Lost World: Jurrasic Park]](few of which were actually released).
Additionally, the Game.com was to be the first handheld system to feature internet connectivity. This was, in fact, the handheld's main selling point. Internet connectivity would prove difficult, however, as access required a phone cord and jack, as well as a bulky external modem. Users were required to use Tiger's own ISP to get online with the devices. Like most WAP-enabled devices of the day, the Game.com was equipped with a text-based web browser that allowed users to access online scoreboards and other WAP and Game.com specific content. Users could also check their email through the service, but due to the high cost of getting the Game.com online, adoption rates for the console's online services were low.
Later in the console's lifespan, Tiger released a new, smaller version called the Game.com Pocket Pro. It features a smaller screen, one cartridge port, a lit screen (in the first few production runs), and eliminated the console's online functionality. New games, including ports of [[Games/Resident_Evil_2|Resident Evil 2]] and the modernized versions of [[Games/Centipede_1998|Centipede]] and [[Games/Frogger_1997|Frogger]], were released alongside the console. In 2000, when both the original Game.com and the Pocket Pro failed in the marketplace, Tiger pulled support, leaving games such as [[Games/Metal_Gear_Solid|Metal Gear Solid]], [[Games/Castlevania_Symphony_of_the_Night|Castlevania: Symphony of the Night]], Giga Pets, and [[Games/George_Foremans_KO_Boxing|Foreman Boxing]] (supposedly with force feedback capabilities) unfinished.

==Legacy==
While the console was a commercial failure, internet capabilities in handheld gaming devices became a popular feature in later handheld consoles. The console also featured a touch screen before the [[Platforms/Nintendo_DS|Nintendo DS]] made touch-screen gaming popular in the handheld market. The console's failure caused Tiger to leave the gaming market and focus on developing consumer electronics aimed at children.

==Emulation==
In 2005, an online group referring to themselves as the "game.commies" announced they would be working on hacking the game.com platform to enable emulation. An emulator was released in 2011.</text>
      <sha1>h6thp4t4sehi5ntk62sxd24m7wcsux3</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>Platforms/Game Gear</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>456579</id>
    <revision>
      <id>797137</id>
      <parentid>797136</parentid>
      <timestamp>2026-03-20T23:15:20Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Frobie</username>
        <id>300</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>change month desgination to full</comment>
      <origin>797137</origin>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text bytes="2826" sha1="k6k1xurs7qndxrtv9p9yp9w7taumeaj" xml:space="preserve">{{Platform
|Guid=3045-5
|Name=Game Gear
|Aliases=Sega Game Gear,Mercury
|Image=https://www.giantbomb.com/a/uploads/scale_super/0/1992/1426271-logo.jpg
|Deck=Sega's first hand held video game system.  It was the portable version of the Master System.
|ShortName=GG
|ReleaseDateType=Full
|ReleaseDate=1990-10-06
|InstallBase=14,000,000
|OnlineSupport=No
|OriginalPrice=149.99
|Manufacturer=Companies/Sega
}}
==Overview==
[[Companies/Sega|Sega]] Game Gear came out in the U.S. in 1991. Work originally began on the console in 1989 under the codename "Project Mercury", following Sega's policy at the time of codenaming their systems after planets. Like the [[Platforms/Sega_Master_System|Sega Master System]], it was an [[Concepts/8_bit|8-bit]] system. It was only the third commercially available color handheld console, after the [[Platforms/Atari_Lynx|Atari Lynx]] and the TurboExpress. .It could run on 6-AA batteries or an AC adapter could be used to plug the GG into the wall or outlet. It came packaged with ''[[Games/Columns|''Columns'']]'' a "[[Games/Tetris|Tetris]] type" game, in which you have to match the colored blocks as opposed to making lines.
The GG had many accessories. One of them was a TV tuner, which no longer works as of February 2000. Rechargable battery packs to help make the GG portable and not make you keep buying AA batteries every 2 hours, master gear converter to play Master System cartridges on the GG, a car adapter for playing in the car without batteries, and much more.
Originally only available in black, the GG was available in other colors. A Japan only release of an ultra-limited (10,000 units) white console in a special metal game case and TV Tuner was available soon after launch. Later a special blue sports themed version and a Coca-cola Red version were available in the US.
The Game Gear was built as a "landscape" hand-held. This meant that the D-pad and buttons were to the sides of the screen as opposed to being at the bottom like the [[Platforms/Game_Boy|Game Boy]]. This made the GG a lot more comfortable to hold because you hands were not so close and crammed together. The Game Gear ultimately played second fiddle to the Game Boy and despite being more popular in Europe it still became the first Sega product to be beaten in sales by a competing [[Companies/Nintendo|Nintendo]] product in the region.

==Launch==

===Japan - October 6, 1990===
* [[Games/Columns|Columns]]
* [[Games/Pengo_4196|Pengo]]
* [[Games/Super_Monaco_GP|Super Monaco GP]]

===North America - April 26, 1991===
* [[Games/Castle_of_Illusion_starring_Mickey_Mouse|Castle of Illusion starring Mickey Mouse]]
* [[Games/Columns|Columns]]
* [[Games/G_LOC_Air_Battle|G-Loc]]
* [[Games/Psychic_World|Psychic World]]
* [[Games/Wonder_Boy|Revenge of Drancon]]
* [[Games/Super_Monaco_GP|Super Monaco GP]]</text>
      <sha1>k6k1xurs7qndxrtv9p9yp9w7taumeaj</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>Platforms/Game Master</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>456718</id>
    <revision>
      <id>738698</id>
      <parentid>722572</parentid>
      <timestamp>2026-02-25T20:37:17Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Marino</username>
        <id>8</id>
      </contributor>
      <origin>738698</origin>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text bytes="525" sha1="5cd73yed9uytc9m6t979oaeiy8seimj" xml:space="preserve">{{Platform
|Name=Game Master
|Guid=3045-158
|Aliases=Systema 2000,Super Game
|Image=https://www.giantbomb.com/a/uploads/scale_super/0/26/2780052-hgm.jpg
|Deck=The Hartung Game Master is a monochrome handheld gaming machine that was marketed under different names, including the Systema 2000 and Super Game.
|ShortName=HGM
|ReleaseDate=1990
|ReleaseDateType=Year
|OnlineSupport=No
|Manufacturer=Companies/Hartung
}}

 The Hartung Game Master was originally released in Germany in 1990. 18 games were produced for the platform.</text>
      <sha1>5cd73yed9uytc9m6t979oaeiy8seimj</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>Platforms/Game Wave</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>456666</id>
    <revision>
      <id>738571</id>
      <parentid>722503</parentid>
      <timestamp>2026-02-24T18:34:38Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Marino</username>
        <id>8</id>
      </contributor>
      <origin>738571</origin>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text bytes="3581" sha1="71uy5qk1ua96eh98s3cnqlb39w9aq51" xml:space="preserve">{{Platform
|Name=Game Wave
|Guid=3045-105
|Image=https://www.giantbomb.com/a/uploads/scale_super/0/4647/2954589-game-wave-console-set-fl.jpg
|Deck=The Game Wave Family Entertainment System is a simple DVD-based game platform from ZAPiT Games.
|ShortName=GWAV
|ReleaseDate=October 2005
|ReleaseDateType=Month
|InstallBase=70,000
|OriginalPrice=99.99
|Manufacturer=Companies/ZAPiT_Games
}}
&lt;div id='imageData' data-json='{"infobox":{"file":"2954589-game-wave-console-set-fl.jpg","path":"0\/4647\/","mime":"image\/jpeg","sizes":"scale_medium,scale_super,square_small,square_medium,scale_small,square_tiny,square_mini,square_avatar,scale_large,screen_medium,scale_avatar,screen_kubrick","caption":null},"background":[]}' /&gt;

==Overview==
The [[Companies/ZAPiT_Games|ZAPiT]] Game Wave Family Entertainment System is a family-oriented video game console released October 2005 in [[Locations/Canada|Canada]].  The console is meant to provide an alternative to traditional game consoles by being a console meant for family settings with a software library almost exclusively for non-gamers.  Game Wave uses up to six proprietary remote controls, which resemble TV remotes, to give non-gamer players a familiar tool to control the game with.  Most games are [[Concepts/Spin_Off|spinoffs]] of popular board games or trivia games.  Games are on DVD media and the limited control system means games must be must more straightforward than traditional games, so it is unlikely games such as action games or RPGs will ever be released on the Game Wave.  One of the main advertised features of the Game Wave is that six players can play simultaneously, so there is no waiting for turns such as in a board game.


==Hardware==
The Game Wave console doubles as a DVD player and comes standard with four wireless remotes for an MSRP of $99.  The console comes bundled with the game [[Games/4_Degrees_Vol_1|4 Degrees: The Arc of Trivia, Vol. 1]].  Two extra controllers are available for $30.  The console itself supports either composite or S-Video output and recognizes up to 6 of the color-coded controllers.  On the side of the console are six slots that hold the controllers.  None of the controllers take precedence over any of the others, so any controller can control movies or game menus.  The system is not very powerful and graphics are colorful, but often simple 2D mixed with text.

In the Bilmar Station Sports Tavern of Tampa, FL there is a prototype coin-op Game Wave system.  It's a 4-player arcade game that has all of the Game Wave games built in, as well as others such as Texas Hold 'Em.  The game is a redemption game but players are ''not ''rewarded with tickets individually.  Presumably the winner of the game gets the tickets.


==Software==
Game Wave software is largely based around trivia, word games, and simple board games, as the console is not powerful enough, nor does the control scheme lend itself to more complex games.  Being marketed as a family console, every game supports multiplayer for six players.  Every game is also developed and published by [[Companies/ZAPiT_Games|ZAPiT Games]] and carries an MSRP of $24.99.  The Game Wave currently has variations of [[Games/Boggle|Boggle]], [[Games/Yahtzee|Yahtzee]], [[Games/Hangman|Hangman]], [[Games/Blackjack_1978|Blackjack]], Sudoku, and [[Games/Scrabble|Scrabble]].  There are also six various trivia games, three of which are based on recent history.  Each trivia game claims to offer up to 25 hours of play without repeat questions.  New software from ZAPiT games does not appear likely.</text>
      <sha1>71uy5qk1ua96eh98s3cnqlb39w9aq51</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>Platforms/Genesis</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>456580</id>
    <revision>
      <id>797138</id>
      <parentid>752560</parentid>
      <timestamp>2026-03-20T23:16:13Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Frobie</username>
        <id>300</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>Undo revision [[Special:Diff/752560|752560]] by [[Special:Contributions/Giantbomb|Giantbomb]] ([[User talk:Giantbomb|talk]])</comment>
      <origin>797138</origin>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text bytes="16767" sha1="et4rmnigw8t8lgircp3qae01tptxhq4" xml:space="preserve">{{Platform
|Name=Genesis
|Guid=3045-6
|Aliases=Sega Mega Drive,Sega Genesis,Sega Nomad,Mark V,Venus
|Image=https://www.giantbomb.com/a/uploads/scale_super/0/26/10576-genesis.jpg
|Deck=After the cult success of their 8-bit Master System, Sega decided to give gamers a taste of their arcade capabilities with a 16-bit console. Known worldwide as the Mega Drive but called Genesis in the US, it provided graphics and sound a couple of steps below their popular System 16 arcade cabinets. The Mega Drive/Genesis turned out to be Sega's most successful console.
|ShortName=GEN
|ReleaseDate=1988-10-29
|InstallBase=30,750,000
|OnlineSupport=Yes
|OriginalPrice=189.99
|Manufacturer=Companies/Sega
}}

==Overview==
https://www.giantbomb.com/a/uploads/original/0/8153/1084124-800px_sega_genesis_original_model.jpg Released as the Sega Mega Drive in [[Locations/Japan|Japan]], [[Locations/Europe|Europe]], [[Locations/South_America|South America]], and [[Locations/Oceania|Oceania]], and as the Sega Genesis in [[Locations/North_America|North America]], it is [[Companies/Sega|Sega]]'s 16-bit console. It was the successor of the 8-bit [[Platforms/Sega_Master_System|Sega Master System]] and predecessor to the 32-bit [[Platforms/Saturn|Sega Saturn]].
The console hardware had both a 16-bit Motorola 86000 for the main console CPU, and 8-bit Zilog Z80 CPU for the sound chip. Both CPU chips were commonly used together in Sega[[Platforms/Arcade|arcade]] cabinets at the time--as well as arcade cabinets in general during the late 80s and early 90s. Sega's goal was to give home consumers a taste of arcade quality gameplay, made popular by their System-16 arcade cabinets, where hit games like [[Games/Golden_Axe|Golden Axe]], [[Games/Altered_Beast|Altered Beast]], and [[Games/Alien_Syndrome_1986|Alien Syndrome]]were frequently played in the arcades. An image from the video game Altered Beast was even used as the console box art, to help market it as a 16-bit arcade console. The console was not as powerful as their System-16 and future 16-bit arcade cabinets, however. The console used a 9-bit color palette, compared to a 16-bit color palette used in their early 16-bit arcade cabinets. The console could only display 80 sprites on screen, compared to the 128 sprites from their System 16 cabinets. Sega also used a lower grade version of the sound chips used in most arcade cabinets at the time. The basic structure, however, allowed for many good (but not perfect) arcade ports of their games, as well as games from other developers.
It had a production run lasting from 1988, when it was first released in Japan, to 1997, when it was finally discontinued. It sold [http://vgsales.wikia.com/wiki/Fourth_generation_of_video_games over 40 million units] worldwide, over half of which were sold in [[Locations/North_America|North America]] alone. While its performance in Japan was underwhelming, coming third place behind both the [[Objects/SNES|SNES]] and [[Platforms/TurboGrafx_16|PC Engine]], the Mega Drive was Sega's most successful console worldwide, outselling the SNES in the overseas territories of North America, Europe, South America, Oceania, and [[Locations/South_Korea|South Korea]].
The console's best-selling stand-alone game was [[Games/Sonic_the_Hedgehog_2|''Sonic the Hedgehog 2'',]] with over 6 million cartridges sold, while its best-selling bundled game was the original ''[[Games/Sonic_the_Hedgehog|Sonic the Hedgehog]]'', with over 15 million units sold.
https://www.giantbomb.com/a/uploads/original/0/8153/1084009-sonic_the_hedgehog_2.jpg To make it seem cooler than its main rival, the [[Platforms/Super_Nintendo_Entertainment_System|Super Nintendo Entertainment System]] (SNES), Sega's Marketing Department came up with the term "Blast Processing" to imply that the Genesis/Mega Drive had more power and was more capable of rendering sprites on screen faster than the SNES. While "Blast Processing" was purely a marketing term, the Genesis/Mega Drive did in actuality run at a higher clock speed than the SNES, enabling many games to feature fast scrolling (often with many background layers in parallax) and a large number of sprites on screen.
During its nine-year production run, it was expanded upon numerous times. These add-ons included the [[Accessories/Power_Base_Converter|Power Base Converter]], allowing it to play 8-bit Master System games, as well as the [[Platforms/Sega_CD|Sega CD]] and the [[Platforms/Sega_32X|32X]]. Additionally, two later models of the Genesis were released.
https://www.giantbomb.com/a/uploads/original/0/8153/1084017-genesisb.jpg The Genesis had two main versions of its controller. The first was slightly larger than the other, with three face buttons and a slightly "sharp," hard-plastic thumb pad. Although this controller was initially well-received, as the popularity of games like [[Games/Street_Fighter_II_The_World_Warrior|Street Fighter II]] rose, there was demand to produce a six-button controller.
Sega finally did release a six-button controller with a slightly streamlined look and feel, a softer thumb pad, and naturally three more face buttons. Many later Genesis games recommended the use of this secondary controller (many of them fighting games), as games that were played with the original controller and designed for the new six-button one would need to tap the start button to switch the three face buttons to the function of the other three.

==Accessories==
https://www.giantbomb.com/a/uploads/original/13/139866/2720463-4113433581-XE1AP.jpg The Sega Mega Drive/Genesis supported the following accessories:
* '''[[Accessories/XE_1AP|XE-1AP]]''', released by [[Companies/Dempa_Micomsoft|Dempa Micomsoft]] only for Japan in 1989. It featured an analog thumbstick, analog slider, four shoulder buttons, and two grip handles. It was supported by [https://www.giantbomb.com/after-burner-ii/3030-2139 After Burner II] (1990), [https://www.giantbomb.com/ayrton-sennas-super-monaco-gp-ii/3030-8935 Ayrton Senna's Super Monaco GP II] (1992), Fastest 1 (1991), [https://www.giantbomb.com/galaxy-force-ii/3030-8320 Galaxy Force II] (1991), and [https://www.giantbomb.com/musha/3030-7928 Musha Aleste] (1990).
* '''[[Accessories/Sega_Activator|Sega Activator]]''', released by Sega in 1993. It allowed full-body [[Concepts/Motion_Control|motion control]], but had limited motion detection.
* '''[[Accessories/Sega_VR|Sega VR]]''', planned for release in 1994 but eventually cancelled. It was a [[Concepts/Virtual_Reality|virtual reality]] headset with [[Concepts/Head_Tracking|head-tracking]] capabilities.

==Network and Cable Support==
In Japan, the Sega Mega Drive had network service available beginning in 1991. In order to use the service, players had to attach a Mega modem (which had a connection speed ranging from 1,600 to 2,400 bits/s) to the DE-9 port on the console. The few games available for download onto the Mega Drive were [[Games/Sonic_Eraser|Sonic Eraser]] and [[Games/Phantasy_Star_II_Text_Adventure_Eusis_no_Bouken|Phantasy Star II Text Adventures]]. In 1995, the service reached Brazil, where two more games were available: [[Games/Mortal_Kombat_II|Mortal Kombat II]] and [[Games/FIFA_Soccer_95|Fifa Soccer '95]]. The service was not successful, and was eventually discontinued.
https://www.giantbomb.com/a/uploads/original/0/8153/959869-sega_channel_1jpgjpg.jpg Despite this, Sega teamed up with TCI and [[Companies/Time_Warner_Interactive_Inc|Time Warner]] in 1994 to release the Sega Channel in the [[Locations/The_United_States_of_America|United States]]. The Sega Channel was a hardware add-on meant to be placed on top of the Genesis cartridge slot. The add-on allowed players to download games directly to their Sega Genesis consoles and play the games for a monthly fee. They did this by connecting a coaxial cable (the same kind used on cable boxes) to the back of the cartridge add-on. One could then choose to browse games from a variety of menus. Categories like shooter, role playing, platforming, etc. contained many popular Genesis titles people could download and play. After 30 days the games available would change. Usually, the most popular games were kept in service while the games people hardly played were replaced with other games. The Sega Channel also kept track of new games that were released. The games were usually available a month after their official release dates. Japanese import games were also available to subscribers. The activation fee was $29.95, and the monthly fee was $14.95. The service lasted until 1998, when the 32-bit era was established with the Sega Saturn, and the [[Platforms/PlayStation|Sony PlayStation]]. The Sega Channel was also the only way American gamers could play the Genesis last two best games, [[Games/Alien_Soldier|Alien Soldier]] and [[Games/Pulseman|Pulseman]].

==Sega Genesis Nomad==
https://www.giantbomb.com/a/uploads/original/1/18617/1096731-sega_nomad_2s.jpg The Sega Nomad was a failed handheld version of the Genesis console. Released in October of 1995 at a price of $180 USD, the Nomad featured a 3.25 inch color screen and ran on six AA batteries.
Interestingly, the Nomad was a fully functional Genesis home console in addition to being a handheld device. Television connectivity was provided through an A/V slot on top of the unit. For single player games, the Nomad itself functioned as the controller, but two player gaming was possible using a controller port on the bottom of the device. This port accepted standard Genesis controllers.
The Nomad suffered from problems that plagued Sega's other handheld, the 8-bit [[Platforms/Game_Gear|Game Gear]]. Both machines were notoriously power-hungry thanks to their (relatively) powerful processors and high quality backlit LCD screens. The Nomad was capable of depleting its batteries in two hours, which lessened its appeal as a portable device. Additionally, despite being advertised as a wholly-capable Genesis console, the Nomad was functionally incompatible with the various Genesis add-ons Sega had released such as the [[Platforms/Sega_CD|Sega CD]] and [[Platforms/Sega_32X|32X]]. These compatibility problems were due to the shape of the Nomad, and the inability to mount these accessories on its portable form factor.
Faced with competition from Nintendo's hugely successful Game Boy, the Nomad faltered at market. By the time Sega ceased production, it had only managed to sell 1 million units.

==PC/Mega Drive Hybrids==
https://www.giantbomb.com/a/uploads/original/1/12063/2902949-1704098014-amstr.jpg In an effort to sell the Genesis hardware to a wider audience, two different PC and Mega Drive hybrid computers were created: the ''TeraDrive'' in Japan (manufactured by IBM), and the ''Mega PC''in Europe (manufactured by Amstrad).
While the Mega PC was an isolated ISA card that could only be used when the PC was inactive, the TeraDrive hardware allowed PC software and Mega Drive games to interact with each other.
Unfortunately, both the TeraDrive and the Mega PC were hampered by low spec PC hardware (286 and 386SX respectively) that had to compete against 486 and Pentium-based PCs.
 
 

==Launch Titles==

===United States===
The Sega Genesis launched along with the following 7 games in the US August 14th 1989.
* [[Games/Space_Harrier_II|Space Harrier II]]
* [[Games/Thunder_Force_II|Thunder Force II]]
* [[Games/Tommy_Lasorda_Baseball|Tommy Lasorda Baseball]]
* [[Games/Last_Battle|Last Battle]]
* [[Games/Altered_Beast|Altered Beast]]
* [[Games/Alex_Kidd_in_the_Enchanted_Castle|Alex Kidd in The Enchanted Castle]]
* [[Games/Ghouls_N_Ghosts|Ghouls n' Ghosts]]

==Hardware Specifications==

===CPU (Central Processing Unit)===
* Main Processor Unit: Motorola 68000 at 7.67 MHz
* Secondary Processor Unit: Zilog Z80 at 3.58 MHz
'''Note: '''The Zilog Z80 is used to control the sound chip.

===Graphics===
* Maximum Color Palette: 512 (9-bit color)
* 64 colors on screen at once
* Maximum Sprites On Screen: 80
* Screen Resolution: 256 x 192 - 320 x 448
* Possible AV Outputs * RF (Radio Frequency Unit with Coaxial Cable)
* Composite (RCA Cable)
* RGB (RGB SCART Cable)

===Sound===
* Yamaha 2612 Sound Chip * 6 Channel FM (Frequency Modulation) at 7.67 MHz
* Texas Instrument Programmable Sound Generator (version Ti-SN76489) * 4 Channels at 3.58 MHz
* Sample Rate 22 KHz
'''Note:''' The sixth FM channel on the YM-2612 can be used as a 8-bit PCM. Doing so disables the FM channel.
'''Note: '''The original sample rate of the YM-2612 was 52KHz, however the sound chip was compressed down to 22KHz on the original Model 1 Genesis. Model 2 had both compression and a filter added to mask the distortion caused by lowering the original sample rate. Unfortunately, this didn't work. This is why you hear little distortion on the Model 1 Genesis, and a lot of distortion on the Model 2 version, which eliminated the direct headphone link to the sound chip, and relied on stereo RCA cables instead. Later revisions fixed some of the sound issues.
'''Note:''' The PSG Ti-SN76489 was the same sound chip used in the Sega Master System. This allowed backwards compatibility with the Genesis. This option, however, was abandoned by the time Model 2 was released and became the norm.

===Memory===
* Main Memory: 64KB
* Video Memory: 64KB
* Sound Memory: 8KB (from Z80)

===Nomad Specifications:===

{| class='wikitable' style='margin:auto;width:100%;'
|-
| Processor:||Motorola 68000 16 bit processor running at 7.67 MHz
|-
| Co-processor (Sound Controller):||Zilog Z80 8-bit at 3.58 MHz
|-
| Memory:||156KB total - 64 KB Main RAM, 64KB VRAM, 8KB Sound RAM. 20 Kb ROM
|-
| Display Palette:||512
|-
| Onscreen colors:||64
|-
| Maximum onscreen sprites:||80
|-
| Resolution:||320 × 224
|-
| Sound:||Yamaha YM2612 6 channel FM, additional 4 channel PSG. Stereo sound. Also Texas Instruments SN76489 PSG ( Programmable Sound Generator)
|-
| Display:||Integrated CSTN LCD at 320 x 224
|-
| Power Rating:||9V 850mA (same as Genesis/Mega Drive model 2)
|}


==Model Versions==

===Model 1===
https://www.giantbomb.com/a/uploads/original/0/8153/1084011-segagenesis1.jpg Model 1 is the original design of the Sega Genesis. It has the logo High Definition Graphics above the Sega Genesis label. It has a headphone jack input for stereo sound. Model 1 only supported RF and Mono Composite outputs like the original [[Platforms/Nintendo_Entertainment_System|Nintendo]]. It has an expansion port for hardware add-ons for things like the [[Platforms/Sega_CD|Sega CD]].

===Model 2===
https://www.giantbomb.com/a/uploads/original/0/8153/1084012-sega_genesis2_1.jpg Model 2 was the redesign of the Sega Genesis, shortly after the Super Nintendo became popular. It got rid of the headphone inputs, as this model supported full stereo composite and component outputs. Sadly, the redesign of the circuits caused a sound distortion that made the quality poor. Later, the sound issues were [http://www.sega-16.com/forum/showthread.php?7796-GUIDE-Telling-apart-good-Genesis-1s-and-Genesis-2s-from-bad-ones improved somewhat] with the VA3 &amp;amp; VA4 motherboards. The Sega CD was also redesigned for Model 2 to fit the new look.

===Model 3===
https://www.giantbomb.com/a/uploads/original/0/8153/1084013-genesis3led.jpg Model 3 came out during the 32-bit era. It's a compact version of the Sega Genesis. It has no expansion slot for add-ons. However, it does have output support for S-Video, which separates the color signal from the contrast making the picture quality much better. S-Video inputs can be found on all modern television sets.

===Model 4===
Sega Genesis 4. also known as Firecore and Blaze Mega Drive, released in 2008, is an officially licensed console using an [[Concepts/Emulation|software emulator]] rather than actual hardware, and comes with a selection of games preinstalled (the number varies by region - the US release has 20 games, the European Blaze console has 15), as well as a slot to play Genesis cartridges. It does not support the [[Platforms/Sega_CD|Sega CD]] or [[Platforms/Sega_32X|32X]]. The emulator has a number of compatibility problems, such as being unable to play the music for some cartridge based games, most notably Sonic the Hedgehog 1 and 2.
In [[Locations/Brazil|Brazil]] another console using model number 4 exists, [[Companies/Tec_Toy_Industria_de_Brinquedos_S_A|TecToy]] Mega Drive 4, which like the Firecore/Blaze uses emulation rather than original hardware, but lacks a cartridge slot, and instead has 87 games pre-installed, some of which are ports of more recent titles, like [[Games/The_Sims_2|The Sims 2]] and [[Games/FIFA_Soccer_08|FIFA Soccer 08]], as well as an [[Franchises/Guitar_Hero|Guitar Hero]] clone titled Guitar Idol. It does support SD cards for MP3 playback and Rom files.</text>
      <sha1>et4rmnigw8t8lgircp3qae01tptxhq4</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>Platforms/Gizmondo</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>456640</id>
    <revision>
      <id>797225</id>
      <parentid>752609</parentid>
      <timestamp>2026-03-21T01:00:39Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Frobie</username>
        <id>300</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>Undo revision [[Special:Diff/752609|752609]] by [[Special:Contributions/Giantbomb|Giantbomb]] ([[User talk:Giantbomb|talk]])</comment>
      <origin>797225</origin>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text bytes="7256" sha1="7k2vfgejony2u0llrzc2d2pfmszps1z" xml:space="preserve">{{Platform
|Name=Gizmondo
|Guid=3045-78
|Image=https://www.giantbomb.com/a/uploads/scale_super/0/26/10602-gizmondo.jpg
|Deck=The Gizmondo is a failed handheld console, which launched in 2005. It was potentially revolutionary for having functionality such as GPRS mobile data connection, a camera, GPS, a multimedia player and of course game playing all in one unit.
|ShortName=GIZ
|ReleaseDate=2005-03-19
|ReleaseDateType=Month
|InstallBase=25,000
|OnlineSupport=Yes
|OriginalPrice=229.99
|Manufacturer=Companies/Gizmondo_Europe_Ltd
}}
&lt;div id='imageData' data-json='{"infobox":{"file":"10602-gizmondo.jpg","path":"0\/26\/","mime":"image\/jpeg","sizes":"scale_medium,scale_super,square_mini,square_medium,square_small,screen_medium,square_avatar,square_tiny,scale_small,scale_large,scale_avatar,screen_kubrick","caption":"Gizmondo"},"background":{"file":"790753-gizmondo_logo.jpg","path":"1\/14036\/","mime":"image\/jpeg","sizes":"square_avatar,scale_small,square_tiny,square_medium,scale_medium,screen_medium,scale_large,scale_avatar,square_mini,square_small,screen_kubrick_wide,scale_super,screen_kubrick","caption":"Gizmondo ~ Logo"}}' /&gt;

==History==
Originally announced as the Gametrac, before being renamed after [[Games/Gametrak_Dark_Wind|Gametrak]] discovered the name and complained that the name breached their copyright, the Gizmondo was a multi-function handheld games device launched by a UK subsidiary of US-based Tiger Telematics in 2005. The device was intended to compete against [[Companies/Sony_Interactive_Entertainment|Sony's]] [[Platforms/PlayStation_Portable|PSP]] and [[Companies/Nintendo|Nintendo's]] [[Platforms/Nintendo_DS|DS]] but due to a limited release which initially only included the [[Locations/United_Kingdom|UK]] (And only select retailers at that) and later limited availability in the [[Locations/The_United_States_of_America|USA]], the console floundered.
The initial release of the console saw only two games, [[Games/Fathammer_Classics_Pack|Fathammer Classics Pack]] (A collection of 3 games from the [[Companies/Fathammer_Ltd|Fathammer]] games line) and [[Games/Trailblazer|Trailblazer]]. The latter game was more popular with users and throughout the life of the platform was one of if not the most popular game in the community. Gizmondo promised to bring more games including some which made use of the console's unique features ([[Games/Colors|Colors]] promised GPS-powered "Turf Wars" where players could fight for control of real-life areas, Agaju promised to use the camera for FPS controls and other augmented reality features), however only 14 games ever made it to release - and none which made use of the platform's unique features.
The console was released in the US exclusively through specific Gizmondo mall kiosks. Shortly after the US release, it was discovered that at least one of the big names ([[People/Stefan_Eriksson|Stefan Eriksson]]) behind the company and, by extension, the platform, were members of the Uppsalamaffian, a Swedish mafia. The company never recovered and at any rate had incurred massive losses. To make matters worse, the company began circulating images of an improved Gizmondo before the console even went on sale in the US. The Gizmondo WS (WideScreen) strongly resembled the PSP and its existence angered existing owners (In the UK) because they felt they had bought the wrong machine and were going to be left out in the cold. American buyers were promised "an upgrade path" to the new system, but what this was was never made clear. No such option was ever said to be available to UK customers.
At any rate, the console never emerged and likely never got beyond the concept stage. The company essentially "went dark" shortly after the US launch due to lack of funds and the company finally went into bankruptcy in February of 2006.
Since then, the console has been cracked and the community, lead by [http:/www.gizmondoforums.com GizmondoForums.com], have spent much time porting games, finding and releasing the console's lost commercial games (Chicane: Jenson Button Street Racing, [[Games/Sonic_the_Hedgehog|Sonic the Hedgehog]], Colors, [[Games/Carmageddon|Carmageddon]] and more) and creating all-new games and applications as homebrew efforts.
Some individuals think that the system failed because of its lack of games. With a catalogue of games like [[Games/Alien_Hominid|Alien Hominid]] and [[Games/SSX_3|SSX 3]], the Gizmondo just couldn't compete with cheaper handheld systems like the Nintendo DS.
In 2008, Carl Freer (Gizmondo's Chairman and the platform's corporate champion) announced he had reached an agreement with the liquidators and planned to re-launch the Gizmondo brand with a new console. This eventually came to nothing. The planned new console had been based on the existing hardware, but running open source software.

==The Hardware==
The Gizmondo was essentially a WindowsCE .net HandheldPC, using the embedded OS to run a custom GUI. It sported a 400MHz ARM9 processor, a 2.8" 320x480 TFT screen and an [[Companies/NVIDIA_Corporation|nVidia]] GoForce 3D 4500 GPU (The GPU initially delayed the launch as the developers decided to change from a 2D chip to a 3D to better compete with the specs of the DS and PSP). Other hardware features included a 0.3 Megapixel camera, GPS for navigation &amp;amp; (In select - canceled - games) location-based gameplay and a tri-band GSM radio which was used to supply an internet connection for e-mails and to send and receive SMS/MMS messages. It was also intended to be used for certain aspects of multiplayer, though this largely failed to materialise. Note that whilst it had a SIM Card and a phone number, the console did not support voice calling or any kind of voice communication.
Additionally, the system featured a Bluetooth radio, primarily used for multiplayer gaming. Other I/O included a standard 3.5mm headphone jack (The console also shipped with re-branded Sennheiser earphones), miniUSB and an SD card slot which served as the primary storage for games, movies and music. The system, like those it competed with, used a rechargeable Lithium-Ion battery (Which was notably temperamental, sometimes only providing an hour's use off of a full charge if users did not charge it in regular charge, drain, charge cycles).
The battery was replaced in the US with a larger version to improve battery life. This necessitated a larger battery door, meaning US Gizmondos do not follow the same curvature as UK models - there is a large rectangular bulge. This new battery door also allowed the attaching of a wrist strap (Which was bundled) though. This model was never offered in the UK.

==Smart Adds==
After the initial launch, users could receive a discount on Gizmondo hardware if they agreed to receive targeted, location-based advertising. This was also offered to existing users who received a voucher and accessories gift pack for signing up in lieu of the discount. Despite a system update which added a "Smart Adds" option to the menu, no ads were ever distributed through the service - which meant everyone who had signed up for the service got either a discount or their gift pack for absolutely nothing. Some people think even the thought of this was partially why the system failed.</text>
      <sha1>7k2vfgejony2u0llrzc2d2pfmszps1z</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>Platforms/Google Stadia</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>456733</id>
    <revision>
      <id>738577</id>
      <parentid>738518</parentid>
      <timestamp>2026-02-24T18:45:20Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Marino</username>
        <id>8</id>
      </contributor>
      <origin>738577</origin>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text bytes="3285" sha1="ghbse66arib6edsx8f9s9oedxowkgmj" xml:space="preserve">{{Platform
|Name=Google Stadia
|Guid=3045-175
|Image=https://www.giantbomb.com/a/uploads/scale_super/0/4647/3184321-images.jpg
|Deck=Stadia was a streaming platform for games powered by Google's cloud infrastructure.
|ShortName=STAD
|ReleaseDate=2019-11-19
|InstallBase=750,000
|OnlineSupport=Yes
|OriginalPrice=139.99
|Manufacturer=Companies/Google
}}
&lt;div id='imageData' data-json='{"infobox":{"file":"3184321-images.jpg","path":"0\/4647\/","mime":"image\/jpeg","sizes":"scale_super,scale_avatar,square_medium,scale_medium,scale_small,square_small,screen_kubrick,screen_medium,scale_large,square_mini,square_avatar,square_tiny,scale_tiny","caption":null},"background":{"file":"3144950-tvs_google_stadia_group_sofa_377_r05_disclaimer.png","path":"0\/26\/","mime":"image\/png","sizes":"square_medium,screen_kubrick_wide,scale_super,square_tiny,square_small,scale_medium,scale_tiny,screen_medium,screen_kubrick,square_avatar,scale_small,scale_large,screen_large,screen_tiny,square_mini,ignore_jpg_scale_small,scale_avatar","caption":""}}' /&gt;

==Overview==
Stadia was a streaming platform for games powered by Google's cloud infrastructure. It was unveiled at a keynote during the 2019 Game Developers Conference. It allowed users to play games via a video feed to devices like a Chromecast Ultra, [[Platforms/Android|Android]] phone, or Chrome web browsers.
The Stadia service offered a paid "Pro" tier and a lower-end free tier. Games were for sale on the service as opposed to being part of the subscription.
The service launched with twenty-two games.
Google announced on September 29, 2022 that all Stadia services would end on January 18, 2023. Google refunded all purchases made by those who bought into Stadia at any point.

==Compatibility==
Stadia can be played with a variety of gamepads on a computer, on a TV with a Chromecast Ultra, and on the following mobile devices:
* Pixel 2, 3, 3a, 4, 4a
* Samsung S8, S8+, S8 Active, Note 8
* Samsung S9, S9+, Note 9
* Samsung S10, S10+, Note 10, Note 10+
* Samsung S20, S20+, S20 Ultra
* Asus ROG Phone, ROG Phone II
* Razer Phone, Razer Phone II
'''Note:''' Playing Stadia on a TV requires the Stadia Controller.
See how devices can connect to Stadia in the table below.

{| class='wikitable' style='margin:auto;width:100%;'
|-
! Gamepad type||On TV with Chromecast Ultra||On Google Chrome (version 77 or greater)||Supported phones with Android 10.0 or greater
|-
| '''Stadia Controller'''||Wi-Fi connectivity||USB connectivity||USB connectivity
|-
| '''Keyboard and mouse'''||Currently unavailable||USB &amp;amp; Bluetooth connectivity||Currently unavailable
|-
| '''DualShock 4 Controller'''||Currently unavailable||USB &amp;amp; Bluetooth connectivity||USB &amp;amp; Bluetooth connectivity
|-
| '''Xbox One Controller'''||Currently unavailable||USB &amp;amp; Bluetooth connectivity||USB &amp;amp; Bluetooth connectivity
|-
| '''Xbox One Elite Controller'''||Currently unavailable||USB connectivity||USB connectivity
|-
| '''Xbox Adaptive Controller'''||Currently unavailable||USB &amp;amp; Bluetooth connectivity||USB &amp;amp; Bluetooth connectivity
|-
| '''Xbox 360 Controller'''||Currently unavailable||USB connectivity||USB connectivity
|-
| '''Switch Pro Controller'''||Currently unavailable||USB &amp;amp; Bluetooth connectivity||Currently unavailable
|}</text>
      <sha1>ghbse66arib6edsx8f9s9oedxowkgmj</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>Platforms/Hitachi S1</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>456756</id>
    <revision>
      <id>797241</id>
      <parentid>738732</parentid>
      <timestamp>2026-03-21T01:12:30Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Frobie</username>
        <id>300</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>fix image</comment>
      <origin>797241</origin>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text bytes="539" sha1="tt43q0ms8ssjfwz55a0jj0grscrg8j2" xml:space="preserve">{{Platform
|Guid=3045-198
|Name=Hitachi S1
|Image=https://www.giantbomb.com/a/uploads/original/0/1992/3242271-hitachi-s1-01.png
|Deck=The Hitachi S1 is a home computer that was primarily sold in Japan, but also in parts of Australia. It used proprietary 5.25" floppy disks.
|ShortName=HS1
|ReleaseDateType=Month
|MonthPart=May
|MonthYearPart=1984
|OnlineSupport=No
|Manufacturer=Companies/Hitachi
}}
The Hitachi S1 is a home computer that was primarily sold in Japan, but also in parts of Australia. It used proprietary 5.25" floppy disks.</text>
      <sha1>tt43q0ms8ssjfwz55a0jj0grscrg8j2</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>Platforms/HyperScan</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>456665</id>
    <revision>
      <id>738568</id>
      <parentid>738567</parentid>
      <timestamp>2026-02-24T18:20:00Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Marino</username>
        <id>8</id>
      </contributor>
      <origin>738568</origin>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text bytes="3754" sha1="1x811n923iq3ofwtp4do5jf3rmutz8l" xml:space="preserve">{{Platform
|Name=HyperScan
|Guid=3045-104
|Image=https://www.giantbomb.com/a/uploads/scale_super/0/2681/841197-hyperscan.jpg
|Deck=Mattel's HyperScan allowed players to scan in RFID-equipped cards to bring in new characters, weapons, and powers. It came packaged with X-Men, Spider-Man and Ben 10.
|ShortName=HYPR
|ReleaseDate=October 2006
|ReleaseDateType=Month
|InstallBase=30,000
|OnlineSupport=No
|OriginalPrice=69.99
|Manufacturer=Companies/Mattel_Electronics
}}
&lt;div id='imageData' data-json='{"infobox":{"file":"841197-hyperscan.jpg","path":"0\/2681\/","mime":"image\/jpeg","sizes":"square_avatar,square_small,scale_small,scale_medium,screen_medium,scale_avatar,square_mini,scale_large,square_tiny,square_medium,screen_kubrick_wide,scale_super,screen_kubrick","caption":""},"background":{"file":"841197-hyperscan.jpg","path":"0\/2681\/","mime":"image\/jpeg","sizes":"square_avatar,square_small,scale_small,scale_medium,screen_medium,scale_avatar,square_mini,scale_large,square_tiny,square_medium,screen_kubrick_wide,scale_super,screen_kubrick","caption":""}}' /&gt;

==Overview==
The [[Companies/Mattel_Electronics|Mattel]] HyperScan is Mattel's only entry into the video game market besides the [[Platforms/Intellivision|Intellivision]]. It is the first and only console to use Radio Frequency Identification (RFID) technology. The console reads UDF-format CDs that contain a proprietary executable file with the game file. The idea of the HyperScan was to combine card collecting with video gaming and target an audience of younger children who are not ready for mainstream consoles. When scanned, cards will activate characters or power them up for the game currently being played. Only five games were released for the HyperScan out of seven announced, and the system was discontinued by Mattel in 2008.

==Hardware==
The HyperScan's main feature is an RFID scanner that reads cards and writes data back to them. It retailed for $69.99, with extra controllers for $19.99. The system has a 4x CD-ROM drive and only supports composite video. The 162MHz Sunplus nMedia processor is not very powerful, and the console only has a 2D graphics engine, so none of the five games released have any 3D graphics. The graphics are frowned upon for being excessively choppy and sluggish, and the load times off of the CD-Rom drive are upwards of 20 seconds in games. The system supports up to two players. Each controller is a simple faux analog stick with 4 buttons which was not ergonomically designed at all. The video in the games is compressed using MPEG4, and the audio using MP3.

===Technical Specifications===
''CPU'' - SCore (162 MHz Sunplus mMedia 32-bit RISC processor)
''Video'' - Composite, 2D graphic engine, 640x480 resolution, MPEG4 codec
''Audio'' - MP3 codec, 24 PCM sound channels
''Memory'' - 16 MB SDRAM
''ODD ''- 4x CD-Rom drive &amp;lt;u&amp;gt;&amp;lt;/u&amp;gt;''IO'' - 1x USB 1.1 port, RFID Scanner
''RFID Scanner'' - 13.56 MHz
''RFID Storage'' - 110 bytes (96 bytes of user memory 8 bytes unique ID 6 bytes of one time programmable memory)

==Software==
The HyperScan had seven titles planned, but only five were ever released. Games were mostly 2D fighters and platformers. An [[Games/X_Men_2006|X-Men]] 2D fighting game was included with the console. Other licensed games were available featuring characters from [[Games/Marvel_Heroes|Marvel Heroes]] and [[Games/Ben_10|Ben 10]]. Each game required cards to work, which were to be purchased separately for $14.99 per booster pack of 6 cards. Games retailed for $24.99 and included the game disc, a manual, and a booster pack. [[Franchises/Avatar_The_Last_Airbender|Avatar: The Last Airbender]] and [[Franchises/Nickelodeon|Nickelodeon]] Sports were planned for the HyperScan, but never released.</text>
      <sha1>1x811n923iq3ofwtp4do5jf3rmutz8l</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>Platforms/Intellivision</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>456617</id>
    <revision>
      <id>797208</id>
      <parentid>752593</parentid>
      <timestamp>2026-03-21T00:53:45Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Frobie</username>
        <id>300</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>Undo revision [[Special:Diff/752593|752593]] by [[Special:Contributions/Giantbomb|Giantbomb]] ([[User talk:Giantbomb|talk]])</comment>
      <origin>797208</origin>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text bytes="4051" sha1="1mwpgrdm9hg7msz4gz7lhgyhlxfxhu6" xml:space="preserve">{{Platform
|Name=Intellivision
|Guid=3045-51
|Image=https://www.giantbomb.com/a/uploads/scale_super/0/24/176540-intellivision_small.jpg
|Deck=The Intellivision by Mattel Electronics was a system known for its unique controllers and cutting-edge graphics in the early 1980s, but it was ultimately overshadowed by the technically less powerful, Atari 2600.
|ShortName=INTV
|ReleaseDate=December 1979
|ReleaseDateType=Month
|InstallBase=3,750,000
|OnlineSupport=No
|OriginalPrice=274.99
|Manufacturer=Companies/Mattel_Electronics
}}

==Overview==
The Intellivision was created by [[Companies/Mattel_Electronics|Mattel Electronics]]and released nationwide in 1980 (the system was previously test marketed in the Fresno, CA area in December 1979), with [[Games/Las_Vegas_Poker_And_Blackjack|''Las Vegas ''Poker andamp;amp;amp; Blackjack]]as the pack-in game. In late 1982, the pack-in was changed to[[Games/Astrosmash|Astrosmash]]. Most of the marketing campaign focused on comparing the Intellivision to the [[Platforms/Atari_2600|Atari 2600]], demonstrating the Intellivision's graphical and technological superiority.
The console had its cartridge slot on the right side of the system, and the top was utilized for controller storage. The controllers were permanently attached with coiled cords, and featured a numeric keypad, a circular pad that detected 16 directions, and four rubber buttons on the sides of the controller. Most games came with small plastic overlays that could be inserted into the controller over the keypad, to help players learn and remember game controls. One disadvantage to the controller was its inability to use the disc and keypad inputs at the same time, making "run &amp;amp; gun" tactics difficult for games that used the disc for movement and the keypad for firing. The most popular solution to this problem involved using one controller's disc to move and the other controller's keypad to shoot. The controller's side buttons posed another problem, as they were very stiff and unresponsive, making games that utilized them difficult, and extended gameplay painful on thumbs.
Although the Intellivision was more powerful, it was never as popular as the Atari 2600, which had more popular games because developers were more interested in exploring the possibilities of the 2600's capabilities. Due to excessive competition in the console market that brought about the "video game crash" of 1983, game sales for the Intellivision tanked, and in 1984 Mattel Electronics was shut down by its parent company Mattel. The rights to the Intellivision name brand and its games were eventually bought by [[Companies/INTV|INTV Corporation]], who made new consoles and introduced new games slowly over time. Production on Intellivision consoles ceased permanently in 1991.

==Intellivoice==
The Intellivoice was a peripheral developed by Mattel Electronics in conjunction with General Instruments. It used G.I.'s SP0256 Narrator speech synthesis chip. Released in 1982, the peripheral sold very poorly and as such only 5 games were ever supported. The original retail price of the unit was $100.

==Technical Specs==
General Instrument CP1610 16-bit microprocessor CPU running at 894.886 kHz (i.e., slightly less than 1 MHz)
1456 bytes of RAM:
* 240 × 8-bit Scratchpad Memory
* 352 × 16-bit (704 bytes) System Memory
* 512 × 8-bit Graphics RAM
7168 bytes of ROM:
* 4096 × 10-bit (5120 bytes) Executive ROM
* 2048 × 8-bit Graphics ROM
160 pixels wide by 196 pixels high (5×2 TV pixels make one Intellivision pixel)
16 color palette, all of which can be on the screen at once
8 sprites. Hardware supports the following features per-sprite:
* Size selection: 8×8 or 8×16
* Stretching: Horizontal (1×, 2×) and vertical (1×, 2×, 4× or 8×)
* Mirroring: Horizontal and vertical
* Collision detection: Sprite to sprite, sprite to background, and sprite to screen border
* Priority: Selects whether sprite appears in front of or behind background.
3 channel sound, with 1 noise generator (audio chip: General Instrument AY-3-8910)</text>
      <sha1>1mwpgrdm9hg7msz4gz7lhgyhlxfxhu6</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>Platforms/Intellivision Amico</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>456739</id>
    <revision>
      <id>738828</id>
      <parentid>722600</parentid>
      <timestamp>2026-02-28T00:38:32Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Marino</username>
        <id>8</id>
      </contributor>
      <origin>738828</origin>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text bytes="10471" sha1="eeri06pcalq2wc06dj9rx0uozqdd92s" xml:space="preserve">{{Platform
|Name=Intellivision Amico
|Guid=3045-181
|Image=https://www.giantbomb.com/a/uploads/scale_super/0/26/3161447-dims.jpeg
|Deck=A console that's intended to be a reimagining of the Intellivision brand.
|ShortName=AMCO
|ReleaseDateType=Year
|InstallBase=0
|OnlineSupport=No
|OriginalPrice=249.99
|Manufacturer=Companies/Intellivision_Productions_Inc
}}

==Overview==
https://www.giantbomb.com/a/uploads/original/31/318695/3341222-pr-800-render_console_whitegloss_wscreenshots_2021_05_22_01.png The Intellivision Amico is a home console in development by Intellivision Entertainment - a new company who acquired the Intellivision brand in 2018.
The console is named after the Italian word for 'friend'. The console is intended to be simple and family friendly - games are designed to be small, cheap, suitable for children and have no online multiplayer, in-app purchases or DLC.
The console has had a troubled history - numerous delays, a lack of clear information on the console, its games and its production process, and inflammatory and contradictory public statements made by Intellivision Entertainment's former CEO (now CCO) [[People/Tommy_Tallarico|Tommy Tallarico]].
In a financial filing made in early 2022, Intellivision stated to potential investors that the console's manufacturing depends on more crowdfunding and may never be released.

==Console==
https://www.giantbomb.com/a/uploads/original/31/318695/3354118-render_amicowhite_3quarterright_2021_05_31.png The console design is a shallow rounded box shape with an indented area that can house 2 controllers for charging (via contact pins on the console and controllers), as well as for placing game NFC cards onto.
Intellivision has not revealed the hardware specs are, but they [https://arstechnica.com/gaming/2021/06/what-the-hecks-an-intellivision-amico-consoles-leaky-dev-portal-offers-hints wrote in their developer portal info] that it will be similar to a low-end smartphone released in 2016 and that its OS will be based on Android.
The unique controllers are meant to be a newer twist on the [[Platforms/Intellivision|original Intellivision]] controllers, featuring a directional disc, touchscreen, shoulder buttons and motion sensors. Games will also be able to be controlled by a mobile phone via an Intellivision app.
Intellivision claims that every game for the system will be an NFT, but have not elaborated on the technical details.

==Announcement and SKUs==
The system was [https://www.dualshockers.com/intellevision-amico-revealed-prge first announced] on 22nd October 2018 at the Portland Retro Gaming Expo, with a scheduled release date of 10th October 2020 and an estimated retail price of $149-179.

===Initial pre-orders===
Pre-orders began in January 2020 with a refundable $100 deposit. At the time pre-orders were released and currently, the price is $249.99 - $299.99 depending on the console, significantly higher than the original estimated price.
From January 2020 - March 2022, the console was offered in 4 different colours, each available at different stores at different price points:
* Graphite Black or Glacier White - $249.99 / £249.99 / €279.99
* Vintage Woodgrain - $289.99 (exclusive to Intellivision.com)
* Galaxy Purple - $299.99 (exclusive to GameStop)
Each of these consoles will come with 2 controllers and 6 pack-in games.

===GameStop Stops pre-orders, Second price increase===
In April 2022, GameStop US refunded pre-order deposits and stopped selling the console. Intellivision announced that the price of new pre-orders would be increased again and start with only one controller, but no deposit would be required.
In addition, they would now offer Galaxy Purple pre-orders as GameStop were no longer selling them, but Black and White pre-orders would no longer be taken for the meantime:
* Galaxy Purple or Vintage Woodgrain console with 1 controller - $289.99
* Galaxy Purple or Vintage Woodgrain console with 2 controllers - $339.99
These consoles will still come with 6 pack-in games.

=='''Delays'''==
The console's release has been pushed back many times since it's original intended launch date of 10th October 2022. It currently has an undefined release date of sometime in 2022.
Intellivision claims these delays are largely due to COVID-19 related supply chain problems.
Critics have disputed that as the sole reason, citing largely unchanged trailers from [https://i.imgur.com/OoxkXX3.jpg 2019-2021] and [https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=xllsIe6ugt8 2020-2022], a lack of full prototype footage, [https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=LV1EKzFUyT8&amp;amp;list=PL4T1sDYpnBr4R7or5khb4MTJGZaZdT4FU&amp;amp;index=11 Intellivision seeking crucial hardware job positions months before their original planned release], a lack of finished software and services, and that similar console projects (such as[[Platforms/Atari_VCS|Atari VCS]] and [[Platforms/Playdate|Playdate]]) which were announced at a similar time have already entered production.
These criticisms would eventually corroborated by the company itself - in [https://arstechnica.com/gaming/2022/02/debt-stricken-intellivision-asks-for-more-funds-to-last-past-july an SEC filing] in early 2022, Intellivision admits there has not yet been a fully-functioning console and that it may never be finished.

=='Unboxing'==
On 22 March 2022, after weeks of silence from the company, [https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=gpYH5c6-nDU Intellivision released an 'unboxing' video of a single hand-produced console in packaging]. It is not visually confirmed that this is a working prototype and the packaging contained numerous spelling and translation errors. The console is still not in production.
https://www.giantbomb.com/a/uploads/original/31/318695/3358351-screenshot2022-03-25001939.png 
=='''Physical product launch'''==
https://www.giantbomb.com/a/uploads/original/31/318695/3341217-volumesbundle_8games_na_squareformat.png [https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=1c6y_-SQsqk Intellivision released physical products] of the console's launch games on 10th October 2021 - before the manufacture of the console. These were limited edition and contain an RFID card containing an activation code to download the game on an Amico system (when the system comes online for them to be redeemed), a commemorative coin, and a lenticular card. These were only sold in multipacks - $80 for 4 or $150 for the entire collection of 8.
The games available as physical products were (in alphabetical order):
* Biplanes
* Brain Duel
* Dynablaster
* Evel Knievel
* Finnigan Fox
* Missile Command
* Moon Patrol
* Rigid Force Redux Enhanced
[http://web.archive.org/web/20211011111538/https://intellivision.com/ecommerce-policy Intellivision's e-commerce policy] states that these are just physical items and not software licenses until the game becomes available to download.

==Funding==
The system's development has been funded in numerous ways.
* Crowdfunding investment sites such as [https://www.fig.co/campaigns/amico Republic] and [https://www.fundable.com/intellivision Fundable].
* [https://www.sec.gov/Archives/edgar/data/1909726/000166516022000236/offeringmemoformc.pdf Financial disclosures made in early 2022] revealed that a significant portion of the console's development was funded by high-interest loans given by various people working at the company and one angel investor.
* [https://arstechnica.com/gaming/2022/02/debt-stricken-intellivision-asks-for-more-funds-to-last-past-july Intellivision also received a grant for €450,000] from the Bavarian regional government in Germany, the 'majority' of which was spent on the development of Amico games.
* Smaller amounts from system pre-order deposits and physical product sales.

==Controversies==

==='''Ars Technica investigation'''===
In June 2021, [https://arstechnica.com/gaming/2021/06/what-the-hecks-an-intellivision-amico-consoles-leaky-dev-portal-offers-hints an investigation into an unsecured dev portal of the console] showed that the console has a similar computing power to a low-power smartphone from 2016. This means the console seems to have an unusually high profit margin.
These investigations also revealed that in a pitch to angel investors in March 2021, Intellivision Entertainment's then-CEO said they intended to take a cut of 'around 50 percent' cut of all third party games.

==='''J. Allard's involvement in the company'''===
[[People/J_Allard|J Allard]], co-founder of Xbox, joined the company in May 2020 as Global Managing Director. [https://www.geekwire.com/2021/xbox-co-founder-j-allard-left-intellivision-short-stint-hints-project-gaming-vet-brother He left in the summer of 2020, stating that he was 'not a good fit']. When this was revealed in January 2021, former CEO Tommy Tallarico made a comment stating that he was never a full-time employee, only a contractor.
In an investor pitch video recorded in March 2021, [https://arstechnica.com/gaming/2021/06/what-the-hecks-an-intellivision-amico-consoles-leaky-dev-portal-offers-hints Tommy Tallarico said that he was still on their team], leading to the [https://www.sec.gov/Archives/edgar/data/0001658966/000121390021015823/filename1.htm SEC sending a letter asking for clarification.].

==='''Potential game asset plagiarism and other game issues'''===
When the company started releasing sneak peeks of games in 2021, one of their games (Battle Tanks) [https://techraptor.net/gaming/news/intellivision-amico-game-lands-tommy-tallarico-in-hot-water had many visual assets that appear to have been plagiarised] from non-commercial image sites and [[Games/World_of_Tanks|World of Tanks]]. When this was discovered, the video for the game was edited and relisted twice.
[https://twitter.com/samred/status/1444849819265089541 A public demo for Moon Patrol in October 2021] showed copy-pasted text from a [[Franchises/Star_Fox|Star Fox]] game.

==='''Company response to criticism'''===
Intellivision Entertainment's former CEO (now CCO), [[People/Tommy_Tallarico|Tommy Tallarico]] has been known to make inflammatory statements, [https://twitter.com/ConVito/status/1410340382270017545/photo/1 such as calling critics of the Amico 'gaming racists' and 'mentally unstable'] and [http://web.archive.org/web/20210629185822/twitter.com/TommyTallarico/status/1409949240726487040 threatening to take legal action against a journalist] who was investigating the console with legally-obtained information. Tallarico has since then stepped down from his role as CEO of Intellivision.</text>
      <sha1>eeri06pcalq2wc06dj9rx0uozqdd92s</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>Platforms/Interton VC 4000</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>456749</id>
    <revision>
      <id>738811</id>
      <parentid>722613</parentid>
      <timestamp>2026-02-27T22:58:21Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Marino</username>
        <id>8</id>
      </contributor>
      <origin>738811</origin>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text bytes="622" sha1="85gum0ywg0mzlgz974mdx02r023dn3d" xml:space="preserve">{{Platform
|Name=Interton VC 4000
|Guid=3045-191
|Image=https://www.giantbomb.com/a/uploads/scale_super/0/1992/3195628-screen shot 2020-05-25 at 12.41.55 pm.png
|Deck=The Interton Video Computer 4000 is an 8-bit console released in Europe (primarily Germany) in 1978. Around forty "cassettes" were released for the system.
|ShortName=VC4K
|ReleaseDate=1978
|ReleaseDateType=Year
|OnlineSupport=No
|OriginalPrice=150.00
|Manufacturer=Companies/Interton_Electronic
}}

The Interton Video Computer 4000 is an 8-bit console released in Europe (primarily Germany) in 1978. Around forty "cassettes" were released for the system.</text>
      <sha1>85gum0ywg0mzlgz974mdx02r023dn3d</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>Platforms/Jaguar</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>456601</id>
    <revision>
      <id>797190</id>
      <parentid>752580</parentid>
      <timestamp>2026-03-21T00:41:11Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Frobie</username>
        <id>300</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>Undo revision [[Special:Diff/752580|752580]] by [[Special:Contributions/Giantbomb|Giantbomb]] ([[User talk:Giantbomb|talk]])</comment>
      <origin>797190</origin>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text bytes="8803" sha1="3m3c9nkrp6jxucux8eb7szb0pcibftq" xml:space="preserve">{{Platform
|Name=Jaguar
|Guid=3045-28
|Aliases=Atari Jaguar
|Image=https://www.giantbomb.com/a/uploads/scale_super/0/4647/2954600-atari-jaguar-console-set.jpg
|Deck=The Atari Jaguar was the first 64-Bit game console, and Atari's final console.
|ShortName=JAG
|ReleaseDate=1993-11-23
|ReleaseDateType=Full
|InstallBase=150,000
|OnlineSupport=No
|OriginalPrice=249.99
|Manufacturer=Companies/Atari
}}


==Overview==
After an absence from the video game console market since the demise of the 7800 system in 1991, [[Companies/Atari|Atari]] made its return with the Jaguar. The system was released in 1993 in [[Locations/San_Francisco|San Francisco]] and in 1994 for the rest of [[Locations/The_United_States_of_America|America]] and [[Locations/Europe|Europe]]. Unfortunately, the Jaguar was a commercial failure that left the company financially crippled. It was the last console Atari produced.
In the early 1990s, Atari was negotiating with a British company called Flare Technology, who had designed the unreleased Konix Multisystem console. Atari was impressed by the work Flare had done on the Konix, and provided to the funding to found a new company, Flare 2. Flare 2 started development on two consoles, the 32-bit Panther and the 64-bit Jaguar. Eventually, after seeing the Jaguar's graphical abilities, Atari ceased work on Panther and focused their attention on the more powerful Jaguar. They aimed to surpass the abilities of the Sega Genesis and the Super Nintendo, and compete against the new generation of consoles in development by [[Companies/The_3DO_Company|3DO]], [[Companies/Nintendo|Nintendo]] and [[Companies/Sega|Sega]], while still remaining cost effective. Despite the Panther's cancellation, some games developed for it saw release. For example, the game [[Games/Cybermorph|Cybermorph]] that came bundled with the Atari Jaguar was a game designed for Panther.

==64-bit?==
Atari advertised the Jaguar aggressively in the press with its "Do the Math" campaign; boasting about its technical superiority over the 16-bit platforms, and claiming to be the first 64-bit home console on the market. While the Jaguar was certainly more powerful than the [[Platforms/Super_Nintendo_Entertainment_System|Super Nintendo]] and [[Platforms/Genesis|Genesis]] in most respects, these claims caused some controversy.
Many technically knowledgeable industry insiders and gamers claimed that the Jaguar was not a true 64-bit platform, because the Jaguar’s Motorola 68000 CPU chip was only 16/32-bit (like in 16-bit systems), and the primary GPU delivered a 32-bit instruction set. The complaint is similar to the earlier argument that the [[Platforms/TurboGrafx_16|TurboGrafx-16]] was actually an 8-bit system, since it was based around an 8-bit CPU (but with 16-bit video chips), and equally gray.
A major contributor to this issue was the industry's desire to use "bits" as a concrete measure of subjective "impressiveness." With Sega and Nintendo promoting 16-bit systems as vastly superior to previous 8-bit systems, gamers naturally expected a similar, obvious jump in quality with the Jaguar. In theory, 64-bit games should have been 4x as impressive as 16-bit systems (as frequently cited when the Jaguar is compared to the ). In reality, this is misunderstanding the meaning of "bits," and applying some wishful thinking toward rating a console's performance by a simple number.
Ultimately, due to Jaguar's chip set architecture and processing methods, there was just enough to backup Atari’s 64-bit claim. The design, if always followed as intended, would indeed utilise 64-bit graphical processing and buck claims of the Jaguar being simply "two 32-bit chips glued together." Unfortunately, the architecture proved difficult for third-party developers to utilize effectively, and made porting games less profitable - a situation echoed by developers' issues with the [[Platforms/PlayStation_3|Playstation 3]]. Thus the games most often fell short of the system's theoretical potential.
Jaguar [http://www.jaguarsector.com/index.php?showforum=2 programming enthusiasts] looking over dumped code from retail titles have suggested many companies treated the Motorola CPU as the main processing unit, instead of as a controller for the 64-bit Tom and Jerry "workhorse" chips as Atari intended. This would artificially limit the machine's capabilities, and has been cited as the primary reason for choppy performance in some games ([[Games/Checkered_Flag|Checkered Flag]] is a specific example). It is unclear as to how frequently this occurred, and if it was due to poor documentation from Atari, or simply that developers were more familiar with the common 68000 chip.

==Legacy==
The Jaguar platform did boast some well-received games, including [[Games/Alien_Vs_Predator_1994|Alien VS Predator]], [[Games/Doom|Doom]] and [[Games/Tempest_2000|Tempest 2000]], but the graphical leap from 16-bit systems was not extreme, contrary to the expectations Sega had created. Indeed, a large number of Jaguar releases were ports of games released on the Genesis and the Super Nintendo.
The Jaguar was a powerful system for its time, with many of the units being sold to the loyal and dedicated Atari fan base that had built up since the early 1980‘s. Many clever and innovative ideas for the system were in the pipeline, most of which never made it past the prototype phase because of poor sales and short life span of the console.
The Jaguar’s success was hindered by a number of contributing factors, such as a limited game library, third party software development issues, and fierce competition in the form of [[Companies/Sony_Corporation|Sony]]’s [[Platforms/PlayStation|PlayStation]] and [[Companies/Sega|Sega]]’s [[Platforms/Saturn|Saturn]], which finally finished off the Jaguar by mid-1996.
In the late 1990’s [[Companies/Hasbro_Interactive_Inc|Hasbro interactive]] bought out all Atari properties and declared the Jaguar an open platform for homebrew development. Today the Atari Jaguar has a loyal cult following, who use the console for all sorts of development, including utilizing the COM [[Platforms/Atari_Lynx|Lynx]] and "CatBox" device for the networking of up to 32 Jaguar consoles.

==Specifications==

===First Chip - Tom Chip (26.59 MHz)===
* * Graphics processing unit (GPU) – 32-bit RISC architecture, 4 KB internal cache.
* Object Processor – 64-bit RISC architecture.
* Blitter – 64-bit RISC architecture; high speed logic operations, z-buffering and Gouraud shading, with 64-bit internal registers.
* DRAM controller, 32-bit memory management.

===Second Chip - Jerry Chip (26.59 MHz)===
* Digital Signal Processor – 32-bit RISC architecture, 8 KB internal cache. Same RISC core as the GPU, but not limited to graphic production.
* CD-quality sound (16-bit stereo). Number of sound channels limited by software. 2 DACs (stereo) convert digital data to analog sound signals. Full stereo capabilities.
* Wavetable synthesis, FM synthesis, FM Sample synthesis, and AM synthesis.
* A clock control block, incorporating timers, and a UART.
* Joystick control.

===Features===
* Motorola 68000 (used as a manager).
* General purpose 16/32-bit control processor, (13.295 MHz).
* 2 MB RAM on a 64-bit bus using 4x 16-bit fast page mode DRAMS.
* Storage - Cartridge – up to 6 MB.
* Support for COM Lynx I/O.
An interesting note is that Jaguar cartridges are generally not [[Concepts/Region_Locked|region locked]], or even linked to PAL or NTSC video rates. While other consoles do this at the software level, Jaguar consoles are PAL or NTSC specific, and the cartridges themselves are commonly agnostic. This is why most Jaguar packaging is in English, French, and German. Production costs were saved by printing one cart type and selling it worldwide.
http://www.giantbomb.com/a/uploads/original/11/117445/2090429-jag_3_.png The Jaguar's cartridge port contains no hinged dust cover or similar protection. The port is simply left exposed on the top of the console. Because of this design flaw, contacts on both the console and the cartridges are extremely sensitive to dust, oil, corrosion, or other elements that prevent a solid contact. Poor contact between the cartridge and the console leads to the common "Red Screen of Death" on booting the console. Contrary to popular belief, this does not indicate a hardware failure. In nearly every case, the red screen can be cleared by aggressively cleaning the cartridge with mild solvents (alcohol or peroxide) - just blowing on the cart won't usually do.

==U.S. Launch Titles==
The following are launch titles for the Jaguar when it was released in November 1993.
* [[Games/Cybermorph|Cybermorph]]
* [[Games/Raiden|Raiden]]
* [[Games/Trevor_McFur_In_The_Crescent_Galaxy|Trevor McFur in the Crescent Galaxy]]</text>
      <sha1>3m3c9nkrp6jxucux8eb7szb0pcibftq</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>Platforms/Jaguar CD</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>456729</id>
    <revision>
      <id>738650</id>
      <parentid>722587</parentid>
      <timestamp>2026-02-24T23:58:15Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Marino</username>
        <id>8</id>
      </contributor>
      <origin>738650</origin>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text bytes="1434" sha1="lejmwyx90e5jz9trq9nsgpq2021fqpn" xml:space="preserve">{{Platform
|Name=Jaguar CD
|Guid=3045-171
|Aliases=Atari Jaguar CD,Jaguar II
|Image=https://www.giantbomb.com/a/uploads/scale_super/0/1992/2988687-atari_jaguar_cd_retropixl_retrogaming_retro_gaming_2.png
|Deck=Atari released a CD-ROM drive for the Jaguar on September 21, 1995 for $149.99.
|ShortName=JCD
|ReleaseDate=1995-09-21
|InstallBase=20,000
|OnlineSupport=No
|OriginalPrice=149.99
|Manufacturer=Companies/Atari
}}
&lt;div id='imageData' data-json='{"infobox":{"file":"2988687-atari_jaguar_cd_retropixl_retrogaming_retro_gaming_2.png","path":"0\/1992\/","mime":"image\/png","sizes":"scale_super,scale_medium,scale_small,square_mini,square_medium,square_tiny,square_small,scale_avatar,scale_tiny,square_avatar,scale_large,screen_kubrick,screen_medium","caption":""},"background":[]}' /&gt;

==Overview==
When [[Companies/Atari|Atari]] released the [[Platforms/Jaguar|Jaguar]] in November 1993, they also promised to expand upon the system with an attachable CD-ROM drive. After numerous delays, the Jaguar CD was released on September 21, 1995, less than two weeks after the [[Platforms/PlayStation|PlayStation]]. Included with the system were two games ([[Games/Blue_Lightning|Blue Lightning]] and [[Games/Vid_Grid|Vid Grid]]), a [[Games/Tempest_2000|Tempest 2000]] soundtrack CD, and a demo disc for [[Games/Myst|Myst]].
Only eleven games were officially released for the Jaguar CD and the system was discontinued just a year later.</text>
      <sha1>lejmwyx90e5jz9trq9nsgpq2021fqpn</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>Platforms/LeapPad</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>456744</id>
    <revision>
      <id>738623</id>
      <parentid>722607</parentid>
      <timestamp>2026-02-24T22:15:03Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Marino</username>
        <id>8</id>
      </contributor>
      <origin>738623</origin>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text bytes="1111" sha1="gyz0glpisomrwgldc09jfa1imvzr2hs" xml:space="preserve">{{Platform
|Name=LeapPad
|Guid=3045-186
|Aliases=LeapPad Plus Writing,Read and Write LeapPad,LeapPad Plus Microphone,Read Aloud LeapPad,LeapPad Pro,Quantum LeapPad,LeapPad Plus Writing and Microphone,Learn &amp; Go LeapPad,CocoPad,LeapPad2,LeapPad Ultra,LeapPad3,LeapPad Platinum,LeapPad Ultimate
|Image=https://www.giantbomb.com/a/uploads/scale_super/0/1992/3195586-91siqfml3ul._ac_sl1500_.jpg
|Deck=LeapPad is a series of tablets developed by LeapFrog beginning in 1999. They are primarily intended for children.
|ShortName=LPAD
|ReleaseDate=May 1999
|ReleaseDateType=Year
|OnlineSupport=No
|OriginalPrice=69.99
|Manufacturer=Companies/LeapFrog_Enterprises
}}
&lt;div id='imageData' data-json='{"infobox":{"file":"3195586-91siqfml3ul._ac_sl1500_.jpg","path":"0\/1992\/","mime":"image\/jpeg","sizes":"scale_super,square_avatar,square_mini,screen_kubrick,scale_small,scale_large,scale_avatar,screen_medium,square_small,square_medium,scale_medium,square_tiny,scale_tiny","caption":""},"background":[]}' /&gt;
LeapPad is a series of tablets developed by LeapFrog beginning in 1999. They are primarily intended for children.</text>
      <sha1>gyz0glpisomrwgldc09jfa1imvzr2hs</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>Platforms/Leapfrog Didj</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>456704</id>
    <revision>
      <id>738562</id>
      <parentid>738561</parentid>
      <timestamp>2026-02-24T18:05:31Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Marino</username>
        <id>8</id>
      </contributor>
      <origin>738562</origin>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text bytes="1158" sha1="5j1bcibbbiqj2ceh28iym4577h7ibqs" xml:space="preserve">{{Platform
|Name=LeapFrog Didj
|Guid=3045-144
|Aliases=Didji
|Image=https://www.giantbomb.com/a/uploads/scale_super/14/148570/2203035-didj_custom_gaming_system_product_shot_540x360.jpg
|Deck=The Leapfrog Didj is a handheld console that was originally released in 2008. It's built for educational software, but runs a Linux distribution that has created a bit of hacker interest.
|ShortName=DIDJ
|ReleaseDate=2008-08-31
|ReleaseDateType=Month
|OnlineSupport=No
|OriginalPrice=89.99
|Manufacturer=Companies/LeapFrog_Enterprises
}}
&lt;div id='imageData' data-json='{"infobox":{"file":"2203035-didj_custom_gaming_system_product_shot_540x360.jpg","path":"14\/148570\/","mime":"image\/jpeg","sizes":"scale_medium,scale_super,square_mini,square_medium,square_small,screen_medium,square_avatar,scale_small,scale_large,scale_avatar,square_tiny,screen_kubrick","caption":""},"background":[]}' /&gt;

=='''Overview'''==
The Didj is a basic handheld system with a D-pad and A and B buttons. It also has start select and bumpers. Users can also customize their avatar with unlockables from games. There have been 17 games released for the system. It has an ARM9 @ 393 MHz CPU.</text>
      <sha1>5j1bcibbbiqj2ceh28iym4577h7ibqs</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>Platforms/Leapster</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>456651</id>
    <revision>
      <id>738611</id>
      <parentid>722484</parentid>
      <timestamp>2026-02-24T21:27:30Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Marino</username>
        <id>8</id>
      </contributor>
      <origin>738611</origin>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text bytes="3849" sha1="4iscvhwbcyl9wme8wyxagk8o7h84a3t" xml:space="preserve">{{Platform
|Name=Leapster
|Guid=3045-89
|Image=https://www.giantbomb.com/a/uploads/scale_super/0/26/10607-leapster.jpg
|Deck=The LeapFrog Leapster is a stylus-based educational game device aimed at children under 10.
|ShortName=LEAP
|ReleaseDate=2003-11-29
|ReleaseDateType=Month
|InstallBase=4,000,000
|OnlineSupport=No
|OriginalPrice=79.99
|Manufacturer=Companies/LeapFrog_Enterprises
}}
&lt;div id='imageData' data-json='{"infobox":{"file":"10607-leapster.jpg","path":"0\/26\/","mime":"image\/jpeg","sizes":"scale_medium,scale_super,square_mini,square_medium,square_small,screen_medium,square_avatar,scale_small,scale_large,scale_avatar,square_tiny,screen_kubrick","caption":"Leapster"},"background":[]}' /&gt;

==Overview==
The LeapFrog Leapster Learning Game System is a handheld video game system released in 2003.  The Leapster is an educational system targeted at children 4-10 years old with games to teach phonics, spelling, math, art, music and animal facts.  It features a 160x160px color touch screen controlled by a stylus as well as a D-Pad and various buttons.  The device is by far the most popular educational console in history, with a library of over 40 games and an install base of over 4 million.  In 2008 the Leapster was succeeded by the Leapster 2.


==Hardware==
The Leapster was designed to be visually appealing, easy to use, and durable.  The device features multiple methods of control including a 2.25" touch screen, directional pad, and two buttons on the right side of the unit.  The screen is backlit and large enough to support most games adequately, although some drawing/art games may be cluttered.  The Leapster has no hardware graphics acceleration, so graphics are simple and two dimensional, but are appropriate for the intended age range. The device has a large, mono speaker in the bottom right corner of the device.  It runs off 4 AA batteries, and an optional rechargable battery pack was available called the L-Max Recharging System.  Only one model revision was made to the Leapster in it's 5 years as a portable console called the Leapster L-Max, released in 2004.  The L-Max had slightly smaller dimensions and could output video to a TV via a composite cable.  In 2005 a fully consolized Leapster unit was released called the Leapster TV.


===Technical Specifications===

''CPU ''- ARCTangent 5.1 running at 96MHz.
''Memory ''- 2MB onboard RAM, 256 bytes non-volatile.
''Media ''- Cartridges of 4-16MB with between 2 and 512kb non-volatile storage.
''Graphics ''- No hardware acceleration.
''Audio ''- Proprietary hardware audio acceleration.
''Screen ''- 160x160px color.


==Software==
Leapster cartridges are compatible with all three Leapster models and include a large range of children edutainment software.  Many licensed characters are present in Leapster games such as [[Characters/SpongeBob_SquarePants|SpongeBob Squarepants]], [[Games/Thomas_the_Tank_Engine_And_Friends|Thomas the Tank Engine]], [[Characters/Dora_the_Explorer|Dora the Explorer]], [[Characters/Nemo_7442|Nemo]], [[Characters/Cinderella|Cinderella]], [[Characters/Ariel_12406|Ariel]], and [[Characters/Batman|Batman]].  LeapFrog also created their own character Tad who narrates a few games.  Two games are pre-loaded onto the device: Rabbit River, a sort of educational Frogger clone and Color Corral, a problem solving and coloring activity suite.  Over 40 additional titles are available.  All games on the LeapFrog are educational, developed and produced by LeapFrog, have multiple skill levels, and carried MSRPs of $24.99.  All games also feature a hint system so children don't get stuck for too long, which will bring up visual or audio clues.  If a child answers a question incorrectly too many times, Edison the firefly pops up and coaches the child to teach them the concept they do not understand.</text>
      <sha1>4iscvhwbcyl9wme8wyxagk8o7h84a3t</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>Platforms/Leapster Explorer</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>456743</id>
    <revision>
      <id>1008542</id>
      <parentid>738596</parentid>
      <timestamp>2026-07-19T18:54:08Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Giantbomb</username>
        <id>1</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>Point cover at a rendition that actually serves</comment>
      <origin>1008542</origin>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text bytes="883" sha1="lcjna5ro7zde6vhqnjyxw6d9qbd72mm" xml:space="preserve">{{Platform
|Name=Leapster Explorer
|Guid=3045-185
|Image=https://www.giantbomb.com/a/uploads/scale_super/0/1992/3195577-91b99%2B96oel._ac_sx425_.jpg
|Deck=Leapster Explorer is a cartridge-based handheld console developed by LeapFrog and intended for children under the age of ten.
|ShortName=LEXP
|ReleaseDate=2010-06-19
|ReleaseDateType=Year
|OnlineSupport=No
|OriginalPrice=69.99
|Manufacturer=Companies/LeapFrog_Enterprises
}}
&lt;div id='imageData' data-json='{"infobox":{"file":"3195577-91b99+96oel._ac_sx425_.jpg","path":"0\/1992\/","mime":"image\/jpeg","sizes":"scale_super,screen_kubrick,square_mini,square_medium,scale_small,scale_avatar,scale_large,square_small,scale_medium,square_avatar,screen_medium,square_tiny","caption":""},"background":[]}' /&gt;
Leapster Explorer is a cartridge-based handheld console developed by LeapFrog and intended for children under the age of ten.</text>
      <sha1>lcjna5ro7zde6vhqnjyxw6d9qbd72mm</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>Platforms/Linux</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>456712</id>
    <revision>
      <id>797168</id>
      <parentid>752643</parentid>
      <timestamp>2026-03-21T00:03:26Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Frobie</username>
        <id>300</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>Undo revision [[Special:Diff/752643|752643]] by [[Special:Contributions/Giantbomb|Giantbomb]] ([[User talk:Giantbomb|talk]])</comment>
      <origin>797168</origin>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text bytes="4787" sha1="53el6abacxx6oldxp92a2x1xx7sg2dj" xml:space="preserve">{{Platform
|Name=Linux
|Guid=3045-152
|Aliases=Ubuntu,GNU/Linux
|Image=https://www.giantbomb.com/a/uploads/scale_super/1/14761/2435328-tux.png
|Deck=The Linux operating system was initially released in 1991 and has gone on to become a very popular free alternative to other, commercial systems.
|ShortName=LIN
|ReleaseDate=1991-09-17
|ReleaseDateType=Full
|OnlineSupport=Yes
|OriginalPrice=0.00
|Manufacturer=Linus Torvalds
}}
==Overview==
Linux is a Unix-like operating system created as a free software alternative to other Unix-like operating systems. The core component of any Linux-based operating system is the kernel, which was originally authored by Linus Torvalds and first released in 1991. Linux is typically distributed with user space applications developed from the GNU Project. Because of this, the Free Software Foundation, which created the GNU Project, prefers to refer to the operating system resulting from the combined kernel and applications as GNU/Linux.
Linux is generally released in a distribution, such as Ubuntu, Gentoo, Debian, or Fedora (though a skilled user could theoretically build it from scratch). These distributions can be commercial, like Red Hat, or free like Ubuntu.

==Creation==
Developer Linus Torvalds created Linux in 1991 due to dissatisfaction with the license restrictions of the MINIX operating system, which only allowed distribution for educational purposes. He initially developed the Linux kernel on MINIX and MINIX applications were used along with it. Development eventually moved to Linux with a GNU user space when the kernel had matured.
Torvalds initially released Linux under a license that restricted commercial distribution, but in 1992, the license was switched to the GNU General Public License (GPL). The GPL is a [[Concepts/Open_Source|free software]] license and does not contain the same restrictions as Torvalds' initial license choice. After switching the license to GPL, developers worked on porting the GNU Project applications to Linux, creating what is now commonly referred to as Linux or GNU/Linux.

==Linux Gaming==
Linux has long been a popular choice for free and open source games like [[Games/NetHack|NetHack]]. Commercial games started appearing in 1994, when [[Companies/id_Software|ID Software]]'s [[People/Dave_Taylor|Dave Taylor]] ported [[Games/Doom|Doom]] to the platform. With the creation of [[Companies/Loki_Entertainment_Software_Inc|Loki Software]] in 1998 porting became more common. Former Loki Software programmer [[People/Ryan_C_Gordon|Ryan C. Gordon]] continues to be involved in porting Linux games to this day.
Windows compatibility layers such as [[Objects/Wine|Wine]] can be used to play games native to Windows on Linux, though it's not typically the best way to play those games. Wine can, however, run the Windows version of the Steam platform on Linux, which has a much greater library than the Linux version. The [http:/appdb.winehq.org Wine website] has a detailed database of games with information on how to run them in Wine. With the advent of Steam Play + Proton, however, playing games through the native Linux steam client is now the best way to run Steam games on Linux, as thousands of Windows games are now reported to work on Linux through Steam. Protondb.com maintains a database of games that work via this method.
Indie developers generally support native Linux versions much more than larger publishers, with games like [[Games/Minecraft|Minecraft]] being very successful on the platform.
The [[Concepts/Humble_Bundle|Humble Bundle]] debuted in 2010, offering a selection of games to raise money for charity. Games are available for Windows, Mac and Linux, sometimes with games making their Linux debut as part of the bundle. Typical sales for the Linux version of the bundle rank it third, but the Linux users generally pay the highest average amount of money for the bundle(Contributors pay what they want).
In 2013 the [[Concepts/Steam|Steam]] digital distribution platform was officially released for Linux along with a variety of games. Although Valve only officially supports this version of Steam on Ubuntu, it can be installed on other distributions. Valve has also confirmed that their version of the "Steam-box" will run a version of Linux, though users will be able to install other OS's.
On July 24, 2014, [[Concepts/GOG_com|GOG.com]] officially started supporting Linux (four months after announcing their plans to add Linux support), inititally with a batch of 50 games, with another hundred to be made available in the following months. The games are made sure to work in the Ubuntu and Mint distributions and includes ''.deb'' installers for ease of use on those (and other Debian derivatives), but also include distro-independent ''tar.gz'' files.</text>
      <sha1>53el6abacxx6oldxp92a2x1xx7sg2dj</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>Platforms/Luxor ABC80</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>456728</id>
    <revision>
      <id>738809</id>
      <parentid>722586</parentid>
      <timestamp>2026-02-27T22:21:46Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Marino</username>
        <id>8</id>
      </contributor>
      <origin>738809</origin>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text bytes="2078" sha1="hp5usk796lmxht3onwxe6p7dznlcfoy" xml:space="preserve">{{Platform
|Name=Luxor ABC80
|Guid=3045-170
|Aliases=ABC800,Metric 65,BRG ABC 80
|Image=https://www.giantbomb.com/a/uploads/scale_super/0/26/2975830-1340529857-Luxor.jpg
|Deck=The Advanced BASIC Computer line was created in 1978 with the release of the ABC80, a joint venture between Luxor AB, DIAB and Scandia Metric.
|ShortName=ABC
|ReleaseDate=1978-08-31
|ReleaseDateType=Month
|InstallBase=35,000
|OnlineSupport=No
|OriginalPrice=1500.00
|Manufacturer=Companies/Luxor
}}


==History==
The companies Dataindustrier AB (DIAB) and Scandia Metric started looking into creating a Swedish home computer after seeing the success of the Tandy TRS-80 in 1977. The project was initially named HD-80 (HD meaning Hemdator, the Swedish word for home computer).
The two companies felt they had the technical expertise to design the computer, but not the means of producing it in the quantities needed, so they pitched the idea to the TV manufacturer Luxor AB, which ended up not only helping with manufacturing the computer, but took a leading role in its development. Early models were tied to repurposed monochrome Luxor TV that both served as the monitor and provided power to the computer, while later models were sold with an external power supply and RF adapter allowing it to be connected to the household's existing TV.
The computer was released in August 1978, initially with Luxor selling the consumer version and Scandia Metric selling their version (re-branded Metric 65) to businesses.
Over the next year they started blaming each other for encroaching on each other's markets however, and went their separate ways - with Luxor released the business model ABC800, and Scandia Metric licensing the Compucorp 655 as their follow-up "Metric 85".
The primary market of the computer was Sweden, though the Hungarian company Budapesti Rádiótechnikai Gyár produced some under license as the BRG ABC 80.
As IBM PC gained popularity in the early 80s, Luxor unsuccessfully tried to market their ABC 800 line with the slogan "Who needs IBM compatibility?". Production ceased in 1986.</text>
      <sha1>hp5usk796lmxht3onwxe6p7dznlcfoy</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>Platforms/M2</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>456761</id>
    <revision>
      <id>738829</id>
      <parentid>722627</parentid>
      <timestamp>2026-02-28T00:41:15Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Marino</username>
        <id>8</id>
      </contributor>
      <origin>738829</origin>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text bytes="2603" sha1="8d1sfwvgltjlt5dh2059y6tnoe97h1f" xml:space="preserve">{{Platform
|Name=M2
|Guid=3045-203
|Aliases=Panasonic M2,Matsushita M2
|Image=https://www.giantbomb.com/a/uploads/scale_super/0/1992/3306128-91e5b27a651edbf791d7830c2eb725d2.jpg
|Deck=The M2 was a console developed by The 3DO Company. It was originally intended to be an add-on to the 3DO console, but later transitioned into a full-on successor before Panasonic (Matsushita) canceled the project in 1997. The hardware was later implemented in other appliances.
|ShortName=M2
|InstallBase=0
|OnlineSupport=No
|Manufacturer=Companies/The_3DO_Company
}}

==Overview==
https://www.giantbomb.com/a/uploads/original/0/1992/3306129-m2_prototype_7.jpg Originally announced in 1995 as an an add-on accessory for the [[Platforms/3DO|3DO]], the M2 console was developed by [[Companies/The_3DO_Company|The 3DO Company]] as a competitor to the [[Platforms/PlayStation|PlayStation]]. After multiple public appearances including [[Concepts/E3_1995|E3 1995]], The 3DO Company sold all rights to the M2 to Panasonic (known as Matsushita in Japan). Panasonic attempted to strike a deal with [[Companies/Sega|Sega]] to use the technology in their next console, but the deal reportedly fell apart at the last minute. The console did not making a showing at [[Concepts/E3_1996|E3 1996]], where a Panasonic spokesman said they were reevaluating the console's future in games. In mid-1997, the project was officially canceled.
Panasonic later used the hardware in multimedia players, ATMs, and vending machines.

==Games==
At the time of the M2's cancellation in 1997, Ultra Game Players magazine reported that up to eighty games had been in development for the console.
While obviously no games were released for the canceled console, several games were shown publicly in various stages of development running on the M2 hardware.
* [[Games/ClayFighter_63_1_3|ClayFighter III]] (later renamed to ClayFighter 63 1/3)
* [[Games/D2|D2]]
* [[Games/Descent|Descent]]
* [[Games/IMSA_World_Championship_Racing|IMSA Racing]]
* [[Games/Iron_And_Blood_Warriors_of_Ravenloft|Ironblood]] (later renamed to Iron &amp;amp; Blood: Warriors of Ravenloft)
Other games that were confirmed to be in development for the M2 included:
* [[Games/Battlesport|Battlesport]]
* Escape from L.A.
* NFLPA Superstars
* Power Crystal
* [[Games/Return_Fire_2|Return Fire 2]]

==Konami==
[[Companies/Konami|Konami]] also briefly used the M2 hardware in arcade machines.
* [[Games/Battle_Tryst|Battle Tryst]]
* [[Games/Evil_Night|Evil Night]]
* [[Games/Heat_of_Eleven_98|Heat of Eleven '98]]
* [[Games/Polystars|Tobe! Polystars]]
* [[Games/Total_Vice|Total Vice]]</text>
      <sha1>8d1sfwvgltjlt5dh2059y6tnoe97h1f</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>Platforms/MSX</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>456588</id>
    <revision>
      <id>797147</id>
      <parentid>752568</parentid>
      <timestamp>2026-03-20T23:38:26Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Frobie</username>
        <id>300</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>Undo revision [[Special:Diff/752568|752568]] by [[Special:Contributions/Giantbomb|Giantbomb]] ([[User talk:Giantbomb|talk]])</comment>
      <origin>797147</origin>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text bytes="4357" sha1="ax1fe6jzsi6klx2tv7m0mv9slwkwwue" xml:space="preserve">{{Platform
|Name=MSX
|Guid=3045-15
|Aliases=MSX 2, MSX II
|Image=https://www.giantbomb.com/a/uploads/scale_super/0/25/176106-msx_philips_vg8020.jpg
|Deck=MSX is a standardized home computer architecture. It was popular in Japan, South Korea, Brazil, Netherlands, France, Spain, Finland, Arabian Gulf countries and former Soviet Union during the 1980s. Like the PC of today, the MSX computers were manufactured by many different companies.
|ShortName=MSX
|ReleaseDate=1983-10-21
|InstallBase=5,000,000
|OnlineSupport=No
|OriginalPrice=400.00
|Manufacturer=Companies/ASCII_Corporation
}}

==History==
The MSX home computer architecture standard was conceived by [[Companies/ASCII_Corporation|ASCII Microsoft]] executive [[People/Kazuhiko_Nishio|Kazuhiko Nishi]]. Inspired by the success of VHS as a standard for video cassette recorders he had proposed the MSX standard as a single industry standard for home computers. This was many years before the [[Platforms/PC|PC]] later became a standardized home computer architecture.
The MSX standard was first formally announced in 1983 and was followed by three other standards: MSX2 (1986), MSX2 (1988) and MSX turbo R (1990).
Over a hundred different companies have manufactured MSX computers. The list of companies includes: [[Companies/Sony_Interactive_Entertainment_America|Sony]], [[Companies/Panasonic_Interactive_Media|Panasonic]], Sanyo, JVC, Spectravideo, [[Companies/Toshiba_Corporation|Toshiba]], Canon, [[Companies/Casio_Co_Ltd|Casio]], Dragon, Dyndata, [[Companies/Fujitsu|Fujitsu]], Hitachi, Sharp/Epcom, [[Companies/Pioneer_LDC|Pioneer]], Alalamia, Mitsubishi, NEC, [[Companies/Philips_Interactive_Media_Inc|Philips]], Radiola, Schneider, Talent, Telematica, Yamaha, Yashica, Aster International, General, Samsung, Hyosung, Limco, Oric, Radofin.
Although it was developed by Microsoft's Japanese partner, Microsoft itself showed little support for the project beyond making the system software, and the MSX-based machines were seldom seen in the [[Locations/The_United_States_of_America|United States]]. Most of the Japanese companies decided to avoid the intensely competitive U.S. market, only Spectravideo and Yamaha decided otherwise. The MSX computers became popular in [[Locations/Japan|Japan]], [[Locations/South_Korea|South Korea]], [[Locations/Brazil|Brazil]], [[Locations/The_Netherlands|Netherlands]], [[Locations/France|France]], [[Locations/Spain|Spain]], [[Locations/Finland|Finland]], Kuwait and former [[Locations/Soviet_Union|Soviet Union]]. A total of 5 million MSX-based units were sold world-wide.

=='''Standard definition'''==
'''MSX'''
* Processor: Zilog Z80A 3,579 MHz (8-bit)
* ROM: 32 KB
* RAM: 8 KB minimum (Most machines provided 64K.)
* Video Display Processor: Texas Instruments TMS-9918/TMS-9928/TMS-9929
* Video RAM: 16 KB (Maximum resolution: 256×192 pixels with 16 colors)
* Sound chip: General Instrument AY-3-8910 (PSG)
* Connector for tape/data recorder.
* A Centronics interface (interface for connecting printers and other parallel devices)
* At least one joystick/mouse/paddle/trackball/graphic tablet connector. (Most computers have two.)
* At least one expansion port.
* A keyboard with At least 70 keys (including five function keys with ten programmable functions and four arrow keys).
'''MSX2''' (only changed to MSX listed)
* ROM: 48 KB
* RAM: 64 KB minimum
* Video Display Processor: Yamaha V9938
* Video RAM: At least 64kB (usually 128kB)
* Sound chip: Yamaha YM2149 (PSG)
* Clock chip: Ricoh RP5C01 (or compatible)
* A 3.5" Floppy disk drive was common
'''MSX2+''' (Only released in Japan)
* Processor: Zilog Z80 compatible running at 3.58 MHz or more (5.37 MHz versions were available)
* ROM: 64 KB
* RAM: At least 64 KB
* Video Display Processor: Yamaha V9958
* Sound chip: Yamaha YM2149 (PSG)
* Optional sound chip: Yamaha YM2413 (OPLL) (MSX-Music)
* Clock chip: RP5C01
* 3.5" Floppy disk drive was very common
'''MSX turbo R''' (Only two machines were made and they were only released in Japan)
* Processor: R800 (7.16 MHz) and Zilog Z80A compatible
* ROM: 96 KB
* RAM: 256 KB (FS-A1ST) or 512 KB (FS-A1GT)
* Video Display Processor: Yamaha V9958
* Sound chip: Yamaha YM2413 (OPLL) (MSX-Music)
* Sound chip: PCM synthesizer 8-bit (sample rate 16kHz)
* Sound chip: MIDI in/out (FS-A1GT only)
* 3.5" double sided double density (720kB) disk drive</text>
      <sha1>ax1fe6jzsi6klx2tv7m0mv9slwkwwue</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>Platforms/Mac</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>456590</id>
    <revision>
      <id>797146</id>
      <parentid>752570</parentid>
      <timestamp>2026-03-20T23:38:03Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Frobie</username>
        <id>300</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>Undo revision [[Special:Diff/752570|752570]] by [[Special:Contributions/Giantbomb|Giantbomb]] ([[User talk:Giantbomb|talk]])</comment>
      <origin>797146</origin>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text bytes="6800" sha1="c3g9zz3fiphyjr822hjyrx9jcklwlvl" xml:space="preserve">{{Platform
|Name=Mac
|Guid=3045-17
|Aliases=Macintosh,OSX,OS X
|Image=https://www.giantbomb.com/a/uploads/scale_super/0/5150/1500874-overview_gallery3_20090828.jpg
|Deck=The Macintosh (Mac) line of personal computers is designed and developed by Apple, Inc. - formerly Apple Computer, Inc. It runs macOS, a Unix operating system. Its current version, macOS 13.4 "Ventura" was released on May 18, 2023.
|ShortName=MAC
|ReleaseDate=1984-01-24
|ReleaseDateType=Month
|OnlineSupport=Yes
|OriginalPrice=2495.99
|Manufacturer=Companies/Apple_Inc
}}
==History==
The Macintosh was designed as part of a skunkworks operation originally headed by Jef Raskin. Raskin planned to create an easy to use and affordable appliance computer for use by ordinary people. The project was ongoing at the same time as [[Companies/Apple_Inc|Apple]] founder [[People/Steve_Jobs|Steve Jobs]] was leading development of Lisa, Apple's intended flagship computer. Despite his heavy involvement in the inital stages of the Lisa project, Jobs eventually caught wind of the Macintosh project and gradually turned his full attention to it. In 1981, Raskin departed the team over a dispute with Jobs, making Steve the de facto leader.
https://www.giantbomb.com/a/uploads/original/0/66/521728-macintosh.gif It was under Jobs that the Mac became a GUI-oriented computer, influenced by a tour given to Apple staff of Xerox's Palo Alto Research Center which included looks at PARC's Alto computer and the related Smalltalk software. The computer eventually released in 1984 as a vertically-oriented all-in-one and was gradually revised over the course of the decade. Eventually, Apple began to offer Macs in different formats, ranging from standard desktops to early laptops and other portable designs.
The Mac's popularity was at first fairly high, but after Steve Jobs was stripped of power within Apple (eventually departing to form NeXT), executives who did not fully understand the platform began to devalue it (notably, Apple was criticized in the nineties for offering an absurd amount of Macs which were too similar and had generic names) and the platform struggled. To compound these problems, Apple's Mac System (later Mac OS), the OS powering the Macs, was outdated and needed replacing.
Unfortunately, Apple's internal software R&amp;amp;D had become bloated and ineffectual, stalling development on the next-generation Mac OS codenamed Copland. In 1996, Apple wrote it off as a sinking ship and decided to source the basis for their next-generation operating system from elsewhere. Several options were considered, such as licensing Microsoft's NT architecture and purchasing Be, Inc. for its BeOS. In the end though, it was Apple founder Steve Jobs and his NeXT outfit which Apple decided to buy, allowing them to base what would become OS X (as in the roman numeral for 10) on NeXT's powerful and robust OpenSTEP OS. 
This also brought Jobs back into the company. He quickly assumed control and began to turn the Mac platform around. Jobs trimmed the bloat from the product line and steadily began to focus on releasing stylish computers like the iMac and iBook for consumers and powerhouses for the Mac's creative professional base like the PowerBook and PowerMac lines.
https://www.giantbomb.com/a/uploads/original/0/66/428003-imac2.jpg Despite the perception of the Mac as a second-rate games platform (by comparison to the dominant Windows PC), it has played host to a number of popular exclusives, most notably much of [[Companies/Bungie|Bungie's]] earlier games (before the Microsoft buyout) catalog. In fact, Bungie's [[Games/Halo_Combat_Evolved|Halo]], a huge hit for the Xbox, was originally a Mac exclusive, built on [[Concepts/OpenGL|OpenGL]]. The game later found its way onto Mac as a port of the PC release.
In 2016, Apple changed the name of the operating system on Mac computers to "macOS", which aligns with their other products (iOS, iPadOS, watchOS, tvOS, audioOS).

===='''Gaming on the Macintosh'''====

===macOS 10.13 "High Sierra" Improvements===
With the release of macOS 10.13 "High Sierra" came a number of improvements, through Apples graphical API called "Metal 2" by introducing virtual reality, machine learning and support for external GPU's (eGPU) to improve gaming and media experiences.

==='''Windows Gaming on the Mac'''===
On April 5, 2006 Apple released a beta version of software called Bootcamp. Due to the recent change in architecture - PowerPC to Intel - Mac and Windows computers were now more similar than ever. Bootcamp embraced this by allowing the user to install Windows on a Mac. Windows XP - and later Windows Vista and 7 - now ran natively on Macintosh computers, making gaming on Mac's easier than ever.
With the release of macOS 10.5 (Leopard), Bootcamp comes pre-installed on all macOS devices and is thus officially supported by Apple. Although many Mac users are unwilling to install Windows on their computer, Boot Camp still offers Mac users something they've never had before - the ability to run any PC game 100% natively.

==='''Steam for Mac'''===
On March 8th, 2010, [[Companies/Valve_Corporation|Valve]] announced that it would begin a new [[Concepts/Steam|Steam]] program for the Mac. Under this new system, Valve games would be able to run natively on the Mac, and 3rd parties would be able to release a Mac version of their game on Steam. Also announced is a program called Steam Play, where players who buy the Mac version of a game will also be able to download the PC version of the same game free of charge. Steam for Mac was released on May 12, 2010.
With the release of macOS Catalina (10.15) in 2019, Apple ceased support for 32-bit applications, which impacted compatibility of certain games on Steam. Users can run incompatible games in their library on Windows via Bootcamp on their macOS devices.

==='''Mac App Store'''===
Mimicking their strategy with the [[Platforms/iPhone|iOS]] platform, Apple has recently added an integrated App Store to macOS. Users can purchase Applications in the same way as on iOS. Apps are then downloaded to a user's system and the App Store App itself keeps track of updates for these Apps. In addition, once an App is purchased, users are free to install it on any other Mac computer by logging into the Mac App Store with the same Apple Account.
This service, just like on iOS, extends to games and already a number of Publishers have made classic and more recent titles available for purchase on the Mac App Store. These games range from recent and current hits to old favourites, to popular indie games like the [[Games/Penny_Arcade_Adventures_On_the_Rain_Slick_Precipice_of_Darkness_Episode_One|Penny Arcade Adventures]] episodes and also ports of existing iOS games like [[Franchises/Angry_Birds|Angry Birds]].</text>
      <sha1>c3g9zz3fiphyjr822hjyrx9jcklwlvl</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>Platforms/Magic Leap One</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>456731</id>
    <revision>
      <id>738580</id>
      <parentid>738520</parentid>
      <timestamp>2026-02-24T18:59:41Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Marino</username>
        <id>8</id>
      </contributor>
      <origin>738580</origin>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text bytes="798" sha1="3mg32xcfwd57xlm2v3nk8i351d02xuu" xml:space="preserve">{{Platform
|Name=Magic Leap One
|Guid=3045-173
|Image=https://www.giantbomb.com/a/uploads/scale_super/0/26/3059027-product-family-shot_3x.jpeg
|Deck=The Magic Leap One launched as a developer-focused "Creator Edition" in August 2018.
|ShortName=ML1
|ReleaseDate=2018-08-08
|OnlineSupport=Yes
|OriginalPrice=2299.99
|Manufacturer=Companies/Magic_Leap
}}
&lt;div id='imageData' data-json='{"infobox":{"file":"3059027-product-family-shot_3x.jpeg","path":"0\/26\/","mime":"image\/jpeg","sizes":"scale_super,square_tiny,square_medium,square_small,square_mini,scale_small,scale_medium,scale_tiny,scale_avatar,square_avatar,screen_medium,scale_large,screen_kubrick","caption":""},"background":[]}' /&gt;
The Magic Leap One is an Augmented Reality device consisting of a headset with an attached processing pack.</text>
      <sha1>3mg32xcfwd57xlm2v3nk8i351d02xuu</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>Platforms/Mega Duck</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>456697</id>
    <revision>
      <id>738668</id>
      <parentid>738667</parentid>
      <timestamp>2026-02-25T02:07:07Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Marino</username>
        <id>8</id>
      </contributor>
      <origin>738668</origin>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text bytes="2187" sha1="rr895xpxw3o061bui26w3mnzd4syl6v" xml:space="preserve">{{Platform
|Name=Mega Duck
|Guid=3045-137
|Aliases=Mega Duck WG-108,Cougar Boy
|Image=https://www.giantbomb.com/a/uploads/scale_super/12/126726/1755677-8347458953222508.jpg
|Deck=The Mega Duck is a 1993 handheld that was released in some territories under the name Cougar Boy. It was released as the Mega Duck in France, Germany, Brazil, and China. The handheld was also released as the Cougar Boy in the USA and some other countries.
|ShortName=DUCK
|ReleaseDate=1993-08-31
|ReleaseDateType=Month
|OnlineSupport=No
|OriginalPrice=72.00
}}
==Overview==
Produced by the Hong Kong-based Welback Holdings, the oddly-named Mega Duck was marketed under a number of companies throughout the world, like Creatronic, Videojet and Cougar USA (hence the redubbing in the US as the Cougar Boy). Welback positioned it as a "rival" to the [[Platforms/Game_Boy|Game Boy]].
The electronics inside the system are oddly similar to those of the [[Platforms/Watara_Supervision|Watara Supervision]] - the positioning of certain components is virtually identical! - with the exception of less cartridge pins and a bigger screen.
Most of the games were produced by Taiwanese company Thin Chen Enterprise, better known as the infamous unlicensed developers [[Companies/Sachen|Sachen]], and they would mostly go on to be ported to the Game Boy as part of multicarts.

==Hardware Specifications==
* '''CPU''': MOS version of the Z80 (embedded in the main VLSI )
* '''Clock Speed''': 4.194304 MHz (= 2 Hz)
* '''RAM''': 16 KB in two 8K chips (Goldstar GM76C88LFW)
* '''System Logic''': 80 pins VLSI chip (Just the die on the PCB covered with a blob of epoxy)
* '''LCD''': 2,7" (48 (h) x 51 (w) mm) STN dot matrix resolution 160×144 at 59.732155 Hz
* '''Gray Scales''': 4 levels of dark blue on a green background
* '''Player Controls''': 4 directional keys, A, B, Select and Start keys
* '''Other Controls''': On/off switch and contrast and volume regulators
* '''Sound''': Built in speaker (8Ω 200 mW) and stereo headset output
* '''Dimensions''': 155 (l) x 97 (w) x32 (h) mm
* '''Weight''': 249 gram (w.o. batteries)
* '''Power''': Four AA batteries or AC adapter 6VDC/300mA
* '''Current Consumption''': 700 mW</text>
      <sha1>rr895xpxw3o061bui26w3mnzd4syl6v</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>Platforms/Memorex MD 2500 VIS</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>456713</id>
    <revision>
      <id>738674</id>
      <parentid>722565</parentid>
      <timestamp>2026-02-25T02:25:17Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Marino</username>
        <id>8</id>
      </contributor>
      <origin>738674</origin>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text bytes="1394" sha1="ttbq9kw2l9gbtb7garyezfhp0mplcs2" xml:space="preserve">{{Platform
|Name=Memorex MD 2500 VIS
|Guid=3045-153
|Aliases=Tandy VIS
|Image=https://www.giantbomb.com/a/uploads/scale_super/0/4647/2954664-5814140637-C2fBm.jpg
|Deck=The Memorex MD 2500, also known as the Tandy VIS, was released in 1992. It ran a version of Windows that can be described as a precursor to WinCE and primarily focused on educational games.
|ShortName=VIS
|ReleaseDate=1992
|ReleaseDateType=Year
|InstallBase=11,000
|OnlineSupport=No
|OriginalPrice=699.99
|Manufacturer=Companies/Tandy_Corporation
}}


==Overview==
The Memorex/[[Companies/Tandy_Corporation|Tandy]] VIS was a "Visual Information System" that also doubled as a gaming machine. The machine was only sold at Radio Shack, and the games released for the system were mostly educational.
The system is notable for it's operating system, Modular Windows. A special embedded version of Windows 3.1, it acts as a precursor to the modern Windows CE. While there were plans to use Modular Windows in other devices like televisions, it appears that the VIS was the only released platform to actually use it.

==System Specs==
* '''CPU:''' Intel 286, manufactured by AMD
* '''Video System:''' Cirrus Logic
* '''Sound System:''' Yamaha
* '''Chipset:''' NCR Corporation
* '''CD-ROM:''' x2 IDE by Mitsumi
* '''OS:''' Microsoft Modular Windows
* '''ROM:''' 1mb, containing minimal MS-DOS 3.x, a few drivers, and Modular Windows.</text>
      <sha1>ttbq9kw2l9gbtb7garyezfhp0mplcs2</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>Platforms/Memotech MTX</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>456764</id>
    <revision>
      <id>738756</id>
      <parentid>722631</parentid>
      <timestamp>2026-02-26T22:59:28Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Marino</username>
        <id>8</id>
      </contributor>
      <origin>738756</origin>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text bytes="524" sha1="jdkdkn4l1fo0qq07zgyvbj5edusaffs" xml:space="preserve">{{Platform
|Name=Memotech MTX
|Guid=3045-206
|Aliases=Memotech MTX500,Memotech MTX512,Memotech RS218
|Image=https://www.giantbomb.com/a/uploads/scale_super/0/1992/3341703-images.jpeg
|Deck=The Memotech MTX is a series of British-developed home computers released in 1983 and 1984.
|ShortName=MTX
|ReleaseDate=1983
|ReleaseDateType=Year
|InstallBase=25,000
|OnlineSupport=No
|OriginalPrice=300.00
|Manufacturer=Companies/Memotech
}}

The Memotech MTX is a series of British-developed home computers released in 1983 and 1984.</text>
      <sha1>jdkdkn4l1fo0qq07zgyvbj5edusaffs</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>Platforms/Meta Quest</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>456735</id>
    <revision>
      <id>1008543</id>
      <parentid>797243</parentid>
      <timestamp>2026-07-19T18:54:11Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Giantbomb</username>
        <id>1</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>Point cover at a rendition that actually serves</comment>
      <origin>1008543</origin>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text bytes="2390" sha1="7svveytcqiewxzw8kwq07korgpztcyv" xml:space="preserve">{{Platform
|Guid=3045-177
|Name=Meta Quest
|Aliases=Oculus Quest
|Image=https://www.giantbomb.com/a/uploads/scale_super/0/26/3099536-71nk%2Bjjlzzl._sx679_.jpg
|Deck=Oculus Quest is a self-contained virtual reality platform from the makers of the Oculus Rift.
|ShortName=MQST
|ReleaseDateType=Full
|ReleaseDate=2019-05-21
|InstallBase=2,000,000
|OnlineSupport=Yes
|OriginalPrice=399.00
|Manufacturer=Companies/Oculus_Studios
}}
&lt;div id='imageData' data-json='{"infobox":{"file":"3099536-71nk+jjlzzl._sx679_.jpg","path":"0\/26\/","mime":"image\/jpeg","sizes":"scale_super,square_small,square_tiny,scale_medium,square_medium,scale_small,scale_avatar,square_mini,scale_large,square_avatar,screen_medium,screen_kubrick","caption":""},"background":{"file":"3191025-oculus-quest-review-1280x720.jpg","path":"3\/31685\/","mime":"image\/jpeg","sizes":"screen_kubrick_wide,square_tiny,square_medium,square_small,scale_super,scale_medium,scale_tiny,square_mini,scale_small,scale_avatar,screen_medium,screen_kubrick,scale_large,square_avatar","caption":null}}' /&gt;

===Overview:===
The Oculus Quest is a standalone virtual reality headset with inside-out tracking and two hand controllers. It launched on May 21, 2019 at a price of $399 for a device with 64GB of storage and $499 for 128GB of storage. The Quest can cast its display to Google Chromecast devices, allowing for external viewing of VR content.
Despite being a smaller, less-powerful device than the PC-based hardware that typically drives an Oculus Rift, several games that appeared on the Rift store are making their way to the Quest, including Beat Saber, Space Pirate Trainer, Superhot VR, and more.
On November 18th, 2019 the Oculus Quest was given a new piece software called the Oculus Link. When hooked into a VR capable PC via a USB C to USB A 3.0 capable and operate and play Oculus Rift games utilizing the PC hardware. 
 
The Oculus Quest requires a phone running an Oculus app for setup purposes.
 

====Oculus Go:====
Is an even more budget friendly stand alone VR headset that allows instant Virtual Reality with the use over 1, 000 apps, the same kind of apps you'd see on a Roku device, Amazon Fire Stick device and others. There is a 32GB version for 199.00$ and a 64GB version for 248.99$. The headset comes with one controller and allows you to access most of the stuff you get on the Quest, including many of the games.</text>
      <sha1>7svveytcqiewxzw8kwq07korgpztcyv</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>Platforms/MicroBee</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>456726</id>
    <revision>
      <id>738782</id>
      <parentid>722583</parentid>
      <timestamp>2026-02-27T01:51:39Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Marino</username>
        <id>8</id>
      </contributor>
      <origin>738782</origin>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text bytes="438" sha1="0gja0n3nk26sh6z3zridxs58plbeq44" xml:space="preserve">{{Platform
|Name=MicroBee
|Guid=3045-168
|Image=https://www.giantbomb.com/a/uploads/scale_super/0/26/2974952-microbee_computer-in-a-book.jpg
|Deck=The MicroBee line of computers started with the release of a mail-order kit computer in 1982.
|ShortName=MBEE
|ReleaseDate=1982-02-01
|InstallBase=65,000
|OnlineSupport=No
|OriginalPrice=399.99
}}

The MicroBee line of computers started with the release of a mail-order kit computer in 1982.</text>
      <sha1>0gja0n3nk26sh6z3zridxs58plbeq44</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>Platforms/Microvision</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>456652</id>
    <revision>
      <id>738805</id>
      <parentid>722486</parentid>
      <timestamp>2026-02-27T21:44:33Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Marino</username>
        <id>8</id>
      </contributor>
      <origin>738805</origin>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text bytes="1980" sha1="emvt6lejkkki9wfsux8i72l9hjnvi5p" xml:space="preserve">{{Platform
|Name=Microvision
|Guid=3045-90
|Aliases=MVIS
|Image=https://www.giantbomb.com/a/uploads/scale_super/0/26/10813-MicroVision.jpg
|Deck=The first gaming handheld, Surpisingly big but extremely rare.
|ShortName=MVIS
|ReleaseDate=November 1979
|ReleaseDateType=Month
|OnlineSupport=No
|OriginalPrice=49.99
|Manufacturer=Companies/Milton_Bradley_Co
}}

Microvision was a hand-held gaming console that was released by the [[Companies/Milton_Bradley_Co|Milton Bradley]] Company in 1979. It was the very first handheld console to have interchangable cartridges. The Microvision led to moderate success but due to a fairly small screen and limited support from gaming companies and very few games, the sale and production of the Microvision ended in 1981.

Designed by Jay Smith (who later designed [[Platforms/Vectrex|Vectrex]]). With a small library, no tie in to a home unit, and a screen resolution that provided little ability to produce meaningful graphics, Microvision soon became little more than a memory. Still, the Microvision was a pioneer, overcoming the limitations of the light-emitting-diode displays that were standard for hand-held games at the time. 
 
Microvision units and cartridges are now very rare. Those that are still in existence are susceptible to three main problems: screen rot, static [http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Electrostatic_discharge ]damage, and keypad destruction.




==='''Technical specifications'''===

* CPU: Intel 8021/TI TMS1100 (on cartridge)
* Screen type and resolution: 16 x 16 pixel LCD
* Register width: 4 bit (TMS1100), 8 bit (8021)
* Processor speed: 100 kHz
* RAM: 32 nybbles (16 8-bit bytes, integrated into CPU)
* ROM: 2K
* Cartridge ROM: 2K masked (integrated into CPU; each game's CPU was different)
* Video Display Processor: Custom (made by Hughes)
* Sound: Piezo beeper
* Input: Twelve button keypad, one paddle
* Power requirements: One 9 volt battery (TMS1100 processors), Two 9 volt batteries (Intel 8021 process</text>
      <sha1>emvt6lejkkki9wfsux8i72l9hjnvi5p</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>Platforms/Mitsubishi Multi 8</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>456763</id>
    <revision>
      <id>738755</id>
      <parentid>722630</parentid>
      <timestamp>2026-02-26T22:56:52Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Marino</username>
        <id>8</id>
      </contributor>
      <origin>738755</origin>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text bytes="521" sha1="6si12aq9a3sqn1ccb3wvhwtj2b9vcpe" xml:space="preserve">{{Platform
|Name=Mitsubishi Multi 8
|Guid=3045-205
|Image=https://www.giantbomb.com/a/uploads/scale_super/0/1992/3341686-multi8.jpeg
|Deck=The Mitsubishi Multi 8 is a home computer released in Japan in 1983. Several cartridge-based games were released for it.
|ShortName=MM8
|ReleaseDate=1983
|ReleaseDateType=Year
|OnlineSupport=No
|OriginalPrice=1200
|Manufacturer=Companies/Mitsubishi_Electric
}}

The Mitsubishi Multi 8 is a home computer released in Japan in 1983. Several cartridge-based games were released for it.</text>
      <sha1>6si12aq9a3sqn1ccb3wvhwtj2b9vcpe</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>Platforms/Monon Color</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>456762</id>
    <revision>
      <id>738527</id>
      <parentid>722629</parentid>
      <timestamp>2026-02-24T03:22:50Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Marino</username>
        <id>8</id>
      </contributor>
      <origin>738527</origin>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text bytes="945" sha1="le0x7k57f4vrpg0kishwy2nj6l4qu99" xml:space="preserve">{{Platform
|Name=Monon Color
|Guid=3045-204
|Image=https://www.giantbomb.com/a/uploads/scale_super/0/1992/3341671-4c3443fd23473ce64296b645f6507ade.jpeg
|Deck=Monon Color is a handheld console developed and released in China in 2014. Twenty games were released for it including Marvel and Dragon Ball.
|ShortName=MC
|ReleaseDate=2014-10-01
|OnlineSupport=No
|Manufacturer=Companies/M_And_D
}}
&lt;div id='imageData' data-json='{"infobox":{"file":"3341671-4c3443fd23473ce64296b645f6507ade.jpeg","path":"0\/1992\/","mime":"image\/jpeg","sizes":"scale_super,square_avatar,scale_avatar,square_mini,scale_small,scale_medium,square_small,square_medium,screen_medium,screen_kubrick,scale_large,square_tiny,scale_tiny","caption":""},"background":[]}' /&gt;

==Specifications==
* Size: 130x81x33mm
* Screen: 320×240 TFT 2.4″
* CPU: 100MHz
* RAM: 15K
* Infrared Sensor
* Internal Speaker
* Headphone jack
* 3 AA batteries (rechargeable version later released)</text>
      <sha1>le0x7k57f4vrpg0kishwy2nj6l4qu99</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>Platforms/NEC PC 6001</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>456676</id>
    <revision>
      <id>797224</id>
      <parentid>752628</parentid>
      <timestamp>2026-03-21T01:01:08Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Marino</username>
        <id>8</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>Undo revision [[Special:Diff/752628|752628]] by [[Special:Contributions/Giantbomb|Giantbomb]] ([[User talk:Giantbomb|talk]])</comment>
      <origin>797224</origin>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text bytes="990" sha1="099546mrhz1xl3sbzd8rwo3ug1qsy5r" xml:space="preserve">{{Platform
|Name=NEC PC-6001
|Guid=3045-115
|Image=https://www.giantbomb.com/a/uploads/scale_super/0/4/1151382-250px_nec_pc_6001.jpg
|Deck=The first in NEC's PC-6000 line of computers.
|ShortName=6001
|ReleaseDate=November 1981
|ReleaseDateType=Month
|InstallBase=150,000
|OnlineSupport=No
|OriginalPrice=900
|Manufacturer=Companies/NEC_Home_Electronics_Ltd
}}
The PC-6001 was first released in November of 1981 in Japan at the price of 89,800 yen. A special version branded "NEC Trek" was released in North American territories shortly afterwards.
'''Standard definition'''
* Processor: μPD780C-1（ Z80-A compatible） 3.993600MHz
* ROM: 16 KB (Basic) 4 KB (character ROM)
* RAM: 16KB (expandable up to 32KB)
* Sound chip: General Instrument AY-3-8910 (PSG)
* Display resolutions: 256x192, 256x128, 128x192, 128x128, 64x48
* Display colors: monochrome (256x192) / 2 (128x192) / 9 (64x48)
* Interface: Tape (600 / 1200 baud), RGB, Centronics, Atari Joystick (2), ROM/RAM cartridges, Audio</text>
      <sha1>099546mrhz1xl3sbzd8rwo3ug1qsy5r</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>Platforms/NEC PC 8801</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>456670</id>
    <revision>
      <id>973861</id>
      <parentid>797219</parentid>
      <timestamp>2026-05-18T10:10:21Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Nintendo</username>
        <id>3860</id>
      </contributor>
      <origin>973861</origin>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text bytes="1907" sha1="3ri18g4g7gwoudfk8mjrc9la98l47b4" xml:space="preserve">{{Platform
|Guid=3045-109
|Name=NEC PC-8801
|Image=https://www.giantbomb.com/a/uploads/scale_super/0/4647/961635-nec_pc8801_1.jpg
|Deck=This NEC computer was released in 1981 and is more commonly referred to as the PC-88.
|ShortName=PC88
|ReleaseDateType=Month
|MonthPart=August
|MonthYearPart=1981
|OnlineSupport=No
|Manufacturer=Companies/NEC_Home_Electronics_Ltd
}}
&lt;div id="imageData" data-json="{&amp;quot;infobox&amp;quot;:{&amp;quot;file&amp;quot;:&amp;quot;961635-nec_pc8801_1.jpg&amp;quot;,&amp;quot;path&amp;quot;:&amp;quot;0\/4647\/&amp;quot;,&amp;quot;mime&amp;quot;:&amp;quot;image\/jpeg&amp;quot;,&amp;quot;sizes&amp;quot;:&amp;quot;square_avatar,square_small,square_avatar,scale_medium,screen_medium,scale_small,scale_large,scale_avatar,square_mini,square_tiny,square_medium,scale_super,screen_kubrick&amp;quot;,&amp;quot;caption&amp;quot;:&amp;quot;&amp;quot;},&amp;quot;background&amp;quot;:[]}"&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
Released in 1981, the PC-8801 was an 8-bit [[Platforms/PC|computerfrom]] [[Companies/NEC Home Electronics Ltd|NEC]] that dominated the 8-bit [[Locations/Japan|Japanesecomputer]] market in the 1980's, beating out competition from the [[Platforms/Sharp X1|Sharp X1]], [[Platforms/FM 7|Fujitsu FM-7]], and [[Platforms/MSX|MSX]].
In 1983, the [http://www.computinghistory.org.uk/det/16680/NEC-PC-8201A PC-8201A] was produced by [http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Kyocera Kyocera] as one of the world's first laptop computers.
In 1987, a more advanced 16-bit model was released, the PC-88 VA, which featured some of the graphical capabilities of NEC's [[Platforms/TurboGrafx 16|PC Engine]] (TurboGrafx-16) console along with the Yamaha YM2608 stereo FM sound chip, in order to rival the more powerful 32-bit [[Platforms/Sharp X68000|Sharp X68000]] computer.
By the end of the 80's, the PC-88 was superceded by the [[Platforms/NEC PC 9801|NEC PC-98]] line, which would dominate the Japanese computer market during the late 80's to 90's, and become one of the best-selling computers of all time.</text>
      <sha1>3ri18g4g7gwoudfk8mjrc9la98l47b4</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>Platforms/NEC PC 9801</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>456673</id>
    <revision>
      <id>973862</id>
      <parentid>973814</parentid>
      <timestamp>2026-05-18T10:18:42Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Nintendo</username>
        <id>3860</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>Play Station influences</comment>
      <origin>973862</origin>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text bytes="20162" sha1="6p6mhh4uoot3ui0fptpol90ysuzkf7p" xml:space="preserve">{{Platform
|Guid=3045-112
|Name=NEC PC-9801
|Aliases=PC-98,PC-9800,PC-9821,SMC-7000,SMC-7K
|Image=https://www.giantbomb.com/a/uploads/scale_super/5/59247/1129864-pc_9801_l.jpg
|Deck=A 16/32-bit Japanese personal computer system launched by NEC in 1982. It was the most successful computer platform in Japan and one of the best-selling computer systems of the 20th century. It has a very large video game library with thousands of titles, the majority of which were never released outside Japan.
|ShortName=PC98
|ReleaseDateType=Month
|MonthPart=October
|MonthYearPart=1982
|InstallBase=18,300,000
|OnlineSupport=Limited
|OriginalPrice=1200.00
|Manufacturer=Companies/NEC_Home_Electronics_Ltd
}}
== Overview ==
PC-98 is a series of 16/32-bit Japanese [[Platforms/PC|personal computers]], designed by [[Companies/NEC Home Electronics Ltd|NEC]], but also licensed to other companies (including Sony). In contrast to its [[Platforms/NEC PC 8801|PC-88]] predecessor, the PC-98 was initially created as a business machine, but over time it eventually became popular with game developers. The PC-98 is based around Intel 8086 and later MIPS compatible processors, but the design is proprietary, and it is not compatible with the [[Platforms/PC|IBM PC]] or clones, although versions of DOS, UNIX and Windows NT were ported to it.
The system has a very large library of video games, consisting of more than 4,000 commercial titles and countless more [[Concepts/Indie|doujin]] ([[Concepts/Indie|indie]]) titles. The games and system are difficult to find outside of Japan, even on eBay. There are a few sites however that sell the games and systems.

== History ==
When the PC-98 was launched in 1982, it was initially priced at ¥298,000 (about $1400 in 1982 dollars, equivalent to about $3400 in 2012 dollars). The PC-98 computer platform eventually went on to sell more than 18 million units in [[Locations/Japan|Japan]] by 1999, surpassing the [[Platforms/Commodore 64|Commodore 64]] (17 million units) as the best-selling home computer system of the 20th century.
[[Platforms/PC|Laptop]] versions of the PC-9801 were also being sold in the late 1980s. The first was the PC-98 LT, one of the first mass-market laptops, released in 1986. It is considered the world's first major [http://www.computerandvideogames.com/399405/features/history-lesson-turbografx-pc-engine laptop PC]. The world's first notebook computer was released in 1989, NEC's UltraLite. By 1990, the 32-bit PC-9801 NC model became the world's first laptop/notebook computer with a colour TFT LCD display.

=== NEC APC and rivalry with IBM PC overseas ===
In the early 1980's, the PC-9801 was more advanced than Western computer platforms. The PC-98 featured the first dedicated computer GPU chip, the [http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/NEC_%C2%B5PD7220 NEC 7220 GDC], along with a 16-bit NEC CPU. It featured higher VGA display resolutions (initially up to 640x475 pixels, then up to 1024x1024 in 1983, and then up to 1120x750 pixels by 1985) in order to more accurately display Japanese text, a wider [http://books.google.co.uk/books?id=_C8EAAAAMBAJ&amp;pg=PA33 color palette] (16, 64, 256 or 4096 colors displayed out of a 65536 color palette), Yamaha [[Concepts/Chiptune|FM synthesis]] sound chips for higher-quality audio, and a modem for [[Concepts/Online|online]] internet access.
NEC attempted to introduce the NEC PC-9801 in [[Locations/North America|North America]], where it was re-branded as the NEC APC in 1982. NEC, the largest semiconductor company of the 1980s, marketed the APC III as the most powerful computer on the market and more reliable machine than leading competitor [[Companies/IBM|IBM]]'s [[Platforms/PC|PCplatform]], with the APC III offering twice as much speed (8 MHz), storage (720 KB floppy disks) and resolution (640x479 pixels) at around the same price. Despite the superior hardware compared to its competitors, the APC III eventually failed to make in impact in North America, largely due to the rise of IBM PC clones, which also negatively impacted IBM's share of the North American PC market.
While the NEC APC was unsuccessful in North America, it became successful in the [[Locations/Asia|Asia]]-Pacific region, [http://www.old-computers.com/museum/computer.asp?c=333 particularly] in [[Locations/Australia|Australia]].

=== Rivalry with Sharp X68000 and FM Towns in Japan ===
The PC-98 was later technically surpassed by fellow Japanese rivals [[Companies/Sharp Corporation|Sharp]] and [[Companies/Fujitsu|Fujitsu]] when they launched their own more powerful 16/32-bit computers, the [[Platforms/Sharp X68000|Sharp X68000]] and [[Platforms/FM Towns|FM Towns]], in 1987 and 1989, respectively.
In response, the PC-98 began using 32-bit Intel CPU (or in Sony's case, MIPS CPU) processors from 1987 and supported the CD-ROM format from 1989. While both rival computers were capable of more advanced, [[Platforms/Arcade|arcade]] quality graphics (especially in the X68000's case) and/or greater multimedia features (in the FM Towns' case), neither computer platform was able to dethrone the PC-98 as the Japanese computer market leader.

=== 3D graphics cards and rivalry with IBM-compatible PC's in Japan ===
Just as [[Platforms/PC|IBM-compatible PC's]] were on the rise in the mid-1990s, [[Companies/NEC Home Electronics Ltd|NEC]] and [[Companies/Sony Interactive Entertainment|Sony]] came back by releasing the first [[Concepts/Polygonal 3D|3D graphics]] accelerator cards on the market, initially for the PC-98. By 1984 onwards, [[Companies/Sony Interactive Entertainment|Sony]] started working on the first 3D graphics board, the System G which would be later released in 1987 exclusively for the [[Platforms/NEC PC 8801|PC-88]] and PC-98. This allowed the PC-98 to produce the most advanced [[Concepts/Polygonal 3D|3D graphics]] seen on a home system up until that time, with a polygon rendering performance directly influencing the [[Platforms/PlayStation|PlayStation]] console and even rivaling the then upcoming [[Platforms/Nintendo 64|Nintendo 64]]; in contrast, rival early 1996 3D graphics accelerators for IBM PC clones, such as Creative Labs' 3D Blaster and [[Companies/NVIDIA Corporation|NVIDIA]]'s NV1, were unable to rival the PlayStation's 3D graphics. By 1994 onwards, Sony released the DTL-H2000 development board which allowed users to develop games for the [[Platforms/PlayStation|PlayStation]] on the PC-98 and DOS/V computers. In 1995, NEC released the second 3D graphics card, the PC-FXGA (PC-FX Game Accelerator), exclusively for the PC-98. The PC-FXGA was originally intended for both the PC-98 computer and the [[Platforms/PC FX|PC-FX]] console, with as a [[Concepts/Homebrew|homebrew development]] kit for the [[Platforms/PC FX|PC-FX]] console, allowing the PC-98 to play PC-FX games. However, the PC-FX console lacked the 3D graphical capabilities of the PC-FXGA card, due to the FXGA's HuC6273 graphics chip (originally intended for the PC-FX) never actually being used by the PC-FX console.
The PC-FXGA was the most powerful 3D graphics card on the market up until it was surpassed by NEC's successor, the PowerVR, in early 1996. Unlike the PC-FXGA, the succeeding PowerVR was no longer exclusive to the PC-98, but supported both the PC-98 and IBM-compatible PC's. The PowerVR was able to produce near [[Platforms/Arcade|arcade]] quality 3D graphics, demonstrated by a near arcade quality port of [[Companies/Namco|Namco]]'s [[Games/Rave Racer|Rave Racer]], though this PowerVR port was later cancelled. The PowerVR would not be rivaled until the arrival of the 3dfx Voodoo graphics card for IBM-compatible PC's in late 1996. Though both the PowerVR and Voodoo were more or less evenly matched when it came to 3D capabilities, it was the Voodoo that became the most popular graphics card line-up of the late 1990s, due to the PowerVR's lack of third-party software support. Besides the PowerVR, the PC-98 very few other 3D graphics cards supported the PC-98.

=== Decline ===
The PC-98 would continue to dominate the Japanese computer market until the late 1990s, when the arrival of [[Companies/Xbox Game Studios|Microsoft]] Windows 95 alongside 32-bit consoles like the [[Platforms/PlayStation|PlayStation]] made it possible for [[Platforms/PC|IBM-compatible PC's]] to accurately output Japanese text, leading to the rise of IBM-compatible PC's in Japan and marking the end of the 'Golden Age' of Japanese computer gaming.
By the end of the 1990s, the PC-98's dwindling market share as well as NEC's greater support for the growing IBM PC market eventually led to the PC-98 slowly losing ground to IBM-compatible PC's. In 1997, the PC-98 NX and (Sony VAIO) became one of the first computer platforms produced in line with the PC97 System Design Guide standard, which would later become the worldwide standard for IBM-compatible PC's. As a result, PC-98 standards eventually merged with IBM-compatible PC standards and as well PlayStation standards, bringing an end to the traditional PC-98 platform by the early 2000s, succeeded by IBM-compatible PC-98 NX computers which are still manufactured through to the present day.

== Technical specifications ==

=== '''Main processors''' ===
'''Main CPU (Central Processing Unit) processor''':

* 1982: 16-bit [[Companies/NEC Home Electronics Ltd|NEC]]μPD8086 (i8086 compatible) @ 5 MHz
* 1983: 16-bit Intel 8086-2 @ 5-8 MHz
* 1984: 16-bit NEC V30 @ 8-10 MHz / 16-bit Intel 80286 @ 8 MHz
* 1986: 16-bit NEC V50 @ 8 MHz / NEC V30 @ 8-10 MHz / Intel 80286 @ 8-10 MHz
* 1987: 32-bit MIPS R2000 @ 12.5 MHz / Intel 80386 @ 16 MHz / NEC V30 @ 10 MHz / Intel 80286 @ 8-10 MHz
* 1988: 32-bit MIPS R2000A @ 15 MHz / Intel i386DX @ 16-20 MHz / NEC V30 @ 8-10 MHz / Intel 80286 @ 10-12 MHz
* 1989: 32-bit MIPS R3000 @ 20 MHz / Intel i386DX @ 20 MHz / Intel i386SX @ 16 MHz / NEC V30 @ 8-10 MHz
* 1990: 32-bit MIPS R3000A @ 25 MHz / Intel i486DX @ 25 MHz / Intel i386DX @ 25-33 MHz / Intel i386SX @ 20 MHz
* 1991: 32-bit MIPS R3000A @ 40 MHz / Intel i486SX @ 16-25 MHz / Intel i386DX @ 25-33 MHz
* 1992: 64-bit MIPS R4000 @ 100 MHz / 32-bit [[Companies/Texas Instruments|TI]] 486SXLC2-40 @ 32-40 MHz / Intel i486DX2 @ 66 MHz / Intel 80486 @ 16-20 MHz / Intel i386SX @ 16-20 MHz
* 1993: 64-bit MIPS R4400 @ 133 MHz / 32-bit Intel i486SX @ 33 MHz
* 1994: 64-bit MIPS R4600 @ 133 MHz / 32-bit Intel DX4 @ 100 MHz / 32-bit Intel Pentium @ 66-90 MHz
* 1996: 64-bit MIPS R10000 @ 195 MHz / 1-2x Pentium Pro @ 200 MHz, 1-2x Pentium @ 120-200 MHz, AMD X5-133ADZ @ 133 MHz
* 1997: 64-bit MIPS R10000A @ 250 MHz / 1-2x Pentium II @ 266 MHz / Pentium MMX @ 200 MHz / Pentium @ 166 MHz
* 2000: 64-bit MIPS R12000 @ 360 MHz / Intel Celeron @ 443 MHz

'''Additional processors:'''

* '&lt;nowiki/&gt;'''''Additional CPU processor'''''': 16-bit NEC V30 @ 8 MHz (1986 onwards)
* '''ODP (OverDrive Processor)'''
* 1992: 32-bit NEC PC-9801BX-01 (based on Intel i486DX2 ODP) @ 40 MHz
* 1993: 32-bit NEC PC-9801BX-01 (based on Intel i486DX2 ODP) @ 40-66 MHz
* 1996: 32-bit Intel DX4 ODP @ 100 MHz
* '''FPU (Floating Point Unit) co-processor'''
* 1982: Intel 8087 @ 5 MHz
* 1983: Intel 8087 @ 8 MHz
* 1984: Intel 8087 @ 10 MHz
* 1987: MIPS R2010 @ 16MHz / Intel 80387 @ 16 MHz
* 1988: MIPS R2010 @ 16-20MHz / Intel 80387 @ 16-20 MHz
* 1989: MIPS R3010 @ 20MHz / Intel 80387 @ 20 MHz
* 1992: 32-bit Cyrix Cx83S87-33 @ 16 MHz / Cyrix Cx83S87-25 @ 20 MHz / Intel 487SX

=== '''Graphics''' ===

* '''Main GPU (Graphics Processing Unit) processors''':
* 1982: 2x [[Companies/NEC Home Electronics Ltd|NEC]] µPD7220 GDC (Graphics Display Controllers) (one for graphics, one for text)
* 1983: NEC GRCG (Graphic Charger) / 2x NEC µPD7220
* 1986: NEC μPD72120 AGDC (Advanced Graphics Display Controller) / 2x NEC µPD7220
* 1987: NEC EGC (Enhanced Graphic Charger) / 2x NEC µPD7220 / Sony System G 3D Graphics Accelerator
* 1992: NEC EGC / 2x NEC µPD7220 / S3 86C775 (Trio64V2/DX, 4 MB VRAM)
* 1997: STMicroelectronics RIVA 128 3D Multimedia Accelerator (AGP)
* '''Maximum resolution''': 640x475 (1982), 1024x1024 (1983), 1120x750 (1985), 1280x1024 (1987), 1280x768 (1994), 1600x1200 (1996), 1920x1440 (1997)
* '''Maximum colour palette''': 4096 (1982), 65,536 (1987), 16.78 million (1993)
* '''On-screen colours''': 16 (1982), 256 (1986), 4096 (1993), 16.78 million (1995)

'''[[Concepts/2D|2D graphics]] accelerator cards''':

* 1983: NEC PC-9801-24 (NEC GRCG, 4096 colour palette, 16 simultaneous colours)
* 1987: NEC EGC (Enhanced Graphic Charger, 65536 colour palette, 16 to 65536 colours simultaneously)
* 1992: NEC EGC / S3 86C775 (Trio64V2/DX, 4 MB VRAM)
* 1993: Matrox MGA-II (2 MB VRAM) / S3 86C928 (1 MB VRAM) / Cirrus Logic GD5428 (1 MB VRAM)
* 1994: NEC PC-9821X-B01 (Matrox MGA-II GPU @ 175 MHz, 2-4 MB VRAM) / S3 Vision864 (2 MB)
* 1995: NEC PC-9821X-B03 (Matrox Millenium MGA 2064W GPU @ 175 MHz, 2-4 MB VRAM)
* 1996: NEC PC-9821X-B03 (4 MB VRAM) / Trident Providia9685/TGUI9682TMXGi (2 MB VRAM)

'''[[Concepts/Polygonal 3D|3D graphics]] accelerator cards''':

* 1994: Sony DTL-H2000 (Development Tool) * Additional CPU: 32-bit MIPS R3051 (CXD8530CQ) RISC CPU @ 33.8688 MHz
* Main GPU: 32-bit Sony GTE (designed by [[Companies/Toshiba Corporation|Toshiba]] and LSI Logic)
* Additional GPU: V1 (Rev 90025), V2 (Rev 90048), V3 (Rev 90082), V4 (Rev 90182)
* Motion JPEG decoder: Motion Decoder (MDEC)
* Additional sound chip: Sony SPC-700 (ADPCM, PSG, mixer, DAC)
* Video RAM (VRAM) memory: 4.25 MB * 2 MB main DRAM (Dynamic RAM), 1 MB frame buffer RAM, 1.25 MB fast-page DRAM
* Performance: 100,000 polygons/sec, 10 million pixels/second
* Resolution: 256x240, 256x256, 512x240, 512x256, 512x480, 512x512, 640x480 (@ 30 frames/sec), 768x512, 800x600, 1024x768, 1024x1024, 1280x1024
* Colours: 16.78 million
* Features: [[Concepts/Flat Shading|Flat shading]], [[Concepts/Gouraud Shading|Gouraud shading]], texture mapping
* 1995: NEC PC-FXGA (PC-FX Game Accelerator) * Additional CPU: 32-bit NEC V810 (μPD70732GD-25) RISC CPU @ 21.48 MHz
* Main GPU: HuC6273 (designed by [[Companies/Hudson Entertainment Inc|Hudson]] and Kubota Comps)
* Additional GPU: Hudson HuC6272, HuC6271, 2x HuC6270, HuC6261
* Motion JPEG decoder: Hudson HuC6271
* Additional sound chip: Hudson HuC6230 (ADPCM, PSG, mixer, DAC)
* Video RAM (VRAM) memory: 4.25 MB * 2 MB main DRAM (Dynamic RAM), 1 MB frame buffer RAM, 1.25 MB fast-page DRAM
* Performance: 100,000 polygons/sec, 10 million pixels/second
* Colours: 16.78 million
* Features: [[Concepts/Flat Shading|Flat shading]], [[Concepts/Gouraud Shading|Gouraud shading]], texture mapping
* 1996: NEC PC 3DEngine / NEC PC-9821VC-B03 * Main GPU processor: 64-bit NEC PowerVR PCX1 (μPD62010) @ 66 MHz
* Additional GPU processors: * NEC ISP (Image Synthesis Processor)
* NEC TSP (Texture &amp;#x26;amp;amp; Shading Processor)
* NEC MC (Memory Controller)
* Video RAM (VRAM) memory: 4 MB
* Bandwidth: 492 MB per secondc (including 264 MB/sec texture memory bandwidth)
* Performance: 250,000 polygons/sec, 60 million pixels/sec, 60 million texels/sec
* Resolution: 320x200, 640x480 (@ 30 frames/sec), 800x600, 1024x768, 1024x1024
* Colours: 16.78 million
* Features: Lighting, shading (including pixel shader and vertex shader), texture mapping unit, perspective correct texture mapping, texture filtering, bilinear filtering, mipmapping, per-pixel fogging, exponential fogging, shadows, translucency, render output unit, anti-aliasing
* 1997: NEC PC 3DEngine2 * GPU: 64-bit NEC PowerVR PCX2 (μPD62011) @ 66 MHz
* Video RAM (VRAM) memory: 4 MB
* Texture memory: 1-4 MB
* Bandwidth: 541 MB/se
* Performance: 66 million pixels/sec, 66 million texels/sec * Polygons/sec: 500,000 (practical performance), 1.5 million (theoretical peak)
* Resolution: 640x480, 800x600 (@ 30 frames/sec), 1024x768, 1024x1024, 1920x1440
* Colours: 16.78 million
* Compatibility: Direct3D, RenderWare, SurRender, GLQuake, PowerSGL Direct
* Features: Adaptive bilinear filtering, 32-bit Z buffer, real-time shadows, lighting, smooth shading, highlighting, fogging, hidden surface removal, plane modeling, render output unit, texture mapping unit, mipmapping, 32-bit depth precision, 8/16-bit texture, anti-aliasing, translucency
* 1997: NEC PK-UG-X003 * GPU: 3DLabs Permedia 2 @ 230 MHz
* Video RAM (VRAM) memory: 8 MB
* Performance: 1 million polygons/sec (theoretical peak)
* 1998: NEC PK-UG-X003E (3DLabs Permedia 2 GPU @ 230 MHz, 8 MB VRAM)
* 1998: NEC GA-VDB16/PCI (3dfx Voodoo Banshee GPU @ 100 MHz, 16 MB VRAM)

=== '''Sound''' ===

* '''Default''': * 1982: Internal beeper
* 1985: NEC PC-9801-26 sound board * Sound chip: Yamaha YM2203 (OPN)
* Channels: 3 FM (Frequency Modulation) synthesis, 3 SSG/PSG
* 1987: NEC PC-9801-26K sound board, Yamaha YM2608 (OPNA) FM synth sound chip
* 1991: 16-bit NEC PC-9801-86 sound board * Sound chip: Yamaha YM2608B (OPNA)
* Channels: 6 FM synth, 5 rhythm, 3 SSG/PSG, 1 noise, 1 ADPCM (8-bit @ 2-16 Hz)
* Other features: Stereo, CD-quality PCM (16-bit @ 44.1 Hz), linear PCM
* 1992: NEC PC-9801-86 board, Yamaha YM2203C (OPN) FM chip, Crystal CS4231 chip
* '''Supported''': Sound cards (from 1985), CD audio (from 1989), DVD audio (from 1997)
* '''Sound cards''': NEC sound boards, Yamaha FM synthesis sound chips, Roland MIDI modules, Creative Sound Blaster cards

=== '''Memory''' ===

* '''Main RAM (Random Access Memory)'''* Default: 128 KB (1982), 128-256 KB (1984), 256-640 KB (1985), 384-1152 KB (1986), 1536-1664 KB (1987), 1-2 MB (1988), 1-3 MB (1989), 1-8 MB (1990), 2-22 MB (1992), 8-34 MB (1994), 16-34 MB (1995), 32-34 MB (1997), 32-256 MB (1998)
* Upgradable: 640 KB (1982), 768 KB (1985), 9 MB (1986), 14.5 MB (1987), 15 MB (1989), 34 MB (1990), 48 MB (1991), 64 MB (1992), 74 MB (1993), 256 MB (1994), 512 MB (1996)
* '''Dynamic RAM (DRAM) memory'''* 1992: Parity, non-parity, NEC PC-9801-61 (parity SIMM)
* 1996: FPDRAM (Fast-Page DRAM), EDO DRAM (Extended Data-Out DRAM)
* '''Main VRAM ('''Video RAM)''' memory'''* Default: 48 KB (1982), 204 KB (1983), 256 KB (1987), 1-4 MB (1992), 2-4 MB (1994), 4 MB (1996), 4-6 MB (1997)
* Upgradable: 4 MB (1992), 8.25 MB (1994), 11.25 MB (1995), 12 MB (1996), 14 MB (1997), 32 MB (1998)
* '''Text VRAM memory''': 12 KB
* '''L1 (1st-level) cache memory''': 8 KB write-back cache (1992)
* '''L2 (2nd-level) cache memory'''* Default: 64 KB (1990), 128 KB (1992), 256-512 KB (1994)
* Upgradable: 256 KB (1992), 512 KB (1994)
* '''ROM (Read-Only Memory) memory''': 96 KB (1993)

=== '''Storage''' ===

* '''Storage''': Floppy disk (8", 5" &amp; 3.5"), (1982) hard disk drive (1984), CD-ROM (1989), DVD-ROM (1997)
* '''Hard disk drive''': 10-20 MB (1984), 20 MB (1985), 40 MB (1987), 40-100 MB (1990), 40-730 MB (1992), 120-730 MB (1993), 510-1024 MB (1994), 1-3 GB (1996), 2-3 GB (1997), 8 GB (2000)
* '''CD-ROM speed''': 1x (1989), 2x-4x (1994), 4x-8x (1996), 6x-13x (1997), 8x-20x (1998), 24x (2000)

=== '''Other specifications''' ===

* '''Display''': * 1982: 15" colour CRT monitor
* 1990: TFT LCD display
* 1994: 15" TFT LCD monitor
* 1997: 17" display (with built-in PC-9821C166 speakers)
* '''Input''': Keyboard, NEC PC-9872K mouse, joystick, gamepad
* '''Supported operating systems''': DOS, OS/2, SMC-UX, GX-Windows, Windows NT 3.1 / 3.5 / 3.51 / 4.0
* '''Expansion slots''': 5 (1982), 4-6 (1983), 5-6 (1993), 4-8 (1994), 7-9 (1996), AGP (1997)
* '''Other options''': [[Concepts/Online|Online]] modem, joystick, gamepad, SCSI, VGA, [[Concepts/Multiplayer LAN|LAN]], headphone, microphone, wireless mouse, wireless keyboard, NEC FC-9801-KB7 keyboard, printer, TV tuner, MPEG card

== External links ==

* [http://translate.google.co.uk/translate?sl=ja&amp;tl=en&amp;u=http://www.pc-9800.net/db_98/index.htm With98], PC-98 hardware database
* [http://www.retropc.net/yui/np2help/pc98x1.html PC-98], RetroPC hardware database
* [http://museum.ipsj.or.jp/en/computer/personal/0011.html NEC PC-9801], IPSJ Computer Museum hardware database
* [http:/fullmotionvideo.free.fr Tokugawa Corp], PC-98 game database
* [http://translate.google.co.uk/translate?hl=en&amp;sl=ja&amp;u=http://blog.goo.ne.jp/limited_terra/e/cc4b730116a5871988366cd8911b9a69 PC-98 graphics chipsets]
* [http://books.google.co.uk/books?id=_C8EAAAAMBAJ&amp;pg=PA31 NEC's 7220 GDC Chip]</text>
      <sha1>6p6mhh4uoot3ui0fptpol90ysuzkf7p</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>Platforms/NUON</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>456647</id>
    <revision>
      <id>738626</id>
      <parentid>722479</parentid>
      <timestamp>2026-02-24T22:23:42Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Marino</username>
        <id>8</id>
      </contributor>
      <origin>738626</origin>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text bytes="5591" sha1="okuz8cauis8sj9qz1lox3jwvac2w0zp" xml:space="preserve">{{Platform
|Name=NUON
|Guid=3045-85
|Aliases=Project X
|Image=https://www.giantbomb.com/a/uploads/scale_super/0/4647/2954590-nuon-n2000-wcontroller-l.jpg
|Deck=Originally called "Project X", the Nuon started out as a concept for a stand alone console but instead became a built in 3D enhancement technology in a handful of DVD players.  NUON technology fared abysmally and the platform only managed to get 8 titles.
|ShortName=NUON
|ReleaseDate=1999-03-09
|ReleaseDateType=Month
|OriginalPrice=0.00
|Manufacturer=Companies/VMI
}}
&lt;div id='imageData' data-json='{"infobox":{"file":"2954590-nuon-n2000-wcontroller-l.jpg","path":"0\/4647\/","mime":"image\/jpeg","sizes":"square_small,square_mini,square_medium,square_tiny,scale_super,scale_small,scale_avatar,scale_medium,square_avatar,scale_large,screen_kubrick,screen_medium","caption":null},"background":[]}' /&gt;

==Overview==
NUON was a failed attempt by [[Companies/Toshiba_Corporation|Toshiba]], Motorola, Samsung, and Raite Optoelectronics to add gaming, internet, and enhanced navigation to certain DVD players. NUON technology was developed by [[Companies/VMI|VM Labs Inc]]. as an attempt to turn passive digital video into an interactive experience. NUON DVD players were supposed to be the "all-in-one" digital media experience. Richard Miller, using experience gained developing [[Companies/Atari|Atari]] [[Platforms/Jaguar|Jaguar]] hardware, created a powerful 128-bit processor to embed in DVD players. The NUON had the power to decode audio and video while providing and enhanced UI and trick-play modes. More importantly, it provided a platform for 3D digital interactive content straight from a DVD player. NUON technology was only added to a handful of DVD players and support for the platform was abysmal. VM Labs filed for bankruptcy in 2001, just one year after the release of the NUON. VM Labs sold the NUON technology to Genesis Microchip, where development ceased after July 2002.

==Hardware==
At the core of the NUON is the Aries 3 chip, which was based on a 128-bit, 4 way parallel VLIW processor architecture. It manages the CPU, decodes audio and video, and preforms all system management. A hardware block on the chip assisted with MPEG video decoding so the Aries 3 was free to process other instructions. The chip was very powerful for it's time.
Features of the Aries 3:
* MPEG-1 and MPEG-2 audio/video decoding
* 5.1 channel Dolby Digital audio decoding
* Extended DVD trick modes
* 32-voice wave table synthesizer
* MP3 audio decoding
* Content Scrambling System descrambling module
* Video Scaling
* 3D video gaming
The first DVD player to use NUON technology was the Toshiba SD-2300. The technology in the few available NUON DVD players raised the price around $100 over comparable players. The choice to market games to the movie audience ultimately ended up being a mistake. Sales were very poor, and support was absolutely terrible. The first NUON enhanced DVD was the software/movie Bedazzled by Fox Home Video. Just about every other publisher waited on the technology and support never truly came to the device. With the [[Platforms/PlayStation_2|PlayStation 2]]'s release imminent as a game console that plays DVDs rather than a DVD player that plays games, the chances of success for the NUON had gone. The public opted for the game console that was cheaper and had much better support for games.
The NUON had a variety of controllers, one popular standard one being white in color with a D-pad with 4 buttons. The stealth gamepad is 3-pronged controller with a mini analog stick, a D-pad, and a trigger button. It is designed very similarly to the [[Platforms/Nintendo_64|Nintendo 64]]'s controller. A memory unit was planned for Q1 2002 release for the NUON in sizes ranging from 2MB to 4MB, but was canceled. Many games used passwords to make up for the lack of a released memory card.

==Software==
Only eight games were ever released for NUON. The graphics are comparable to early [[Platforms/PlayStation_2|PlayStation 2]] games, and are most notable in [[Games/Iron_Soldier_3_2000|Iron Soldier 3]], a mech combat game. The best game is generally regarded to be [[Games/Tempest_3000|Tempest 3000]] (many sources consider it the only truly playable game) and it's valued at much more than the other NUON games. Games were controlled via a proprietary controller. Depending on the model, there could be one or two controller ports.

==Homebrew==
The NUON homebrew community was more active than the commercial community. In late 2001, VM Labs released a homebrew SDK so developers could put out their own homebrew NUON software, even as the platform died and faded into obscurity. Homebrew games are simply burned to CD-Rs

===List of models that can play NUON homebrew from CD-R.===
* Samsung DVD-N501
* Samsung DVDN504
* Samsung DVDN505
* RCA DRC300N
* RCA DRC480N
''The RCA models cannot play commercial NUON games.''
''In 2022 the authentication keys to sign code for use from DVD were released and now homebrew can be played from all models.''

===List of NUON homebrew===
* Ambient Monsters
* Atari / C64 Video Game Music Player
* Atari 800 Emulator
* Atari 2600 PacMan (Hacked version of Chomp)
* BOMB
* Breakout
* Chomp (Sample game included with the second NUON SDK)
* Decaying Orbit
* Doom Shareware
* Pac-Man - Tournament Edition (Hacked version of Chomp)
* SameGame - Colors
* SameGame - Shapes
* Sheshell's Sea Adventure
* Snake
* Synth Demo
* Yaroze Classics (Katapila, Invs and BreakDown)

==Links==
[http:/www.nuon-dome.com http://www.nuon-dome.com/], a site dedicated to the NUON.</text>
      <sha1>okuz8cauis8sj9qz1lox3jwvac2w0zp</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>Platforms/N Gage</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>456606</id>
    <revision>
      <id>738624</id>
      <parentid>738613</parentid>
      <timestamp>2026-02-24T22:17:12Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Frobie</username>
        <id>300</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>add image</comment>
      <origin>738624</origin>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text bytes="8384" sha1="irr59misa3xvtibsu6xwij7m1hpdm7j" xml:space="preserve">{{Platform
|Name=N-Gage
|Guid=3045-34
|Aliases=N-Gage QD,Nokia n85,n85,Nokia Download Service
|Image=https://www.giantbomb.com/a/uploads/scale_super/1/14912/702653-ngageqd.jpg
|Deck=The N-Gage (later re-released as N-Gage QD) was a failed gaming platform developed by phone manufacturer Nokia. Games in MMC-Card format were sold for the platform, and towards the end, games were available for download to your own MMC.
|ShortName=NGE
|ReleaseDate=2003-10-07
|ReleaseDateType=Month
|InstallBase=3,000,000
|OnlineSupport=Yes
|OriginalPrice=299.99
|Manufacturer=Companies/Nokia
}}
&lt;div id='imageData' data-json='{"infobox":{"file":"702653-ngageqd.jpg","path":"1\/14912\/","mime":"image\/jpeg","sizes":"scale_medium,scale_super,square_mini,square_medium,square_small,screen_medium,square_avatar,scale_small,square_tiny,scale_large,scale_avatar,scale_tiny,ignore_jpg_scale_small,screen_kubrick","caption":""},"background":{"file":"11732-QDsidetalkin.jpg","path":"0\/26\/","mime":"image\/jpeg","sizes":"scale_medium,scale_super,square_mini,square_medium,square_small,screen_medium,square_tiny,scale_tiny,screen_kubrick_wide,scale_large,scale_small,scale_avatar,screen_kubrick,square_avatar","caption":"Sidetalkin' into a QD? That's crazy talk!"}}' /&gt;

==Overview==
The N-Gage was a cellphone and handheld gaming platform, released by [[Companies/Nokia|Nokia]] in 2003. It was supposed to be a competitor to Nintendo's [[Platforms/Game_Boy_Advance|Gameboy Advance]], but was unsuccessful because of its clumsy design. Today the N-Gage brand is used for Nokia's mobile gaming service, available for the company's N-Series phones which is itself now obsolete. It had some big design flaws, that made the gaming and calling aspects of the phone clumsy.

===Criticisms:===
https://www.giantbomb.com/a/uploads/original/2/25966/2362590-11932_122303_006_super.jpg https://www.giantbomb.com/a/uploads/original/1/15035/705190-ngage.gif * The battery had to be removed to switch games.
* The speaker and microphone was on the side of the phone. To make calls you had to hold the phone up to your head like a taco. This led to the internet meme of people "sidetalking".
* The screen orientation was unusual for a gaming system (vertical instead of horizontal).

==N-Gage QD==
The N-Gage QD was released six months after the original N-Gage, and improved many of the flaws found in the previous device. QD stands for "Quaque Die", which is Latin for "Every Day"

===Differences:===
https://www.giantbomb.com/a/uploads/original/1/15035/705191-n_gage_qd_front_1.jpg * New revamped look.
* Games could be switched without removing the battery.
* The earpiece was moved to the front of the device.
* No support for MP3 playback.

==White screen of death==
The N gage QD also had a memory problem known as the white screen of death, the white screen of death became a serious problem with many users as it was easy to get the problem. The problem was that if the internal memory on the phone (3 MB) had been fully used up, then the phone would start using memory from the phones Ram. This meant that the phone would no longer have enough memory to start up the phone or even open the main menu to delete the files taking up the memory. Once this problem occurs if you turn off the N gage then it will no longer work, when turned back on the N gage would show a white screen and stay that way until the phone was switched off, now known as the white screen of death. Another problem with this was that there was and still isn't anyway to fix the N gage after getting the white screen of death, the only known way of fixing is for it to be sent to an official Nokia store.

==N-Gage Arena==
https://www.giantbomb.com/a/uploads/original/1/19490/765403-1online.jpg The N-Gage also fully supported online play with some games, N-Gage arena allowed players to play against other people wherever they were, even with no wi-fi connectivity at all. However N-Gage Arena had problems, such as having to register with your network provider, which was a problem as some networks did not allow N gage Arena despite working on the N-Gage console. Arena also suffered from lag problems and slow down and was sadly never used by many players, meaning that the people who did play on N-Gage Arena could rarely find another player to play with, however Nokia still even today supports N-Gage Arena in some countries (such as UK) and still works just as well as it originally did.
N-Gage Arena was also used in some games as a global high score service. Some games, such as [[Games/Atari_Masterpieces_Vol_1|Atari Masterpieces Vol. 1]] used this service so players could compare their scores with people from all over the world.

==N-Gage today==
https://www.giantbomb.com/a/uploads/original/1/15035/705192-ngage_profile.jpg In 2008 Nokia released a mobile gaming service, under the N-Gage brand. The company dropped the idea of combining cellphones with handheld gaming devices, and chose to make N-gage a part of their Ovi internet services instead. This service is only available on certain Nokia smartphones running the company's S60 software platform, including several Nseries, Eseries and XpressMusic phones. The revamped N-gage service resembles Microsoft's [[Concepts/Xbox_Live|Xbox Live]], with additions like N-Gage points, and gamer profiles.
With the N-Gage platform games are downloaded to the phone, and doesn't support the game cartridges the old N-gage system used. That means there is no backwards compatibility whatsoever. Several first generation N-gage games were ported over to the new platform. It was announced in October 2009 that the service would be shut down by the end of 2010.

==Nokia n85==
Nokia's most recent phone with a capacity comparing to the Android.
n85 Specs:
Dimensions
* Form: Two-way slider
* Volume: 76 cc
* Weight: 128 g
* Dimensions: 103 × 50 × 16.0 mm
Two-way slider with spring assistance mechanism

===Memory===
* microSD memory card slot, hot swappable, max. 32 GB (After firmware update)
* 128 MB internal dynamic memory
* 78 MB internal NAND flash memory

===Data Network===
* HSDPA, maximum speed 3.6 Mbps (DL)
* WCDMA 900/1900/2100, maximum speed PS 384/384 kbps (UL/DL)
* EDGE class B, multislot class 32, maximum speed 296/177.6 kbps (DL/UL)
* GPRS class A, multislot class 32, maximum speed 107/64.2 kbps (DL/UL)
* HSCSD, maximum speed 43.2 kbit/s
* CSD
* WLAN 802.11b, 802.11g * WLAN Security: WPA2-Enterprise, WPA2-Personal, WPA-Enterprise, WPA-Personal, WEP
* WLAN Quality of Service: WMM, U-APSD
* WLAN wizard
* TCP/IP support
* Capability to serve as data modem

===Display and User Interface===
* Size: 2.6"
* Resolution: 320 × 240 pixels (QVGA)
* Up to 16.7 million colours
* Active Matrix OLED technology

===Power Management===
* BL-5K 1200 mAh Li-Ion battery
* ACP-12U 5.7V 800mA AC adapter
* Talk time (maximum): * GSM 6.9 h
* WCDMA 4.5 h
* VoIP 6 h
* Standby time (maximum): * GSM 363 h
* WCDMA 363 h
* WLAN 172 h
* Browsing time with packet data (maximum): 5 h 42 min
* Video playback time (maximum): 7 h
* Video recording time (maximum): 2 h 54 min
* Video call time (maximum): 2 h 42 min
* Gaming time (maximum): 7 h

===Operating Frequency===
* Quad-band EGSM 850/900/1800/1900
* WCDMA 2100/1900/850 (in the Americas) and 2100/1900/900 (everywhere else)
* Automatic switching between WCDMA/GSM bands
* Flight mode

===Connectivity===
* Bluetooth version 2.0 with Enhanced Data Rate.
* Bluetooth profiles: * Dial Up Networking Profile (Gateway)
* Object Push Profile (Server and Client)
* File Transfer Profile (Server)
* Hands Free Profile (Audio Gateway)
* Headset Profile (Audio Gateway)
* Basic Imaging Profile (Image Push Responder and Initiator)
* Remote SIM Access Profile (Server)
* Device Identification Profile
* Phone Book Access Profile (Server)
* Stereo Audio Streaming:
* Generic Audio/Video Distribution Profile
* Audio/Video Remote Control Profile (A/V Remote Control Target)
* Advanced Audio Distribution Profile (Audio Source)
* Add-on solutions enable integration into enterprise private branch exchange (PBX) infrastructure
* DLNA (Digital Living Network Alliance) certification
* UPnP support
* MTP (Mobile Transfer Protocol) support
* TV out (PAL) with Nokia Video Connectivity Cable (CA-75U, in box inclusion may vary based on sales package configuration)
* Nokia XpressPrint
* Support for local and remote SyncML synchronization</text>
      <sha1>irr59misa3xvtibsu6xwij7m1hpdm7j</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>Platforms/Neo Geo</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>456598</id>
    <revision>
      <id>797161</id>
      <parentid>752578</parentid>
      <timestamp>2026-03-21T00:01:25Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Frobie</username>
        <id>300</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>Undo revision [[Special:Diff/752578|752578]] by [[Special:Contributions/Giantbomb|Giantbomb]] ([[User talk:Giantbomb|talk]])</comment>
      <origin>797161</origin>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text bytes="18227" sha1="ho19ooyh62q9qw5hkm4aftqarxeewb4" xml:space="preserve">{{Platform
|Name=Neo Geo
|Guid=3045-25
|Aliases=AES,MVS,NEO
|Image=https://www.giantbomb.com/a/uploads/scale_super/1/13362/613868-neo_20geo.jpg
|Deck=The Neo Geo was a console released by SNK in 1990, featuring a 16/32-bit 68000 CPU with an additional 8-bit Z80 CPU and custom 24-bit GPU chipset. An arcade-based console considerably powerful for a home system at the time, the Neo Geo was notoriously expensive (costing $650 at launch) and aggressively marketed as an Advanced Entertainment System (AES).
|ShortName=NEO
|ReleaseDate=1990-04-26
|InstallBase=1,180,000
|OnlineSupport=No
|OriginalPrice=649.99
|Manufacturer=Companies/SNK
}}


==Overview==
https://www.giantbomb.com/a/uploads/original/4/48409/1652435-neo_geo_hotdog.jpg The Neo Geo AES was born out of [[Companies/SNK|SNK]]'s decision to expand its business beyond [[Platforms/Arcade|arcade]]games and third-party software, and enter the lucrative 16-bit console market. It decided to differentiate the Neo Geo from its competitors by bringing arcade-quality graphics into living rooms. Marketing was heavily geared towards making it a gaming connoisseur's console, and it was even couched as a 24-bit system.
The Neo Geo used a Motorola 68000, a hybrid 16/32-bit CPU, along with the Zilog Z80, an 8-bit CPU, much like [[Companies/Sega|Sega]]'s [[Platforms/Genesis|Mega Drive/Genesis]] console. The difference in bits was that the Neo Geo had a 24-bit GPU chipset, hence the "24-bit" marketing label (much like how the [[Platforms/TurboGrafx_16|TurboGrafx-16]] was labelled "16-bit" because of its 16-bit GPU chipset).
Much of the Neo Geo's advanced graphical capabilities, however, came from the use of custom GPU graphics processors, both within the system as well as additional chips on individual game cartridges, much like an arcade machine. The Neo Geo featured up to seven specialized processors, including the two CPU processors and several graphics chips. And while the RAM was not very large, it could access larger ROM data directly from cartridges at high speeds. These features made the Neo Geo the most powerful home gaming system at the time of its release in 1990, rivalled only by the [[Platforms/Sharp_X68000|Sharp X68000]] home [[Platforms/PC|computer]] (which also used custom GPU graphics processors). Another new feature of the Neo Geo was the use of removable memory cards to save data; it was the first console to have such a feature.
It is the longest supported home platform, having its first game game released in 1990 and the last game, [[Games/Samurai_Shodown_V_Special|Samurai Shodown V Special]], released in 2004.

==Multi Video System==
https://www.giantbomb.com/a/uploads/original/12/121177/1675337-ikyjo_dscn3310.jpg The MVS (Multi Video System) was a fantastic innovation for the arcade industry. It allowed arcade operators to save on much-needed space by having a single cabinet have multiple games. The MVS came in two, four, and six slot systems; these would allow gamers to pick which game they wanted at the title screen. The control options were the same as the AES four-button system, the only difference being the controls were mounted to cabinet. A key difference between MVS and AES were the cartridges: a MVS cart will not work in an AES, and vice-versa. The goal behind this incompatibility was to deter arcade operators from buying the cheaper AES cartridges. The MVS carts from did not come with colorful artwork or plastic boxes like their home counterparts; they would often come in plain cardboard boxes with only a marquee slip or flyer.
https://www.giantbomb.com/a/uploads/original/12/121177/1676408-japanese_arcade.jpg Candy Cabs are Japanese sit down cabinets that SNK used for their MVS machines inside Japanese arcades. These machines are typically smaller and lighter than there American counterparts, some weighing as little as 175 lbs (80 kg). This style of cabinet is normally lined in long uniform rows allowing for each person to have their own screen and controls. Vs play is achieved with either vs cabinets in older machines, or newer networking cabinets.
https://www.giantbomb.com/a/uploads/original/12/121177/1693940-14022801.jpg In North America Neo Geo games were normally housed in red stand-up cabinets branded with the Neo Geo logo. Becuse by design the MVS had multiple games running on it at one time, the cabinets would rarely have game artwork featured on the side. The North American MVS cabinets supported headphones and a memory card, something that made the MVS unique.
https://www.giantbomb.com/a/uploads/original/12/121177/1694390-251892859_efabd10364.jpg The North American Neo Geo cabinets have a 4 button layout labeled with the first four letters of the alphabet. The buttons were always colored the same, A being red, B yellow, C green, and D blue. These were the official colors of the Neo Geo buttons, and would appear this way when presented in game. The control panel itself has a red background with white diagonal stripes coming from both corners, meeting in the middle with a Neo Geo logo. The North American cabinets would normally have HAPP brand buttons, and a bat-top joystick.

==Advanced Entertainment System==
https://www.giantbomb.com/a/uploads/original/12/121177/1675120-neo_geo_games.jpg AES (Advanced Entertainment System) is the term used for describing the home platform of the Neo Geo system, as opposed to the arcade or MVS (Multi Video system) version. The term has since become slang to describe AES cartridges themselves, However the proper name for a AES Neo Geo game is NGH. The way to tell an NGH cartridge from its arcade counterpart is the large colorful artwork featured on the home carts. Arcade cartridges had no branding or consumer packaging because they were hidden inside the machines.
Before the AES was made commercially available it was only sold to larger video rental stores who would in turn rent the system out. This was an unusual practice for a video game platform, and was speculated that this was SNK testing the waters for mass consumption.

==Neo Geo Memory Card==
https://www.giantbomb.com/a/uploads/original/12/121177/1696917-2046880692_2a897278f8.jpg The Neo Geo system was the first platform to use a removable memory card. The Neo Geo memory card was primarily used to continue from where you left off in an arcade game. The Memory card was also cross-compatible with the AES and would allow you to start a game at home and continue in the arcade, or vice versa.

==AES Launch Library==
https://www.giantbomb.com/a/uploads/original/12/121177/1676512-magicianlord__11_.jpg On January 31 1990 in Osaka Japan the Neo Geo AES was made commercially available.The platform launched with nine titles.
* [[Games/Cyber_Lip|Cyber-Lip]]
* Mahjong Kyoretsuden
* [[Games/NAM_1975|NAM-1975]]
* Joy Joy Kid
* [[Games/Riding_Hero|Riding Hero]]
* [[Games/The_Super_Spy|The Super Spy]]
* Top Players Golf
* [[Games/Magician_Lord|Magician Lord]]
* Minasan no Okagesama Desu

==Neo Geo CD==
https://www.giantbomb.com/a/uploads/original/12/121177/1686764-neogeo_cd.jpg Released in 1994, the [[Platforms/Neo_Geo_CD|Neo Geo CD]] was an attempt to compete with CD-based hardware. CDs were also much cheaper to produce than the large NGH cartridges, allowing SNK to sell this platform at a cheaper price point. The Neo Geo CD contained mostly the same hardware, but with a CD drive instead of a cartridge slot.
https://www.giantbomb.com/a/uploads/original/12/121177/1686765-neogeo_cdz.jpg The Neo Geo CD had a significant downside when compared to the AES: load times. Unlike more popular CD systems at the time thie Neo Geo CD only contained a single speed CD drive, this meant that load times on some games, could be between three to five minutes. While for some systems this would be a burden the fact that the platform was almost exclusively made for fast action arcade experienced this became a much more severe problem for SNK. Fighting games for instance would often load between each round, when compared to it's cartridge counterparts this made the games seemed like lesser products.
In 1995 the Neo Geo CD underwent a redesign, and was renamed the Neo Geo CDZ. It had much of the same hardware, but with a dual-speed CD drive and a larger memory cache. This reduced load times for CD-based games. There was only a very limited run of Neo Geo CDZ's in Japan; no North American or European versions were made.

==High Price Point==
https://www.giantbomb.com/a/uploads/original/4/48409/1652434-biggerbadderbetter.gif The Neo Geo AES was a notoriously expensive console, costing $650 at launch. There was little effort to emulate or adapt MVS hardware builds for home entertainment use, so cartridges costed as much as existing arcade cabinets ($100-$300). The console failed to gain market share because of these prohibitive costs, although it gained a cult following amongst its targeted demographic of gaming aficionados. The console lost what market share it had earned among enthusiasts by refusing to innovate or improve the system when its competitors did, especially when it did not make the jump to the 32-bit generation of consoles in the late 90s.
Efforts to make its games more accessible by porting some of the console's exclusives to specialized arcade cabinets enjoyed limited success, but the console could still not compete with its competitors' price cuts and more extensive game libraries. The increased access to the Neo Geo's library did however cement SNK's reputation as a developer of solid fighting games, fueling its success for the rest of the 90's with hits like the [[Franchises/The_King_of_Fighters|King of Fighters]] franchise.
https://www.giantbomb.com/a/uploads/original/0/8153/924841-90_neo_geo_aes_general2.jpg The console itself ceased manufacture in 1997, but games for the console would continue to be made and released in arcades, mainly in [[Locations/Japan|Japan]]. The last game for the console was made in 2004, giving it the second-longest lifespan for an arcade-to-home console.

==Neo Geo Control Options==
https://www.giantbomb.com/a/uploads/original/12/121177/1674824-neo_geo.jpg The Neo Geo AES was a unique system because although an officially-endorsed joypad was available, it was not the standard controller. An arcade stick featuring the same layout as the Neo Geo's MVS counterpart was the pack-in controller used for the system. The controllers used 30 mm arcade buttons and a 35mm ball top joystick.The physical base of the the stick was quite large measuring 280mm x 190mm x 95mm (Width Height Depth), nearly the same size as the system. The joystick has a cult following, with the controller having reproductions made for the [[Platforms/PlayStation_2|PS2]], [[Platforms/PlayStation_3|PS3]] and [[Platforms/Wii|Wii]].
https://www.giantbomb.com/a/uploads/original/12/121177/1675912-neogeo_stick_knob.jpg Although the AES stick has a cult following, it is not without its problems. The buttons on the stick used arcade micro switches but, unlike real arcade buttons, they did not sit inside sleeves. This made it possible for the buttons to rub up against the shell of the stick, this would result in loud squeaking noises or even get stuck underneath the shell. A common aesthetic problem with the AES stick was the joystick ball top getting hairline cracks in the finish, which in extreme cases would cause the ball top to split open. Finally, the button layout on the original Neo Geo was not very ergonomic, a problem which was addressed with the stick's redesign
https://www.giantbomb.com/a/uploads/original/12/121177/1692755-le_rarissime_neo_geo_mahjong_controller.jpg A Mahjong controller was released in 1990 for the Neo Geo AES and is now a rare collectible. It was never released outside of japan because of the lack of interest in Mahjong games outside of the country. It was designed to assist and facilitate the Mahjong games on the AES.
Two joysticks where released by Hori, the first in 1991 and the updated version in 1992. These sticks where considered an upgrade to the officially released SNK sticks because they used superior components and an ergonomic layout. The Hori joystick also featured a turbo function.

==Success on Other Consoles and Modern Ports==
https://www.giantbomb.com/a/uploads/original/0/8153/924842-snes_sn101.jpg SNK ported the console's most popular games to other home consoles, and established a joint venture with publisher [[Companies/TAKARA_Co_Ltd|Takara]]. The likes of [[Franchises/Samurai_Shodown|Samurai Shodown]], [[Franchises/Fatal_Fury|Fatal Fury]], and [[Franchises/Art_of_Fighting|Art of Fighting]] were made available for the [[Platforms/Sharp_X68000|Sharp X68000]], [[Platforms/Genesis|Sega Genesis]], [[Platforms/Sega_CD|Sega CD]], [[Platforms/Saturn|Sega Saturn]], [[Platforms/Super_Nintendo_Entertainment_System|Super Nintendo]], [[Platforms/Game_Boy|Game Boy]], [[Platforms/Game_Gear|Game Gear]], [[Platforms/3DO|3DO]], and [[Platforms/PlayStation|Sony Playstation]].
There is emulation support for the console's games on the [[Platforms/Wii|Nintendo Wii's]] [[Concepts/Virtual_Console|Virtual Console]], and Neo Geo games are available on [[Platforms/PlayStation_Network_PS3|Playstation Network]] for the [[Platforms/PlayStation_3|PS3]] and [[Platforms/PlayStation_Portable|PSP]]. [[Companies/GameTap|Game Tap]] Subscription Service has Neo Geo emulation support.

==AES as a Collectible==
https://www.giantbomb.com/a/uploads/original/12/121177/1676499-neo_geo_logo.png The Neo Geo AES is a popular collector's item because of the system's quality, rarity, and durability over time. The system's high price point at launch coupled with the fact that games could be hundreds of dollars new meant that most people's libraries of games stayed small. This lead to obscure or popular games becoming more valuable and difficult to track down. For example, the popular AES game [[Games/Metal_Slug_Super_Vehicle_001|Metal Slug]] regularly sells at auctions for eight hundred to two thousand US dollars. The prices of these games have lead some collectors to modify their AES systems to play significantly cheaper MVS cartridges.

==SNK's Insolvency==
https://www.giantbomb.com/a/uploads/original/0/3161/240588-snk.png SNK went insolvent in 2000, and attributed this to the rampant piracy on the Neo Geo. It was then acquired by the Korean company Playmore, and rebranded as [[Companies/SNK|SNK Playmore]].

==Hardware Specifications==

===CPU (Central Processing Unit) processors===
* Main CPU processor: [[Companies/Toshiba_Corporation|Toshiba]] 68HC000 (based on 16/32-bit Motorola 68000) @ 12 MHz * Performance: 2.1 MIPS (Million Instructions Per Second)
* Additional CPU co-processor: Zilog Z80 (8/16-bit) @ 4 MHz * Performance: 580,000 IPS (Instructions Per Second)

===Graphics===
* Graphics pipeline: PRO chipset (1st gen), LSPC2-A2 &amp;amp; NEO-B1 (2nd gen), NEO-GRZ (last gen)
* Main GPU (Graphics Processing Unit) processors: * 1st Generation PRO chipset: * PRO-A0
* PRO-B0 (palette arbiter)
* PRO-CT0 (graphics serializer, sprite graphics multiplexer)
* LSPC2-A0
* 2nd Generation chipset: * LSPC2-A2
* NEO-B1 (sprite &amp;amp;amp;amp; tiletset multiplexer, line buffer, palette arbiter)
* Last Generation chipset: NEO-GRZ (all-in-one GPU)
* Additional GPU processors on board: * NEO-G0 (palette data buffer)
* PRO-C0 (palette arbiter, line buffer)
* NEO-I0 (graphics memory address latch)
* NEO-273 / NEO-CMC (graphics memory multiplexer &amp;amp;amp; bankswitching)
* NEO-ZMC2 (sprite tile serializer)
* [[Companies/Sony_Corporation|Sony]] CXA1145 (RGB encoder)
* Additional GPU processors on cartridges: * LSPC2-A2, NEO-B1, PRO-C0, NEO-GRC2-F, NEO-GRZ, NEO-CMC
* Color palette: 65,536 (16-bit color) * Colors on screen: 8,192 (13-bit color) (8 KB on-screen palette RAM)
* [[Concepts/Sprite|Sprites]](tiles) on screen: 381 hardware sprites (without sprite multiplexing) * Sprite/Tile sizes: 16x16 to 16x512 pixels
* Sprites/Tiles per line: 96
* Texels per line: 1536
* Display resolution: 320 x 224 pixels
* Aspect ratio: Standard (4:3)
* Hardware features: [[Concepts/Side_Scrolling|Side-scrolling]], [[Concepts/Vertical_Scrolling|vertical scrolling]], [[Concepts/Sprite_Scaling|sprite-scaling]]
* Layers/Planes: * 1 hardware (non-scrolling)
* Up to 3 scrolling (requires 128 sprites per plane)
* Possible A/V outputs: RF, Composite, Component (RGB)

===Sound===
* Sound CPU: Zilog Z80 (8-bit) co-processor is used to control sound
* Main sound chip: Yamaha YM2610 (15 channel) @ 8 MHz * 4 channel FM (Frequency Modulation) synthesis, 4 operators per channel
* 3 PSG (Programmable Sound Generator) / SSG (Software Sound Generator) channels
* 7 channel 4-bit ADPCM (Adaptive Differential PCM), six at 18.5 KHz and one up to 55.5 KHz
* 1 programmable noise channel for voices
* 2 interval timers
* LFO (Low Frequency Oscillator)
* Sample rate: 24 KHz (FM), 18.5 - 55.5 KHz (PCM)
* Sound output: Stereo
* DAC (Digital-to-Analog Converter) sound chip: Yamaha YM3016

===Memory===
'''RAM (Random-Access Memory)'''
* Main RAM (Random Access Memory) * Neo Geo: 74 KB (including 64 KB work RAM)
* [[Platforms/Neo_Geo_CD|Neo Geo CD]]: 2 MB
* Video RAM (VRAM) * Neo Geo: 84 KB * Main VRAM: 64 KB (including 8 KB on-screen palette RAM)
* Fast VRAM: 4 KB
* Palette memory: 16 KB
* Neo Geo CD: 4.625 MB
* Sound RAM * Neo Geo: 2 KB (from Z80)
* Neo Geo CD: 1088 KB (including 64 KB for Z80)
* Internal save RAM: 64 KB
* Memory cards: 2 KB RAM each (official), up to 16 KB each (custom)
'''ROM (Read-Only Memory)'''
* ROM (Read-Only Memory) on board: * [[Companies/Toshiba_Corporation|Toshiba]] (SP-S2 / SP-E) BIOS ROM: 128 KB
* Toshiba LO (Lookup) ROM: 64 KB
* Sound ROM: 128 KB
* [[Companies/NEC_Home_Electronics_Ltd|NEC]] SM1 sound driver ROM: 64 KB
* NEC SFIX graphics ROM for default fix layer tileset: 128 KB
* Maximum usable Z80 ROM without bankswitching: 62 KB
* Additional ROM on cartridges: * Maximum cartridge ROM without bankswitching: 2 MB
* Additional sound ROM: 512 KB
* Maximum 8-bit ADPCM ROM for audio samples: 32 MB
* 16-bit C ROM graphics memory for sprite tiles: Variable
* Maximum sprite tileset: 128 MB

==External links==
[http:/wiki.neogeodev.org NeoGeo Development Wiki], for more technical details on hardware.</text>
      <sha1>ho19ooyh62q9qw5hkm4aftqarxeewb4</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
